<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The visions of Pasquin, or, A character of the Roman court, religion and practices together with an account of the arts of the Pope's nephews to get money, the tricks of the priests to fill the churches coffers by masses for the dead, the policy of the Jesuites to cully princes, and cheat Christendom, as also an exact description of purgatory and hell, in a dialogue between Pasquin and Marsorio, translated out of Italian.</title>
            <title>Pasquillus ecstaticus. English</title>
            <author>Curione, Celio Secondo, 1503-1569.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 256 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 37 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A35445</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C7622A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R13924</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11914916</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11914916</idno>
            <idno type="VID">50939</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A35445)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 50939)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 813:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The visions of Pasquin, or, A character of the Roman court, religion and practices together with an account of the arts of the Pope's nephews to get money, the tricks of the priests to fill the churches coffers by masses for the dead, the policy of the Jesuites to cully princes, and cheat Christendom, as also an exact description of purgatory and hell, in a dialogue between Pasquin and Marsorio, translated out of Italian.</title>
                  <title>Pasquillus ecstaticus. English</title>
                  <author>Curione, Celio Secondo, 1503-1569.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 64 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed, and are to be sold by Richard Baldwin ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Curione, Celio Secondo. cf. NUC pre-1956.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Anti-Catholicism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Brian Matzke</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Brian Matzke</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:50939:1"/>
            <p>THE VISIONS OF PASQUIN, OR, A CHARACTER OF THE <hi>Roman</hi> Court, Religion and Practices; Together with an Account of The Arts of the <hi>Popes Nephews</hi> to get Money, The Tricks of the <hi>Prieſts</hi> to fill the Churches Coffers by Maſſes for the Dead, The Policy of the <hi>Jeſuites</hi> to Cully <hi>Princes,</hi> and Cheat <hi>Chriſtendom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AS ALSO An Exact Deſcription of <hi>Purgatory</hi> and <hi>Hell.</hi> In a Dialogue between <hi>Paſquin</hi> and <hi>Marforio,</hi> Tran ſlated out of <hi>Italian.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>—Ridentem dicere verum</l>
               <l>Quis vetat?—</l>
            </q>
            <p>Licenſed, <hi>Feb.</hi> 9. 1689.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed, and are to be Sold by <hi>Richard Baldwin</hi> near the <hi>Black Bull</hi> in the <hi>Old-Bailey.</hi> 1689.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:50939:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:50939:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>THE Vices of the <hi>Roman Court</hi> have been ſo notorious, the Pride of their <hi>Popes,</hi> the Ambition of their <hi>Prelates,</hi> the Covetouſneſs of the <hi>Nephews,</hi> and the Hypocriſy of their <hi>Monaſtick Orders</hi> (not to inſtance in their Luſts, and Brutalities) have been, and ſtill are ſo viſible to the World, that in their own Country <hi>Italy,</hi> under the awe of the <hi>Inquiſition,</hi> and within the immediate reach of his <hi>Holineſſe's</hi> Catchpoles (the <hi>Sbirri</hi>) there have been found ſome men of Courage, and Honeſty, who have dared to pull off the mask, and expoſe their pretended ſanctity, and let the World ſee, that no men have erred more groſly, than the bold pretenders to Infallibility; no men are more ſlaves to the World, its Pomps and Vanities, than thoſe who have vowed to forſake them; and no mens minds are ſo eager<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſet upon hoarding up wealth for their ravenous kindred, as thoſe who ſay in Hypocriſy, what St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſaid in truth, <hi>Silver and Gold have I none.</hi> For there are a ſort of Inbabitants of the <hi>Roman</hi> World, who have no Eſtates, and yet have great Revenues; no tillage, and yet abound in corn; no Wives, and yet have more Children to a ſingle mans ſhare, than the <hi>Counteſs of Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> had at a birth.</p>
            <p>It is true, the learned men of the <hi>Reformed Church,</hi> have with much ſtrength of argument, and authority, baffled, and confuted the falſe Doctrines of the <hi>Papal</hi> faction, but perhaps thoſe, who have ſhown their actions in a true light, and made appear, how ſpecious their ſanctity is, and how ridiculous their devotion, dreſſing up their Narratives in a Jocular, and Comical habit, have uſed the more ſucceſsfull method to make the World acquainted with their extravagancies. This courſe the old <hi>Satyriſts</hi> took to expoſe Vice, and in later ages the Copy was tranſcribed by <hi>Orthuinus Gratius,</hi> and <hi>Rabelais,</hi> who gave the World an excellent Picture of the Ignorance, and Luxury of the <hi>Friars;</hi> and of late the Author of the <hi>Cardinaliſmo,</hi> the <hi>Nepotiſmo,</hi> the life of <hi>Donna Olympia,</hi> and the Hiſtory of the <hi>Roman Curteſans</hi> hath ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirably
<pb facs="tcp:50939:3"/>deſcribed the practices of the <hi>men of the Purple,</hi> the ſottiſhneſs of the <hi>Papal Nephews,</hi> the inceſtuous intrigue between even his <hi>Holineſs</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and his Brother's Wife <hi>Olympia,</hi> together with the unlawful, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſterous Indulgences of that Court, that pretends to unſpotted ſanctity: ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other ſuch writings having been ſent into the World, ſome of which have viſited this Country, while others are ſtill confined to their forreign dreſs.</p>
            <p>Such writings are for the moſt part called <hi>Paſquils,</hi> or <hi>Paſquinades,</hi> from the ſtatue of <hi>Paſquin</hi> in the middle of <hi>Rome,</hi> to which they are commonly affixt. It is thought by learned men to be the remains of a ſtatue of one of the old <hi>Gladiators</hi> with his Enemy lying dead at his Feet; and the conjecture is happy, for <hi>Paſquin</hi> is invincible, he triumphs over Princes, and ſubdues all the World, and without the help of Arms or Armies, makes even <hi>Popes</hi> ſtoop and tremble, and executes thoſe <hi>in Effigie,</hi> who by their power reſcue their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons from the puniſhments they deſerve. It hath been often conſulted (and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps in the <hi>Conclave</hi>) to remove this ſtatue, and a certain Prince once reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to throw it into the River <hi>Tyber,</hi> but chang'd his reſolution, when his Servant told him, that it would make a greater noiſe under Water, than while above-ground, and produce a ſpawn of Frogs, whoſe croakings would deafen the City that ſits on ſeven Hills: and what a noiſe then, may we ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, makes he, when his friend <hi>Marforio</hi> attends him, and like ſome <hi>Ecchoes</hi> repeats what he ſays, much louder than it was firſt ſpoken? Such a couple of Companions are enough to laugh. Impudence it ſelf out of countenance, and put the Governeſs of a <hi>Roman Bordelli</hi> to the bluſh.</p>
            <p>Nor is it but requiſite, that thoſe who by their Station, or their Intereſts are above the Laws, ſhould be ſubject to the laſhes of a ſmart wit, as well as to thoſe of their own Conſciences; the Furies within, when they lay on moſt ſeverely, are ſeldom heard by the by-ſtanders, but the World takes notice, how a diſſolute <hi>Grandee</hi> is whipt by a keen and implacable <hi>Satyriſt,</hi> who rubbs off the Paint, and ſhews the deformities, who ſtrips the Actor in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion of his mortified dreſs, and expoſes the Covetouſneſs and Hypocriſy, the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuality and leudneſs, that lodges under the habit of devotion, and by theſe means inſtructs mankind to make a leſs ſhow, and to be more truly, and really pious and honeſt, and not to admire a demure outſide, which covers all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of villanies. For what inclinations can we have to believe that <hi>Pope Pius</hi> who being forbidden to eat Pork, leſt it ſhould throw him into his grave, made anſwer, that he would indulge his appetite <hi>al deſpito di Dio,</hi> in deſpite of God, and his Authority? What incouragement have we to think him juſt, who throwing St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Keys into the <hi>Tyber,</hi> ſaid, that St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Sword ſhould conquer his adverſaries? Who can believe <hi>Alexander the 6th</hi> to have been true to his vow of chaſtity, who proſtituted his own Daughter <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretia?</hi> Or <hi>Leo the 10th</hi> to have had any regard to Religion, who boaſted of the vaſt ſums he had gotten, by the <hi>Fabula de Chriſto,</hi> the fabulous ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts, which the Goſpel gives of our Holy Saviour, as he blaſphemouſly ſtiled the Sacred Scriptures? Who can believer the <hi>Inquiſition</hi> to be the Tribunal of
<pb facs="tcp:50939:3"/>Chriſt, while their proceedings are a demonſtration, that they are the Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutioners of the Kingdom of Darkneſs? Who can think that there is much charity at <hi>Rome,</hi> when the <hi>Papal Nephews</hi> like the <hi>Plant-animal Bora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nez,</hi> eat up, and devour all that comes within their reach? Or that Chaſtity is to be reckoned among the Vertues of that City, in which their <hi>Curteſans</hi> are the Companions of their <hi>mitred men,</hi> and the <hi>Monks</hi> are the notorious practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers of <hi>Maſculine Venery?</hi> While the book of God is lockt up in Libraries, and made a Priſoner under the reſtraint of an unknown Tongue, and thoſe who all their life long, walk in the direct paths to Hell and Deſtruction, hope to enter into the Kingdom of Heaven at the back-door by the help of an <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence,</hi> or a thouſand <hi>Maſſes,</hi> as if every thing were to be bought in the Court of <hi>Chriſt</hi> above, becauſe there is nothing to be had in the Court of his pretended Vicar on Earth without Money.</p>
            <p>But I detain you too long in the Portal, <q rend="margQuotes">the Book it ſelf affords ſignal in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of the inefficaciouſneſs of <hi>Holy-Water,</hi> (which if it could fright De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils, would undoubtedly drive the Prieſts themſelves out of the Church) of the Vanity of <hi>Prayers</hi> to the Dead, and <hi>Maſſes</hi> for the Dead (while the Damned can neither help themſelves nor others, and thoſe in Bliſs, do not hear; and could they be toucht with a ſenſe of our wants, their happineſs would not be complete) that it is no greater wonder, that <hi>Paſquin</hi>'s ſtatue could die, than that a luxurious Fryar ſhould, when he dies be ſaved, ſince to raiſe ſuch a <hi>Bacchus</hi> to the Palace of Bliſs, would require ſuch an Engine, as that whereby <hi>Pope ſixtus Quintus,</hi> (commonly called <hi>Sice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinque</hi>) raiſed the Pyramid; that too many depend ſo much on <hi>Indulgences,</hi> that they believe there is no need of the Blood of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> to make them happy; that in Hell the very Serpents have on their Heads <hi>Fryers</hi> Cowls; that the <hi>Infernal Vatican</hi> is built on as weak a foundation, as that which is at <hi>Rome,</hi> that the <hi>Papal</hi> Grandeur hath no foundation in Scripture, or Primitive Antiquity, but only in the forged <hi>Donation</hi> of <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> and that to make two Heads of the Church, <hi>Chriſt</hi> and the <hi>Pope,</hi> is to make the Church ſuch a Monſter, as the <hi>Imperial Eagle;</hi> that there is a vaſt difference between the habit of the <hi>Virgin Mary</hi> in Heaven, and at <hi>Loretto;</hi> that the <hi>Papal</hi> ſpectacles leſſen true merit, and magnify what is vile and contemptible; that the employments of the ſeveral members of the Kingdom of <hi>Antichriſt</hi> are either wicked or ridiculous; that the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are kept from the people, becauſe they diſcover the Vices of the <hi>Papacy,</hi> and would, if known, incline men to the love of Vertue and Holineſs; that the <hi>Inquiſition</hi> is the greateſt Plague of mankind; and that the <hi>Infernal Court</hi> is more obliged to the <hi>Popes Nephews,</hi> than to all other men, becauſe by their cruelty they cauſe many Thouſands to die in deſpair.</q>
            </p>
            <p>But above all, here you have a Map, and a deſcription of a large Kingdom, over which <hi>Chriſt's Vicar</hi> pretends to a Juriſdiction, while his Maſter had never any ſuch Territory, as <hi>Purgatory;</hi> in it are houſes of entertainment without number, where amidſt many inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences
<pb facs="tcp:50939:4"/>you have much diverſion, and you may purchaſe a licence, while you are on Earth, to live here as merrily as under the protection of the <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tican;</hi> and what makes the habitation the more tolerable, you may get a lodging for a Month or a Year, upon condition that you pay your Rent, as if you were to dwell there for ever; for, beſides Cloſets, and other private Apartments, you may ſteal out by a back-ſtair, when you pleaſe, only the paſſage is ſo nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, that you can carry nothing with you more than the clothes you brought with you into the World; and by this the <hi>Papal Grandeur</hi> is ſupported, for tho your ſufferings are but for a time, the Legacies given for Maſſes for the Souls in <hi>Purgatory,</hi> are the Churches perpetual and unalterable inheritance; happy are the poor then, you will ſay, who are never ſent to <hi>Purgatory,</hi> becauſe they have no Money to purchaſe their redemption, nor are the rich ſo very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy, who may chuſe how little while they will ſtay there, and cannot fail of eaſy Penance both here and hereafter, while <hi>Father Cornelius</hi> is the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor, and <hi>Father Dominic,</hi> by vertue of a peculiar Bull from his <hi>Holineſs,</hi> ſets the term of years, or days, you muſt ſpend there; ſo true is that obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that <q rend="margQuotes">he who would enjoy all the ſenſualities of this World, and die in the aſſurance of eternal happineſs, ſhould chuſe to live in <hi>Italy,</hi> and die in the Communion of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe, and many other ſuch accounts does this Book afford of the extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary qualities of that <hi>Church,</hi> that excluding all others, calls it ſelf <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> and <hi>Infallible,</hi> to which it may be wondred, that our <hi>Bleſſed Saviour</hi> hath not as yet given a Bill of Divorce, while ſhe hath been ſo notoriouſly guilty of frequent proſtitutions, and hath degenerated from the <hi>Church of Chriſt</hi> into the <hi>Synagogue of Satan.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:50939:4"/>
            <head>Paſquin Dead and Revived.</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſq.</speaker>
               <p>VVHat, <hi>Marforius,</hi> do you go away without bidding me farewel, as if we had never ſeen one another before?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Marf.</speaker>
               <p>Who calls me? what voice is that? methinks I ſee <hi>Paſquin</hi> alive in that Statue? but how is that poſſible ſince he is dead? with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt it is ſome Phantaſm, which would make me believe he was alive. I am very ſorry I have no holy water to drive away the Devil.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſq.</speaker>
               <p>Be not afraid, Friend, I am the ſame <hi>Paſquin</hi> who have been ſo long thy acquaintance; and therefore there is no need of holy water to make me fly away; who am moſt miraculouſly come to life again; for no Human Inventions have any force againſt the Decrees of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and I would have thee lay aſide that falſe Opinion that ſo many fools have, who believe that holy water hath virtue in it to drive away Devils. This is but a jeſt, for were it ſo, the Pope's Nephews and other wicked Prieſts would run out of the Churches; for in Hell it ſelf there are not worſe Devils to be found than them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Marf.</speaker>
               <p>But how doſt thou know that? haſt thou been in ſome parts of Hell? O God how I tremble! and the more I look on thee, the more I am frighted.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſq.</speaker>
               <p>Be not ſo terrified, Brother, at the ſight of an old friend; for true friendſhip ought to laſt in the other world. I am not now dead; I am alive again; but if I were dead, as I was lately, what reaſon wouldſt thou have to be afraid of me? the dead neither kill nor ſteal, nor walk in the ſtreet in the night to aſſaſſinate any; they break not open houſes to violate Virgins, nor combine to tranſgreſs the Laws. Whilſt I was in the world I never was afraid of the dead, but often of the living, who were wicked enough not to ſpare the very dead; therefore I would wiſh thee to be of the ſame humour.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Marf.</speaker>
               <p>Well, I will be as you pleaſe, and although I have never kept company with the dead, yet I will now begin to practiſe it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſq.</speaker>
               <p>O take heed of that! for fear thou ſhouldſt run into that great ignorance which ſo many thouſand people are immerged in in this Age, who invoke the dead. Alas! this is but an invention of the Fryers to deceive the world, and to fill their Cloyſter with the Alms that are gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven them, to intercede for the favour of this or the other Saint. I would have thee know that the departed which are in Heaven enjoy ſo great a beatitude, which holds them in ſo continual and holy a contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that they can neither ſee the miſeries, nor hear the ſupplications
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:50939:5"/>of this world; otherwiſe their felicity would not be perfect, which is a thing too wicked to be believed. And the dead who are tormented in the Infernal Pit, ſuffer ſuch acute pains, that they think of nothing but their own ſad infelicities: ſo that to call upon them would be a madneſs; for how can they give help unto others, that are not able to receive any help for themſelves. For this reaſon I exhort thee to be ſure to live well thy ſelf, and concern not thy ſelf ſo much with the dead.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>But muſt I not converſe with thee, ſince thou art returned to me with ſo much favour and kindneſs?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>But I am not dead, I am alive, and my death was rather a mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous Extaſy than any thing elſe, which the Heavens ordained for the confuſion of thoſe who would never believe me whilſt I ſpoke and writ againſt the Vices of the Chriſtian Church.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Tell me, how is it poſſible that thou which art a Stone couldſt take a Soul, and then die, and now riſe again?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>And thou which art a Roman of <hi>Rome,</hi> how canſt thou be aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed at this? it ſhould be a much greater wonder to thee to ſee ſo many lazy Fryers who eat like Swine, and drink like Fiſhes, grow fat in the idleneſs of the Cloyſters, and dare pretend to the enjoyment of Paradiſe. Nay, I know one who eſteems himſelf already very near the coeleſtial glory, who is ſo fat, that I am confident he is much heavier than St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Statue, which ſtands upon St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Church. Nay, this is the leaſt of the wonders; for thou knoweſt, or oughteſt to know, that the Divines in general write that there is nothing to be found in the world to be of equal weight with ſin: Nay, they will have Iron, Braſs, Gold, to be as light as Straw in compariſon of it. Doſt thou not think then that to raiſe from the Earth but one of thoſe good Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous men, Seculars or Regulars (who are loaden with ſuch enormous ſins) it would be neceſſary to frame ſuch a Machine as <hi>Sixtus Quintus</hi> did to raiſe up thoſe great Pyramids to the top of St. <hi>Peters,</hi> where they now ſtand. Briefly, dear Brother, I eſteem the fooliſh belief of ſome Chriſtians an abſolute Miracle, who ſeeing with their own eyes ſo many Prieſts keep Whores behind the Altars where they celebrate Maſs, ſleeping with the Catamites with ſo much liberty, that amongſt the religious, Sodomy is now eſteemed a Virtue, ſtealing the ſacred Veſſels for prophane uſes, treating about Homicides, Whoredoms, Poyſonings, and all manner of frauds in the ſame place where they ſay the Divine Offices, and then to imagine that ſuch Hypocrites can fly to Heaven as eaſie as Birds do from one Tree to another, is a madneſs and a folly in thoſe that can believe it. For my part, dear Brother, I think it would be a leſs Miracle to ſee a Stone flie to Heaven, than one of the wicked Prieſts of this Age.</p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:50939:5"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Thou waſt ever exceedingly learned in the particular vices which reign at <hi>Rome,</hi> and amongſt the Religious, but now thou haſt travelled into more remote Countries, thou muſt have made deeper ſearches. Tell me therefore all thy Hiſtory.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>With all my heart; we will ſit down in this retired corner, and to ſatisfie thee, I will tell thee of my ancient Genealogy. My Father was Born in <hi>Rome</hi> of the noble Family of the Satyriſts, in which he was inſtructed by his Fore-fathers with great accurateneſs till the Age of eighteen years, when he remained an Orphan by the death of his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents; after which he Married a Lady of the Noble Family of the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractours Maledicenti,</hi> with whom he lived twelve years without the hopes of Children. But whether it was by the means of devout Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, or phyſical Medicines, my Mother after that conceived with Child, and I was Born into the world and brought into it with me all the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations and diſpoſitions of thoſe two Families of the <hi>Satyrita</hi>'s and <hi>Maledicenti</hi>'s, which remained ſo boldly in me, they both quickly dying after my Birth, left me ſo very poor that I was forced to ſeek out ſome Art to live by; and ſome adviſed me to be a Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, that I might underſtand by the practiſe of that I might become more skilful in the Affairs of the world, others adviſed me to become a Taylor, aſſuring me, the Sciſſors would be very properly placed in my hands to cut every Body clothes fit to their Backs; but I reſolv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to follow my own inclination ſet up a Barbers Shop, finding in my ſelf ſharp deſires to ſhave off the Beards of ſo many ſlovenly Fryers. At my firſt opening my Shop, whether it was my too much Youth, or too little Experience, or ſome other reaſon my Cuſtom was not ſo great, but I remained many days idle in my Shop, which wakening my Poetical Vein, I fell into making of Verſes, Songs and Madrigals which were ſoft enough, abſolutely degenerating from the name of both my Paternal and Maternal Family, flattering every one ſo much, that though I acquired but little credit, yet a great number flocked into my Shop under a pretence of being ſhaved, yet indeed it was ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to hear me recite my pleaſing compoſitions; ſo that I exerciſed that flattering Art with no ſmall profit for many years. From all An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity Adulation hath been rewarded, till at laſt by the Prayers of ſome ſincere Souls who abominate the Art of flattery, I was Metamor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phos'd into a Stone, that I might remain conſtantly in one place with a free faculty of diſcourſing and making Verſes. As ſoon as I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived this change, and ſevere chaſtiſement, I immediately reſolved to change my method, and to obtain pardon for ſo many faults commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in my way of flattery, I began to correct the Vices of others to demonſtrate my true repentance to ſo great a degree, that this my Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion was in a ſhort time publiſhed throughout all the City, and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:50939:6"/>from all parts thereabouts a mighty affluence of people ran to hear me; whereupon the Learnedeſt people perceiving that no other compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions were honoured like mine; all their works were put out under my name, and that none of their works might be known one from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nothers, they paſſed them all under the Title of <hi>Paſquin</hi>'s, as though it had been unlawful for any but <hi>Paſquin</hi> to compoſe Satyrs and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels. Various accidents occurred unto me at this time; for the Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticks, againſt whom I moſt whetted my Poetry, were ſo incen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to ſee their Errors publiſht by me, procured me often to be thrown into the Fire, that I might be reduced to a Flint Stone, to have removed me out of their ſight, but they were ſtopt in their intentions by a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation, that I had been transformed from a Man into a Speaking-Stone by the will of Heaven, to ſhew the world that the Vices of Men have been obſerved by the very Stones that have neither Life nor Senſes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>I remember by this your diſcourſe that I once heard a very fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Preacher declare in the Pulpit that at the Day of Judgment the very Wood and Stones would ſpeak and publiſh thoſe guilts which had been committed in ſecret.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>'Tis certain without all diſpute, and I wiſh thee to believe it, that the <hi>Paſquinates</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> are the very Image of the Day of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, whilſt the Stone ſpeaks to reprove the Eccleſiaſticks for their many failings. But to come cloſer to our time, I will tell thee, that when the Chair was empty by the death of <hi>Alexander,</hi> the common Exclamations of all <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> concurred, as thou knoweſt very well, to bring in Witneſſes to examine what things were laid to the charge of that Pope. Now I that was very well informed of all the things of the world, had a great deſire to know what was the Opinion of him in Hell and in Heaven; and whilſt I was toſſed about with theſe thoughts, the violent imagination of Death and Hell turned my Brains, like the drunken Saints of the Cloyſters, or whether the Heavens had a mind to give me more Experience in the things of both this and the other world, that I might with more certainty convince the Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticks of their guilt, I fell into an Extaſie, and ſaw what I could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have believed, and was in places ſo different from any in this world, that I could never have imagined I ſhould have returned to ſee thee again in this world.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Tell me then, I pray thee, all that befel thee, for I imagine it muſt needs be very curious, and every Novelty is pleaſant.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>I cannot tell thee, what the ſtroke of death is, but I know very well that I was greatly oppreſſed, and ſomething within me forced my living Soul out of my Body, and ſo I flew immediately into the firſt Regions of the Air, where I found thouſands of millions of Aeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:50939:6"/>Spirits, which buzzed about like Bees flying up and down to ſeek for a Hive; but I paſſed on without any impediment to the ſecond Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, where I was mightily puzzled, not knowing what path to take, and whilſt I was tortured with this confuſion, I ſaw a certain perſon at a great diſtance off, which I took for the Soul of ſome Fryar that was waiting for his Sentence, but I was miſtaken, for he was either an Interpreter, or a guide for Strangers, who having ſeen me afar off, came to me to know what I deſired, and to ſhew me the way. I was extreamly pleaſed to ſee him, and accoſted him with great joy, and he anſwered me with all civilities, and intreated to know my name, which I preſently told him, and prayed him to conduct me, to ſome full inhabited place: Becauſe I was ever uſed to ſee a great number of people; to this my requeſt he anſwered me, there were three ways to take my choice of; one led to Paradice, the ſecond to Purgatory, and the third to Hell.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Is it true then that there is a Purgatory? and yet they—deny it with a Sword in their hands.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>Who ſays they deny it? There is no body purges more than they; for they throw their Sir-reverences in every corner of their City. It is very true that in a Democracy it is impoſſible to ſhut either the Mouth or the Tail of the people, as you ſee in that City, where the civiller the people of high and indifferent Quality are, the more rude and boariſh the <hi>Plebeians</hi> are.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>What reſolution then didſt thou take when that ſtranger offered thee that choice of three ways.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>You may eaſily judge that I prayed him to lead me into Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice, which he moſt willingly did, declaring that it was his moſt par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Office; ſo taking to that path he bid me follow him, and I who knew not where I was, did not only follow him, but took hold of his Girdle to be the more ſecure, we paſſed over then a narrow Bridge, which was ſo exceeding high that it made our hair ſtand an end; after which we met with ſo many great Rocks, Clifts, Ditches and Precipices, that I could hardly believe that this was the way to Paradice, and I fancied we had loſt the right path, but my companion aſſured me we had not; and I was a little better encouraged, becauſe we preſently ſaw a few perſons of each Sex labouring to go on in the ſame hard way, and it was a great pleaſure to ſee how they ſwate and toyl'd to beat the path.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>This is a great ſign that the Faithful muſt ſuffer and labour to obtain the glories promiſed to them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>Very certain! But to tell you the truth, I had the pleaſure to paſs through that ſtrait path at the labour and ſweat of others; in fine after a long Voyage we arrived at the Gates of Paradice, which were
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:50939:7"/>very little and ſtrait: Nay more, there were three doors, every one of them ſtraiter than the other. And at the firſt Gate ſtood two An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, who would minutely know every thing of us, becauſe one was the Examiner, and the other the Secretary; and the Examiners Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice was to know what they could ſay, who pretended to enter into Paradice, and the other read the proceſs of their Life. The Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner then, as ſoon as they ſaw us, asked my Guide who I was, and he having told him that I was a <hi>Roman</hi> (I having in the way diſcovered my ſelf to him) he began to laugh ſo loud that I was pleaſed to ſee him, but when he had left laughing, not being content with the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation he had received from my Conductor, he turned unto me and asked me theſe following queſtions, What is your name? What Countrey-man are you, and whence do you come? What have you done in the other world? What do you come to do in this? What good do you bring hither? What evil have you left there? What way have you paſſed? How many days have you been a coming? Did you come a foot or a horſeback? and an hundred thouſand ſuch queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; but the greateſt concern was, that the Secretary at the ſame time asked me the Articles of my Faith, and an account of what I had done in the other Life, at which demand I was aſtoniſhed, not having thought that in Paradice they had required ſuch an exact information; and he perceiving my amazement, and that I had no Faith to ſhew no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable anſwers he diſmiſſed me with theſe words, What then, you are one of thoſe brave honeſt men, who having lived a long time in ignorance believe they may have the Gates of Paradice open at their pleaſure. I am ſorry Friend that you as well as many others have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived your ſelf, and come hither with the hopes of entring in with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any difficulty, but are afterwards forced to ſeek for an Habitation ſomewhere elſe. Know then that here they look narrowly into the actions of others, and therefore the place is for ſome particular per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and not for all; yet many enter who did not believe they ſhould get in, and many kept out who fancyed themſelves within.</p>
               <p>This whilſt I remembred my ſelf that I had with me, I cannot tell how many Papal Indulgences ſigned with the Popes own Hand, which I took out inſtantly to ſhew him, eſteeming them effectual to facili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate my entrance into the place, but I found my ſelf miſtaken, for one of the Angels had no ſooner perceived that this was a Paſs from the Datory of <hi>Rome,</hi> but he began to cry out, Get ye gone from hence, get ye gone from hence, and ſo turned away his face from me, which I perceiving, immediately threw away my Indulgences, which did ſo pleaſe the Angels that they turned to me and ſaid, All Indulgences were bought and invented by the Clergy only to draw Money out of the people; and that ſince the Popes had begun to be ſo prodigal of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:50939:7"/>their Indulgences, the Monarch of Heaven had given order that the Chains of the Coeleſtial Gates ſhould be doubled, to take away the hope of all thoſe who pretended to gain Heaven by buying ſuch like Indulgences, for God will have his Souls acknowledge the poſſeſſion of the Heavenly Glory to his infinite mercies and goodneſs, and not to the power the Popes have Uſurped in the World.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>'Tis indeed a great enormity, for they ſpeak ſo much of Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences amongſt the Chriſtians, as if Paradice had been made only to be diſpoſed of at their pleaſures, and what is worſe, they ſpeak of Chriſt as if he had not died for our ſins.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>But whatever they think of, or pretend to in Paradice, I am ſure that if the Souls which are in the other world could riſe again, the firſt thing they would drive out of the world would be the Popes, becauſe they occaſion the Damnation of many, and the Salvation of none.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Didſt thou ſtay a long time with theſe two Angels at the Gates of Paradice?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>Above two hours, nay, If I ſhould ſay three I ſhould not Lie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>In that time if thou didſt not ſee other Souls come in at that place there muſt needs be other Gates to come in at.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>No, there is no other Gate to enter in at, nor any one that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared there all the while I ſtay'd.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>That's impoſſible, ſince they commonly ſay that Souls fly into Heaven by thouſands and thouſands.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>Theſe are the Doctrines of the Prieſts, which Lie like the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, and fell abundance of theſe Fuz-balls by Owl-light to deceive I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diots, for no body elſe can poſſibly give credit to them, nay, I had been cozen'd my ſelf to ſuch a degree, that I thought Souls had gone into Heaven in as great crowds as they go to receive the Jubile from the Pope; but now ſeeing that for two hours there was no concourſe of Souls at all. I begged of the Angel to tell me the reaſon of it, who told me that it proceeded from the too much Faith which the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans gave to the Popes; ſome being loſt by believing nothing at all, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers by believing every thing, and gave me a reaſon for it, from the Seven Trumpets which St. <hi>John</hi> Records in the <hi>Apocalypſe</hi> which muſt have done ſounding before the end of the world; that Six of them were paſt in the time of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> which was about the 5000 year of the world, and therefore the laſt by the ſame computation ſhould have been ended before now becauſe it is 1600 years, yet the Trumpet had not done ſounding by reaſon the empty places are not yet filled up. I then beſeeched him again to tell me why they were ſo long a filling up, and he replyed, that there was no likelihood that they ſhould be filled up whilſt the Popes turned them out of the right way: And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:50939:8"/>
                  <hi>Marforius,</hi> I would have thee know, that till that time that the Papacy was introduced into the Church, Souls flocked into Heaven, and the Heavens ſtood open to them: But ſince that was brought in, and the Romiſh Biſhops began to ingrandize themſelves above all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and to proclaim that it belonged to them to open and ſhut Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice; the Heavens grew angry, and have ſhut up their Gates ſo againſt them, that there is no hopes of getting in without being at enmity with the Popes; ſo that I fancy the world is to remain more than ſix thouſand years more, if but one Soul only in two hours can get into Heaven.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>But why were not the Gates then preſently open to thee, which waſt ever ſuch an enemy to the Popes?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>'Twas enough for me to be ſo near: Beſides, there is ſomething more required than that.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>What didſt thou do then when thou waſt excluded out of that place? what way tookeſt thou?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>I begged that they would at leaſt permit me to go viſit the Popes, becauſe I was a Roman Citizen; but both the Angels anſwered me, there was no Popes had entred in there by the eſtabliſhed Decree of the Eternal Father, ſince the 800 year after the Incarnation of his Son; <hi>i. e.</hi> ſince the corruptions of Popery crept into the world, to avoid all Idolatry, leſt thoſe who had been ſuch fools to have been induced by the temptations of the wicked Prieſts, to adore the Pope upon Earth, ſhould be in danger of ſhewing themſelves ſuch ſotts as to worſhip them in Heaven: This was the anſwer that both the Angels made me; but one of them after ſpoke more clearly to me, ſaying, I know very well by this your Queſtion, that you are a Roman Pilgrim, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bibed with that perverſe Doctrine which they teach in <hi>Rome,</hi> where 'tis believed that all the Popes as ſoon as they die mount ſtraight to Heaven.</p>
               <p>But rid your ſelf, O Pilgrims! from this vain deceit, and know, that the Popes of the <hi>Vatican</hi> are incompatible with the Citizens of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. Be content with this one example I will give you for all; that if <hi>Lucifer</hi> fell from Heaven into ſuch a great Abyſs for but once deſiring to be like unto God, without being able to recover himſelf; how much more difficult would it be for the Popes to continue in Heaven, who make themſelves ſuperiour unto God? for <hi>Lucifer</hi>'s ſin was much leſs that ſinned only by intention, whereas the Pope's ſin is actual. I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained ſtill more aſtoniſhed than ever, and with humble prayers ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicated the Angel that he would be pleaſed at leaſt to inſtruct me what path I might take to go to that place where they were, when he without anſwering me a word whiſpered to him that was with me, whereupon he bid me immediately follow him, and we two walked on towards certain obſcure and ſolitary places, full of ſo many Clifts
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:50939:8"/>and horrid Rocks, that for my part I eſteemed it Hell, and the rather, becauſe I ſaw round about the Rocks a great quantity of Serpents, the moſt part of which had Fryers habits upon their backs; and now I began to lay aſide my thoughts and deſires of travelling on further, when my Comrade told me that there was no going back; for that way had a ſingular propriety to permit one to go forward, but never to return back; and he added, perhaps to comfort me, that the Popes had a particular place, which was neither Hell nor Paradice, but only a a Demy-hell: And whilſt he told me this, Lo a great Caſtle pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented it ſelf to my eyes, not above two miles off, but ſo ſpacious, that it was able to receive a million of Souls. Behold, ſays my Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rade, there is Vatican of the deceaſed Popes. I marvelled at two things in it; firſt, at the immenſe height and vaſtneſs of the Tower; and ſecondly, to ſee ſuch a Fabrick ſupported by a foundation ſo weak, that none imagine it could uphold it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>What doſt thou tell me? How can this be? and what were theſe feeble foundations?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>Of Meddals, of Fryers Cowls, of Monks Hats, Cenſers, Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plines, Hair-cloths, Chains, knotted Cords, Images Caps of a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand colours, Sandals, Clogs, Shoes, Pontifical Mitres, Nuns Veils, red and green Hats, Girdles, Ropes, Saints Reliques, Bulls, Candles, Breviaries, Books of Divinity, Herbs, Pulſe, Paſts, and ſuch like things, which were all plaiſtered together with Clay and Lime; and this was the baſis of the whole foundation of that vaſt Machine, that it was no ſmall pleaſure for me to ſee it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>There is no doubt then but this fabrick muſt fall into ruine, there being ſo great a diſproportion between its weights and its foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>I believe ſo: and now being come near to the Walls of this Palace, we found them built well enough, and upon the top of it ſtood four Statues, which were the Images of Hypocriſie, Superſtition, Pride and Ignorance: the two ſides of the Gate were engraved, one with the Copy of <hi>Conſtantines</hi> Donation, with a particular inſcription ſignifying that the Original was in their hands; the other ſide with ſome Tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phies of thoſe firſt Popes, who by degrees had brought Kings and Emperors under their feet. I ſate down to laugh when I ſaw the Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures of ſome Emperors engraven there, with their breeches in the Air, and their faces on the ground, kiſſing the feet of ſome of their Popes; and there were alſo other Sculptures, ſo obſcure and ambiguous, I could not underſtand them. Now, whilſt I was obſerving theſe things, my Guide was knocking at the Gate, but none anſwering him, he knocked the ſecond time, and perceiving ſtill that no body came towards the door, he began to knock in great fury that they made him wait ſo
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:50939:9"/>long: but I, who knew very well the nature of the Popes, that very late, if ever, give Audiences, was not ſcandalized at this delay. Yet my Guide, who was impatient to endure it, told me, that upon this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, he would believe henceforward that the Popes were of a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent temper from Chriſt, who had ſaid, <hi>Knock, and it ſhall be opened to you:</hi> Whereas the Popes, the harder one knocked, the faſter they ſhut the doors; to which I anſwered him, that Chriſt had ſaid theſe words to his Sheep, and the Popes ſpoke them only to their own Nephews, at whoſe firſt knock they ever opened their doors. But at laſt a certain Old man, with a hoarſe voice, came to open the door, but he firſt opened a little window, through which he asked us who we were? my Guide anſwered, that I was a Roman Citizen, that deſire to ſee thoſe holy Mountains: The Old man anſwered, That I muſt firſt tell him my Name, and my Sir-name. When I told him, he no ſooner heard the name of <hi>Paſquino,</hi> but with a diſcompoſed face, and threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning voice he ſaid to me, Thou art he then, that with ſo many railing Libels and Invectives, perverts the minds of our Proſelytes, to the great damage of our Dominion, drawing men from our ſervice, and counſelling them not to worſhip as we do. Away from this place, for we will not admit in any ſcoffers, detractors, or back-biters. I anſwered him; My profeſſion never was to invent Lyes, but to vindicate the Truth; and I would have peruſed other Arguments in my defence; but the good Old man, at the ſound of that word of Truth, preſently withdrew, and ſhut the window, without ſaying another word; which made me remember that paſſage of <hi>Pilate,</hi> who having asked, <hi>Quid eſt Veritas? i.e.</hi> What is Truth? never ſtayed for an anſwer, but imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately <hi>exivit foras,</hi> went out: From whence I concluded with my ſelf, that it is the Property of the Popes to avoid the Truth; and then turning to my Comrade, I told him, laughing, that there was certainly in that <hi>Vatican</hi> many things fit to be ſcorned and derided; becauſe they would let no body in that was capable to note and obſerve them. Nevertheleſs, being much troubled that I could not enter in, I asked my Guide, what we ſhould do not to loſe our time and our labour? he anſwered then, that he thought it beſt to go round about to ſee if there were not ſome other Gate in the cuſtody of a diſcreeter Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Thus withdrawing ſome ſpaces from the wall to ſecure our ſelves leſt they ſhould chance to ſhoot at us, we went round to ſeek for ſome other entrance, obſerving in this time the ſtructure of that Vaſt Mole. One whole day we continued thus wandring, without ſeeing any thing like a Gate; but towards the Evening we diſcovered ſome certain Caves and Holes, ſtrait, but very deep, through which we thought we might have got an entrance, but it was not poſſible.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>What Holes were theſe? but you did well not to enter through
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:50939:9"/>them, becauſe you had run the hazard of being hanged for Thieves: for the Goſpel tells us, <hi>They that enter not in through the Door are Thieves and Robbers.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>Doſt thou not know that the Popes have reverſed all the holy Scriptures, being reſolved to Act quite contrary to Chriſt: therefore none but Thieves enter into the Popes Palace Doors; and thoſe that entred in by thoſe Holes and Caves were brave men. Now, if thou deſireſt to know what theſe Holes were, I will tell thee what I think of them, and what I have read in ſome old Manuſcripts; they were breaches made by <hi>Marcion, Montanus, Novatian</hi> the Roman, <hi>Sabellius</hi> and <hi>Arrius,</hi> who all ſtrive their utmoſt againſt this Vaſt Mole to deſtroy it. But notwithſtanding they ſought ſeveral Ages, they could never get in, becauſe the Popes ever drive them back. We then ſeeing it would be in vain for us to attempt to enter in by theſe Caves, followed on our way; but night overtaking us, and we being both weary and hungry, we lay down upon the ground upon our backs, and our mouths wide open.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>If any of them had ſhit, you had been in a fine caſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>Where they do not eat, dear Brother, they do not ſh—Indeed, if I had been near the <hi>Roman Vatican,</hi> I had not dared to have ſlept with my mouth open, leſt ſome of the Popes Nephews ſhould have ſquirted into it, ſince they eat till they are ready to burſt. For 'tis certain thoſe Moſt Excellent Nephews have done ſo many villanies and inſolencies againſt the poor Roman Citizens, that perhaps they would have compleated their good actions with ſo much ſtink; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I am reſolved never to truſt them ſo much as to open my mouth in their ſight.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Pray whence comes this, that you lolled with your mouths open?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>To the intent that if any of that party ſhould paſs by us, they might take us for Prieſts, and ſo leave us to our ſelves.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Do the Prelates then in that Country ſleep with their mouths open?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>I know not how they ſleep in thoſe parts, becauſe I have not yet ſeen them: but I know very well, that they are ſo far from ſleeping, that they continually watch for the raining of Manna in the <hi>Vatican</hi> to fill their throats with.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>I thought that the bleſſing of raining Manna had been peculiar to the Jews of the Old Teſtament.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>Thou art deceived, it belongs no leſs to the Jews of the New Teſtament, but with this difference, that the Jews of the Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment had their Manna when they came from the fetters of <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> and the Jews of the New Teſtament when they go in Priſoners into the Popes Chains. But there is another difference more notable, which
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:50939:10"/>is, that thoſe antient Jews were brought by force into <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, but theſe new Jews voluntarily impriſon themſelves in the Popes bonds.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Who are theſe Jews you ſpeak of, and what ſort of Manna is it that rains upon them in <hi>Rome?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>With reverence be it ſpoken unto thee, <hi>Marforius,</hi> thou art a very <hi>Ignoramus;</hi> Doſt thou not know that the Jews of the New Teſtament are the Clergy of <hi>Rome,</hi> who, in imitation of the Antient Jews, who condemned the words of Chriſt, do not only condemn the words, but, the very works, and holy Scriptures of Chriſt, having expreſly for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden the people to read them in any Language, but only that which is paſt their underſtanding? and herein is obvious the great difference between Chriſt and the Popes; ſince that when the Antient Jews would have crowned Chriſt King, he fled from them, refuſing a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom from the hands of the Jews. But the Popes refuſe nothing; but as ſoon as the Eccleſiaſtical Lords preſent them with a Crown, they receive it joyfully. And as for the Manna which rains upon them now, 'tis of a nature infinitely different from that other; for the old Iſraelites loathed the firſt Manna. But this makes the Eccleſiaſticks ſtill more hungry again; that Manna was given to a people almoſt ſtarved, that wanted refreſhment; but this other is never diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſed but to the fatteſt, and the richeſt, and conſequently to ſuch as have leaſt need of it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>But what is this Manna? explain thy ſelf quickly, for my mouth waters.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>Thou mayeſt ſhut thy mouth at thy leiſure, for none of it will rain upon either thee or me: but, ſhall I tell thee what this Manna is? 'tis Prebendaries, Penſions, Canonries, Abbacies, Biſhopricks, Arch-Biſhopricks, Patriarchſhips, and Cardinalſhips, and other ſuch like things. Behold the Roman Manna, which is never given to any poor people, but to the richeſt; as thou very well knoweſt; ſome be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing crammed with them, and others getting nothing at all. And I would alſo have thee know, that this Manna is of that nature, that the more one eats of it, the more he would eat; and the good Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates of this Age are not ſuch fools as the old Jews that deſired to have exchanged their Manna for the Leeks and Garlick of <hi>Egypt:</hi> for our Prelates leave the Onions and Garlick, <hi>i. e.</hi> the labour and pains, to certain poor Curates, whilſt they themſelves enjoy the ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of this Manna, and ever hold their mouths open to gape for more.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>I could wiſh heartily that ſometimes a good Meſs of Broth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cocted in the belly were diſcharged into their mouths to fill them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>We want ſome of theſe Pottages you ſpeak of; for the Prelates are like Dog-graſs, which from one Root produces a thouſand ſhoots.
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:50939:10"/>There are not ſo many Thieves in all <hi>Europe,</hi> as there are Prieſts in <hi>Italy</hi> alone, which ſtand gaping for Manna from the Pope. But now, to return to the thread of our diſcourſe, my Companion and I riſe early the next morning to paſs on in our Journey; we had ſcarce gone two miles when we began to hear a horrible loud noiſe, which frighted us a little, yet hoping to find ſome end of our deſires, we began to walk on; and in a very little time we ſaw one of the Towers of the <hi>Vatican</hi> thrown down to the ground, and abundance of <hi>Swedes, Danes, Germans,</hi> and other Nations climbed up upon it, and made great at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts; in the mean time many <hi>Spaniards</hi> and <hi>Italians</hi> that were with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, endeavoured to repair the breach, yet could not hinder but a great number of people, all goodly perſons, entred in, who couragiouſly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bated to overthrow all the <hi>Vatican.</hi> But the Devils of <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>Italy</hi> oppoſed all their attempts, and ſpoiled all: But when we were come cloſe to this breach, I ſaw a certain French-man, whom I had known in <hi>Rome,</hi> and I asked him, What is this? and he told me, it was a Tower that <hi>Luther</hi> had overthrown, by which breach thoſe Nations had entred in. I had a mind to ſhuffle in amongſt the reſt, but was afraid of paſſing over thoſe Ruines, and the rather, becauſe I ſaw the defence of the contrary part was very great; I turned about to conſult with my Guide, but I could not ſee him, nor know how he was loſt amongſt that crowd of people, which made me the more aſtoniſhed and confuſed, that I knew not what elſe to do but to intreat the French-man not to leave me. And he, continuing his uſual Civility, ſeeing my deſires ſo inclined to go in, bid me follow him, which I willingly did; but going on a little more than a hundred paces from the Tower thrown down by <hi>Luther,</hi> I met with a deep breach which went a great way in; and while I ſtood looking upon it, the French-man told me, I might go in boldly, for that was a breach made by <hi>Calvin,</hi> and enlarged by others: however, I was a while in ſuſpence, but ſoon after, ſeeing a great number of <hi>Engliſh, Hollanders</hi> and <hi>Switzers</hi> go in, and with theſe a great many <hi>French,</hi> and <hi>High Dutch</hi> mingled, I took courage and followed them, and rather becauſe the French-man lent me his hand.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>In fine, you may meet with honeſt men in all places, and this French-man muſt be a brave fellow.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>So he was; and the more, becauſe he never ſhewed himſelf very paſſionate towards this <hi>Vatican,</hi> neither do I believe he would have ſhed many tears if he had ſeen the whole building thrown down: and ſo we entred through the mouth of that Mine, which was much grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than one could have judged it; there being many Bryars and Buſhes which hid it, that the bigneſs of it might not be ſeen, being laid on purpoſe that none might gueſs what it was indeed. But I muſt
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:50939:11"/>tell thee one thing, my dear <hi>Marforius,</hi> which is this, that though I was much tired in this Journey, and wearied with ſo much pains; yet going through this Mine I felt, I cannot tell you what refreſhments, in deſpite of thoſe Thorns which were round about the Entrance, which pricked me now and then on every ſide of my body. In the extremity of the Mine ſtood a perſon with a very lean, yet devout face, who held in his hand a Flag with an Inſcription of one ſide with theſe words, <hi>Poſt Tenebras Lux, i.e.</hi> after Darkneſs comes Light; and of the other ſide, <hi>Venite ad me omnes qui laboratis, &amp; onerati eſtis, &amp; ego reficiam vos, i. e.</hi> Come unto me all that labour and are heavy laden, and I will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh you. As ſoon as I had read theſe two Motto's, I was mightily comforted, and the good man asked me my Name, and my Sir-name: then I ſaid within my ſelf, I am gravelled again, for if this perſon ſhould ſerve me as the other did, I ſhall be ſure to be ſtopt; ſo that I was almoſt reſolved to change my Name, but thinking better of it, I judged it fit to proceed with ſincerity, therefore I anſwered him that my Name was Mr. <hi>Paſquino</hi> a Roman: he ſeemed to be extreamly pleaſed with that anſwer, only adding, that I needed only to have named my ſelf <hi>Paſquino,</hi> becauſe the name of Roman was not well liked here; after that he told me, that none was permitted to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into that place of the ſide that he guarded, till they firſt confeſſed what he himſelf had been forc't to confeſs, and all the reſt of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany; I told him then, that I deſired to be informed what was need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for me to confeſs; and he replied, tell me friend, which of the two doſt thou believe to be Head of the Church, Chriſt or the Pope?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>This was a hard Queſtion; for my part I ſhould have anſwered that they were both Heads.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>That would have been the anſwer of a fooliſh, ignorant and wicked Chriſtian; I wonder thou art not yet inſtructed better in this point. What! thou believeſt the Church hath two Heads as the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror's Eagle. The Eagle of two Heads was the Invention of a Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Poet, and the Church with two Heads was the Invention of the Roman Prieſts.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>I cannot Reaſon ſo finely; I go on in a plainer way: but what didſt thou anſwer him then?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>I confeſs that I believed the Church had only one Head, which was Chriſt; nor would I ever believe there was any other Head, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I would not run into ſuch a diabolical Hereſie: for the having ſo many Heads, and ſo many Bodies are proper to <hi>Cerberus's, Briareus</hi>'s and Devils, and not to coeleſtial creatures; and therefore it was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to believe as I believed, that the Church hath one only Head, and one only Spouſe, and that is Chriſt our Lord; and that all others are Members of the Church, one of which is the Pope. As ſoon as he
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:50939:11"/>heard this, he roſe from his ſeat, and came to embrace me with great tenderneſs, ſaying, Truly thy words ſhew thee to be that pleaſant <hi>Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quin</hi> who I have ſo often heard ſpoken of with infinite praiſe; thou art heartily welcom; and when he had ſaid ſo, he hugged me ſeveral times, and called me his Brother in Chriſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>This title is not ſo common in the Roman <hi>Vatican,</hi> for the Popes give it to none but Cardinals.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>It would be better for the Cardinals if the Pope would leave off calling them Brethren, ſeeing he doth not a little flatten their reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in this world; beſides that he makes them perverſe and wicked in the other.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>How can this be? thou art either too obſcure, or I am too dull to comprehend thee.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>They that come neareſt the Fire are the hotteſt; and they that come neareſt to Clay and Dirt, are the moſt defiled: this is a general Rule in Philoſophy, therefore it muſt needs follow, that thoſe who draw neareſt to evil are the moſt wicked. Now every one knows that the Popes are the fountains of all thoſe evils which the Church hath ſuffered; therefore the Popes calling the Cardinals Brethren, they cannot avoid the reproach of having their part in every miſchief. Moreover, the Popes are like Pitch, which defiles them moſt that roul in it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>What can then be ſaid of Kings which the Pope calls his Sons?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>This alſo is a great Cheat: the Popes believe they have given half the Heavens, and half the Earth to Kings, by giving them the title of Sons; and Kings think they receive the other half of the Earth, and the reſt of Heaven, every time they call the Pope their Father: yet that title ſerves to no purpoſe but to lowre and vilifie Kings in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the Popes, and to render the Pope too proud and high in the preſence of Kings; all the reſt of it is nothing but ſmoke: and tell me the truth, my dear <hi>Marforio,</hi> whether doth the Natural and Divine Law teach a man to love his Children or his Nephews beſt? with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt his Children: but this Rule is not obſerved with the Popes; for they rob all the Treaſure of the Church, and apply to their own occaſions; and when they die, give it all to their Nephews, without leaving any thing to their Sons. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rban</hi> the 8th. <hi>Innocent</hi> the 10th. and <hi>Alexander</hi> the 7th. are great inſtances of this, who left more than ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven millions of Piſtols to their Nephews, and to the poor Emperor oppreſſed with the Turk nothing at all but the title of Son, I would curſe him a hundred times a day to the Devil.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>I beſeech you do not fall into paſſion, but go on with the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe; how did the Careſſes end between you and that honeſt man?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>He perceiving me to be alone, for the French-man was gone
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:50939:12"/>back to his own affairs, promiſed me to be my faithful Companion, and conduct me to ſee all thoſe places. Firſt then, he carried me up a very high Ladder, on the top of which was a Terrace that looked to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Heaven, and when we were there, he bid me look up, and as I looked, I thought I ſaw the Mother of our Lord, ſhining with great glory, but I did not ſee any Pearls, or Jewels, or Gold, or Silver; which amazing me very much, and my new friend perceiving it, asked me what was the cauſe of it? whereupon I anſwered him, that having ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral times ſeen the <hi>Madona</hi> of <hi>Loretto,</hi> loaded with Jewels, and Gold of ineſtimable value, I wondred how ſhe was now deprived of thoſe rich gifts; to which he inſtantly replied, that that Lady of <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retta</hi> was not the Mother of our Lord, but the Mother of the Prieſts; for ſhe not only gives them money enough to buy them food, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to feed their prodigality; neither are we to believe there is any correſpondence betwixt the Mother of Chriſt in Heaven, and that Mother of the Prieſts on Earth; and poſſibly, I replied, the faithful, who give ſuch vaſt Offerings and Alms, believe they put them all into the hands of the Mother of our Lord, and ſhall draw from her the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muneration of graces. Would to God it were ſo, ſaid he immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; but the miſchief is, that the poor <hi>Fideles</hi> impoveriſh themſelves, to enrich the Prieſts; ſo that being ſhamm'd into that falſe belief, they thereby commonly loſe both their Moneys and Rewards.</p>
               <p>I have been fifteen times at <hi>Loretto,</hi> to impetrate ſome bleſſings, which my Curate told me I ſhould undoubtedly obtain, and every time I carried ſome Gift; I ſtill returned with a deſire of attaining that which I thought I ſhould have attained; but that which is moſt material, my Curate ſeeing me ever return empty handed, he told me, it was through defect of my Faith. I durſt anſwer him nothing then, becauſe I was in the other world where the Inquiſition reigns. But I ſaid within my ſelf, It's enough that the Prieſts have ſo much Faith as to take the Gifts, whatever becomes of the reſt. But now I am in a place where Truth is unveiled; I am informed of all thoſe Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors in which ſo many unfortunate poor people are plunged; and 'tis a wonder to ſee how the Chriſtians can imagine that there ſhould be Simony in Heaven, when the Popes have baniſhed it out of the world; 'tis a Diabolical thing not to be forgotten, that the Popes have eſtabliſhed and decreed a moſt ſevere Bull, that under no pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Alms, Donatives or Debts, any one ſhould receive the leaſt thing imaginable out of hope of obtaining any benefits or indulgencies; yet the Chriſtians of <hi>Rome,</hi> deceived, alas! by the Roman Prieſts, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit ſolemn Simony, and indent with Heaven under the name of a Vow; ſome promiſing a pair of ſilver Candleſticks to our Lady of <hi>Loretto,</hi> ſome a Lamp to St <hi>Nicholas</hi> of <hi>Toledo,</hi> ſome a ſilver Statue
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:50939:12"/>to St. <hi>Antony</hi> of <hi>Padua,</hi> ſome this thing, and ſome that thing, to this or that Saint, upon condition of obtaining their requeſt; and in caſe of not obtaining it, the Vow to become null. I know that in the Great Dukes Gallery in <hi>Florence,</hi> they ſhew an Altar-piece of Maſſy Silver, which was made upon the occaſion of a Vow made by the Great Dutcheſs to St. <hi>Charles,</hi> but becauſe the deſired Grace was not obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the Altar remains in the Great Dukes hands, mocking at the Vow, ſince the Saint had mocked at the Offering. This example made me remember another, which I did not fail to relate to my friend. That Roman Lady being barren, whoſe Husband was very deſirous of Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, ſhe recommended her ſelf to the prayers of her Confeſſor, who was a <hi>Theatine</hi> Father, making uſe of all thoſe means that are neceſſary for ſuch a bleſſing. Finally, after two years uſe of prayers made in her own Chamber, the effect of the bleſſing began to appear, there being manifeſt ſigns of her conception; whereupon the Father Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor being greatly pleaſed, and the Lady no leſs, they both poſſeſſed the Husband that it proceeded from a Vow made to the bleſſed <hi>Caje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan;</hi> and thereupon the poor Husband was to make a ſilver Statue, which muſt be preſented by his Wife to the bleſſed <hi>Cajetan:</hi> but the myſtery was, that this Statue muſt be ſolemnly bleſſed by this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor, whilſt the Husband and Wife were kneeling before him with ſo great a Devotion, that all the reſt of the Fathers rejoyced.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Thou wilt make me never credit ſuch like Vows again; but what did your venerable friend ſay to this?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>He fell a laughing, but yet modeſtly; and I in the mean time begged of him to know where were the other Mothers of God; at which he laughed out, and ſaid, What, doſt thou think then that God hath many Mothers, or that there are many Gods? I told him no, I had ever believed one only God, and one Virgin Mother; but that which made me ſpeak, was, that I had heard them at <hi>Rome</hi> diſcourſe of the Mother of God, of the Roſary, of the Mother of God of <hi>Popolo,</hi> of the Mother of God of the <hi>Carmine,</hi> and of ſo many others, that the number of them is infinite. Truly, ſaid he again, the people of <hi>Rome</hi> have great need of that Mother of God of <hi>Loretto,</hi> that ſhe might lend them her Treaſures, to eaſe them from the many inſupportable Exactions which the Popes Nephews have laid upon them. It were better, ſaid I, for the people, to find out ſome kind <hi>Madonna</hi> like her who obtained the Victory againſt the Turks, that by her means they might be once delivered from the Popes Nephews, which are worſe than the Turks. Come, let us leave, ſaid he, all theſe Mothers of God invented by the Prieſts, juſt as the old Poets invented a great number of Deities, and let us go down to ſee the particularities of this <hi>Vatican.</hi> No, I beſeech you, replyed I, have a little patience with
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:50939:13"/>me, and help me firſt to the ſight of the Saints, which are the Senators of Heaven, and the Advocates of the Earth; for I ſee none here, and yet they ſee ſo many in the world. This Queſtion did ſo extreamly diſpleaſe him, that chiding me heartily for ſuch a folly, he proceeded to ſay, For ought I ſee, thou thinkeſt God is grown ſo old, that he hath not ſtrength enough left to govern the world alone, and ſo calls in the Saints to aſſiſt him. I ſeeing him in a rage, endeavoured to pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifie him, profeſſing it had never been my belief, but that I always thought God was the only Ruler of all things, without any help or aſſiſtance; but the Prieſts made the poor Chriſtians believe that God operated nothing at all but through the interceſſions of his Saints; 'tis no news to me, added he then, that the Prieſts joy in the Ignorance of the faithful, and they borrow for lending too much Faith to the Prieſts. 'hoſe who read the ſacred Scripture, have no need to loſe themſelves by the Lectures of the Prieſts.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>He was well acquainted with the Plague which reigns at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent amongſt the Chriſtians in <hi>Europe.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>After this he made me go down, and at the foot of the Ladder he asked me whether I was ſatisfied; to which Queſtion I anſwered, that my Curioſity did but begin to be inflamed, whilſt my Intentions were only ſet upon ſeeing where the Popes lived; therefore the longer I was kept from ſeeing them, the more violently my Curioſity increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; yet the Romans (ſaid he then to me) ought to be glutted with the ſight of the Popes, having perhaps ſeen too many with their eyes, and touched too many with their hands; ſo that methinks they ſhould eſteem it high time to rid themſelves of ſuch Plagues, who infect the very Liberty of Princes, and diſturb the Tranquillity of the People: yet ſince thou haſt ſuch an anxiety ſtill to ſee the Popes, let us go, I will accompany thee not only to ſhew thee the way, but to take care of thee, leſt thou ſhouldſt break thy neck; for uſually near the Papal Habitations, there are great Precipices, which are not ſeen till after one is faln down into them. Thus diſcourſing, we walked on, through a round Gallery, which looked liker the houſe of ſome Magician, than the Palace of the Popes; at the end was a moſt magnificent Hall of a quadrangular form, lofty, and of an admirable ſtructure, but it trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled like a Buſh. I would have ſtopt, apprehending the Machine would have faln down upon my back, and buried me in its ruines, but my Comrade encouraged me, ſaying, there was no danger yet, for the time of the deſtruction of that place was not yet come; invigorated by theſe words, I advanced further on, to ſee whence it could proceed that a Machine that was ſo beautiful, and built with ſuch ſtrong walls, ſhould be liable to ſhake in that manner, as if it had been a little Tree newly planted in the midſt of an open Field</p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:50939:13"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>There muſt needs be ſome myſtery in that, becauſe it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the courſe of nature.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>Thou muſt underſtand that this Hall is upheld by a multitude of Fryers and Prieſts, who kneeling with their hands upon their knees, bare it upon their backs, and they began already to put their hands upon the ground, which made them appear more like beaſts than men. And becauſe it was impoſſible for me to obſerve it without my kneel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, I made no bones of it, to ſatisfie my curioſity; it being very plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant to me to obſerve the poſture of thoſe wretched Fryers; for ſome of them knocked their Noſes to the ground, and others endeavoured to bear themſelves up, and others had a mind to lie flat down, to leave all the weight upon the reſt of their fellows; others curſed thoſe who had planted them to bear up that building. On the back-ſide there was a multitude of perſons heaving with their ſhoulders againſt the Wall of this Hall, ſtriving to throw down this building: but that which imports moſt was, that they did it with ſo great delight and force, that their ſweat ran down all over their faces; being amazed at this, I asked my friend of it, who informed me thus; Thoſe which thou ſeeſt uphold this Fabrick, are the Divines and Doctors of the Roman Church; and becauſe the fatigue is great, they would be willing to be diſcharged of it, but it is impoſſible for them to be freed, being nailed there by their own fault. At firſt they bore it all upon their heads, ſtanding upright; but afterwards being oppreſſed with the extremity of the weight, they bowed down their heads, receiving the weight upon their necks; but thoſe being weakened, they ſhifted it all upon their ſhoulders, whereon they upheld the building a great while, until their ſtrength failed them, and then they bowed down to the Earth, as you ſaw them. Thoſe other who ſtand in a poſture to throw down all this pile into ruine, are the Doctors and Divines of the contrary Religion, who labour ſtoutly for the deſtruction of this Fabrick, and would have done it before now, if it were not for the Aſſiſtance which they often receive from the benignity of Princes. When he had ſaid this, he ſhewed at the four corners of the Hall four Princes, who were ſtretching their wits to prop it up, which was it that kept it upright; for ſtill, as the others endeavoured to overthrow it; theſe ſtaid it with the props which they held in their hands; neither can it be diſcerned which were the readier, the one to maintain it, or the other to throw it down.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>What Princes were theſe who ſo much concerned themſelves for the ſupporting of this place?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>The Emperor, the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> and the King of <hi>Poland</hi> at three corners, and at the fourth many Catholick Princes joyned together as well <hi>Germans</hi> as <hi>Italians:</hi> but yet the greateſt ſupport is that which is given by the Emperor and the King of <hi>Spain.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:50939:14"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>I have ever heard that <hi>France,</hi> and the Republick of <hi>Venice,</hi> have brought a great many props to hold up the <hi>Vatican;</hi> how comes it then that you ſay nothing here of them?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>Softly; you do not give me time to tell all this will come after; but ſince thou art in ſuch haſte to know it. I will tell thee that the King of <hi>France,</hi> and the Republick of <hi>Venice,</hi> defend the <hi>Vatican,</hi> as thou ſayeſt, with Policy, that is to ſay, with moderation: and altho' ſome Ages paſt theſe two Potentates, without conſidering of the infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite charge, and the hazard they put their own States to, ran furiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the defence of the Popes, when they ſaw them oppreſſed either with the ambition of Princes, or the force of Hereſies: yet their principal end was, not to help the Popes to grow ſo proud (being wiſe enough to foreſee that which afterwards came to paſs, whilſt theſe good Popes growing great, not to ſay fat, by the protection of theſe two Monarchies, ſpurned at the obligation, and like Mules kick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at thoſe who brought them their provender) but only to gain themſelves a name of Piety and Zeal towards Religion with the people; ſo that from that time they have gone with leaden heels to the aſſiſtance of the Popes; and I ſee them in this part of the Hall which I have deſcribed to thee, walking up and down with their props in their hands; and I obſerve it is their policy to ſee the place attached, but not conquered; they are pleaſed to ſee it tremble and ſhak'd, but not to be precipitated or caſt down; and therefore they incite the Combatants to fight againſt it; and when they ſee the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory inclining to them, they immediately ſet to their props, not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the heart to ſee the place thrown down.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Now I do not doubt but that place was the habitation of the Popes, thoſe particulars which thou relates ſo clearly manifeſting it, that it would be a groſs ſimplicity to queſtion it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>There is no great wit required to conjecture it; I preſently ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined it before the good man told me any thing of it, and was imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately confirmed in my opinion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Why then did not the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> and thoſe other Princes which ſtrive ſo much to uphold that place, arm themſelves inſtantly to fight againſt the Enemies, it being ever better to ſubdue an Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my before they have had any ſucceſs, than to drive them out again when they have got any footing?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>'Tis certain the Spaniard and the Emperour would have diſturb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the whole world, and turned it up-ſide down, as they have often done with their violent Remedies, if the King of <hi>France</hi> and the <hi>Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian</hi> Republick had not hindred them. But thoſe two great Powers judged the things of Religion according to Policy, and on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary the other Princes judged of matters of Policy according to the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:50939:14"/>Laws of Religion; for the King of <hi>France,</hi> and the Republick of <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice</hi> know very well, that if the Hereticks had not mortified the Pope and his Eccleſiaſticks, the Eccleſiaſticks and the Pope would have been Hereticks againſt the Princes, and therefore they often help the Proteſtants at a pinch, not that they would defend their Religion, but that they might with their Religion mortifie the Popes, and by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence be more humbled to the Catholick Princes. For my part I cannot ſay I ever received ſo much pleaſure in ſo ſhort a time, as when I ſtayed in the out-parts of this Pontificial Seat: for the King of <hi>Spain</hi> and the Emperor who upheld, now and then gave a kick to thoſe Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries that ſought to ſhake it; the King of <hi>France,</hi> and the Repub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick of <hi>Venice,</hi> when they ſaw it, interpoſed, ſo that they put off moſt of the blows.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Doſt thou take this to be well, to protect thoſe who attempt the deſtruction of the Pontificial Majeſty?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>If the Popes ſeek to deſtroy the Majeſty of the Princes, why ſhould not the Princes be permitted to procure the mortification of the Majeſty of the Popes? We muſt diſtinguiſh between mortification and deſtruction; for the <hi>French</hi> and the <hi>Venetians</hi> endeavour only the mortification, but not the deſtruction of the Pontificial Greatneſs, and in truth they much more benefit the Church, than the other Princes do, who would deſtroy the whole world to pleaſe the Pope. But when the concern is for the Church of Chriſt, then the King of <hi>France,</hi> and the Republick of <hi>Venice</hi> are more zealous than the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> who eſteem themſelves ſo Catholical. But on the other ſide, when the Popes In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt is upon the Board, then the <hi>Spaniards</hi> are moſt zealous, and the <hi>French</hi> and the <hi>Venetians,</hi> if they do not ſtand out, are at leaſt content with a natural heat, and upon this account, becauſe the Zeal of the <hi>Spaniards</hi> looks more to the Intereſt of the Pope, than the Intereſt of the Church, and the Zeal of the others regards much more the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of the Church, than that of the Popes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Theſe Reaſons of thine penetrate my heart, and make me think the <hi>Spaniards</hi> great Catholicks for the Popes, and great Hereticks to the Church, and the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Venetians</hi> great Catholicks for the Church, and a little Heretical towards the Popes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>Very right: But now to return to our purpoſe, after I had ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved all things without, my curioſity went on to ſee every thing within, but I durſt not do it, though a Gate preſented it ſelf juſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore my eyes, where was an aſcent of three or four ſteps: but I waited to have the venerable perſon, who conducted me, to ſhew me the way, which he did, by going in firſt without much ceremony. As ſoon as we entred that Great Hall, we ſaw a multitude of Popes, and every one ſet upon a ſeat fixed to the wall. I who knew the great Reverence
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:50939:15"/>that is uſed in the <hi>Vatican</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> walked very ſoftly, my knees almoſt trembling; nay, I will tell you more, I ſneaked behind a pillar, to ſhew my greater Reverence to the place, which being obſerved by my good friend, who went up and down ſo boldly, that he began to laugh, and drawing near to me, ſaid thus, Thou ſavours, <hi>Paſquin,</hi> too much of a Citizen of <hi>Rome,</hi> that is to ſay, art but ill inſtructed in the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the <hi>Vatican;</hi> and indeed the <hi>Romans</hi> are like Fiſh which live in the ſalt water, yet are themſelves inſipid; ſo theſe <hi>Romans</hi> juſt live, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the <hi>Vatican</hi> ſuffers them to live, without underſtanding the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of their <hi>Vatican;</hi> but I am not able to endure that ſuch a perſon as thou art, ſo excellently well inſtructed in ſo many witty Subtilties, ſhould ſtill lie immerged in ſo groſs an Ignorance. Know then, that to the modeſt perſons that haunt the <hi>Vatican,</hi> it happens juſt as it does in <hi>France,</hi> to ſuch as will needs ſtand upon their formality and civility at Table; for the <hi>French</hi> accuſtomed to their liberty of behaviour, eat all up, and the others riſe hungry, and repent their ſtarcht Modeſty.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>So that in <hi>France</hi> it ſeems they are no ſooner ſet down at Table, but their hands muſt be put into the diſh as quick as the reſt of the company.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>Moſt certainly, unleſs they deſire to keep <hi>Lent,</hi> whilſt the <hi>French</hi> keep <hi>Eaſter.</hi> But let me go on, I prethee, with the diſcourſe my friend ran on in. Know, <hi>Paſquino,</hi> ſaid he, that this baſhfulneſs in the <hi>Vatican</hi> runs the ſame riſque that it does at the Tables in <hi>France,</hi> where thoſe that reach not out their hands, go without their Dinners; ſo that it is neceſſary in the <hi>Vatican</hi> to make uſe of the <hi>French</hi> boldneſs, that is, go confidently into all places, pry into the moſt reſerved Writings in Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binets, ask impudently for any thing they have a mind to, ſpeak freely what they intend to do, look out for their Dinners without being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vited; in fine, quarrel with the Maſters in their own houſes, if they give them not more than they offer to ask. Thus the <hi>French</hi> comport themſelves where-ever they are admitted; and thus muſt all people do in the <hi>Vatican,</hi> or elſe they muſt come out as empty as they went in. Fruits never fall from their Trees, till they begin to loſe their ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, and putrifie; ſo that thoſe who make a Trade of them, muſt ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther them before they decay. Modeſty in the <hi>Vatican</hi> ruines thoſe that uſe it. They that would have graces, muſt be importunate for them; and thoſe that would receive favours, muſt earneſtly beg them; and they that would not be rejected, muſt be skilful to put themſelves forward. Thoſe that rule in the <hi>Vatican,</hi> are uſually deaf; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is neceſſary to ſpeak aloud; or they are blind, and thoſe that ſtand at a diſtance are not taken notice of; you muſt, if they be deaf, pull them by the Coat, tell who you are, and what you deſire; and like <hi>Jacob</hi> with the Angel, not ſuffer them to depart till you have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:50939:15"/>the bleſſing; if they be deaf, take them about the neck, ſet your mouth to their ears, and cry out as the Jews do, when they call for their Meſſias, and repeat your note, till you have evident ſigns that all you ſay is well underſtood. Woe be to thoſe that ſtand at the <hi>Vatican</hi> Gates, expecting that the Alms of ſome Benefit ſhould be ſent to them; for this is a place which can never be opened whilſt the Popes keep the Keys themſelves, unleſs it be thoſe who can force it with <hi>Paul</hi>'s Sword; ſince it is the nature of the Popes to deſpiſe thoſe that over-value them, and to value thoſe that deſpiſe them. The devout, the meek and the humble are openly neglected; the inſolent, the raſh and the proud immediately find Hats for their heads; becauſe Cardinal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, Biſhopricks, Abbys and Benefices, are never given by the Popes, but always ſtoln by the pretenders; therefore, my dear <hi>Paſquino,</hi> if thou wilt obſerve Modeſty in that place, thou art certain to have nothing fall to thy ſhare.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>This diſcourſe muſt much encourage thee, and inflame thy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires to go farther on.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>It did ſo embolden me, that I got from behind the pillar, where I retired out of reſpect to the place; ſo that I walked in the midſt of thoſe Great Popes, ſtrutting about with my hands on my Girdle like <hi>Bartholomew</hi> of <hi>Bergamus.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Methinks they ſhould be enraged to ſee you in that poſture; but perhaps none of them knew thee.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>I think not, or at leaſt they would not know me; and I was not ſcandalized at that, for I know it's the nature of the Popes neither to know, nor be familiar with any but thoſe they have a mind to know. Beſides, the Hall was great, and I was in the middle of it; therefore 'tis very poſſible that they might either not diſcover, or not obſerve me; therefore I reſolved to begin on one ſide of the room, and walk on to the other; ſo drawing nearer to them, my venerable friend fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing me, I began to look on the faces of thoſe holy Fathers one by one; when one of them inſtantly ſeeing me paſs near him, took out a pair of Spectacles and looked earneſtly at me for a while, then taking them off his Noſe, he put them into their caſe, and took out another ſmaller pair; and looked at me with thoſe as long as he had done with the other, which I did not much wonder at, becauſe I believed he was ſhort-ſighted; for he had two pair of Spectacles, one to look at a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and the other near hand; and he had committed an errour in taking the wrong firſt; but after, when I ſaw that all the reſt of them did the ſame as we were paſſing before them, I could not but be ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, becauſe I could not imagine that all the Popes were ſo ſhort-ſighted as to need two ſorts of Spectacles; but the good man that was near to me, perceiving my amazement, to clear my mind from ſo many
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:50939:16"/>wandring imaginations ſaid to me, <hi>Pasquino,</hi> for ought I ſee thou art in no little wonder at this manner of the Popes looking at thoſe that draw near them. Alas! thou ſhouldſt rather wonder if they ſhould look at any one as other folks do; for it is their nature to do every thing quite contrary to all others, perhaps to make them know that they are Gods, and not Men, ſeeing they don't act like Men, which they are, but like Gods which they pretend to be. The Spectacles which thou ſaweſt them put on and take off, have their particular virtues; for the one pair makes things ſhew bigger and greater than they are, and contrarily the other makes every thing appear ſo little, that they mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilate the very nature of many: Therefore when they will make a Flie an Elephant, they put on the firſt pair; and when they will make an Elephant a Flie, they put on the ſecond. I no ſooner heard this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, but my thoughts ran to the Roman <hi>Vatican,</hi> and I began to diſcourſe thus with my ſelf: Now I underſtand the reaſon why ſo many poor worthy and deſerving Prelates who have ſerved the Church with ſo much labour, and ſweat for many years, are returned to their own Houſes without any reward, but only having the faculty of going haſtily out of <hi>Rome.</hi> And on the contrary ſo many ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous paltry Prieſts, that deſerve no other honour than the Gallows, who, as ſoon as they come to <hi>Rome,</hi> are ſeen ſuddenly to be promoted to the higheſt degree of Prelacy, to the great aſtoniſhment and heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breaking of Chriſtian people.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>For my part I have been a thouſand times Scandalized at ſuch proceedings, and would have been glad to know the true cauſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>Well then you may leave being ſcandalized if you pleaſe. For the Popes will never leave this practice.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>You having then ſeen them both put on and take off their Specta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, leave me not thus confuſed, but tell me if you pleaſe how was it done?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>To underſtand well the affairs of the <hi>Vatican,</hi> you muſt take pains to trace them, but I am ſure you will not be at that trouble, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you Expect it ſhould be thruſt into your throat with a little Spoon, and I who am very much inclined to lay open the <hi>Vatican</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, am Willing to undertake all the pains, and the rather becauſe I am obliged to it by the friendſhip which I have profeſſed to thee. Know then that when their moſt Illuſtrious Excellencies the Brothers of our Lord, or their Reverend Eminencies the Nephews of his Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, have a mind to favour ſome Petty Clergy man, freſh come forth from the lap of his Mother, who had never ſeen but the outſide of the Court; what do they do but put a pair of Spectacles on the Popes Noſe made with that admirable art, which ſhall make my Petty Clerk look like a Mighty great Doctor? So that the poor Pope de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:50939:16"/>by that falſe perſpective, believing him that might Doctor in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, the Petty Clerk comes out declared not a Biſhop, or a <hi>Nuntio,</hi> but a moſt Eminent Cardinal; whilſt the Prelates of the Court, moſt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of ſuch honours, break their horns by daſhing their heads together, to find out how this comes about; neither do they leave beating their brains, till they come to diſcover the virtue of theſe Spectacles. Now, becauſe naturally the Popes Nephews include the Brothers alſo, incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by a certain natural inſtinct, to vilifie the merits of the moſt deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving perſons; What canſt thou gueſs they do to put them by the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours due to them? As ſoon as they ſee thoſe Prelates come near the preſence of the Pope, with a whole bundle of ſervices performed to the Church, and an infinity of Merits to obtain the deſerved rewards of their fatigues, but put the other Spectacles on the Popes Noſe, which have the virtue of diminiſhing things to ſuch an extremity, that a Tower would ſcarce be ſeen thro' them at the diſtance of four ſteps; ſo that that Mountain of Merit which the good Prelate brings along with him, appears to the Popes eyes but as a little buſh, ſo that he is ſent away without any manner of Reward; and the worſt of all is, that my Lords the Nephews laugh not ſo much to ſee the Prelate ſo ill uſed, as to ſee their Uncle well deceived.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>The guilt then is not in the Popes which are deceived, but in the Nephews which deceive them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>The fault rather is wholly the Popes, who ſuffer themſelves ſo to be deceived, and that upon two accounts; firſt for admitting their Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phews into the <hi>Vatican,</hi> and giving them the ſupream command of all things; the ſecond is, for letting ſuch kind of Spectacles be put upon their Noſes, and be willing rather to ſee with thoſe falſe eyes of their Nephews, than with their own true and natural ones. In the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancy of the Church the Popes ſaw with their own eyes, and not with their Nephews Spectacles; the merits of perſons were meaſured ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their own nature, <hi>i. e.</hi> as the Prelates made proficiency there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, by means of the ſervices which they performed to the Church, and the Popes advanced them in honours ſuitable to the proportion of their ſervices, which ſo edified the people, that they adored thoſe holy Popes which proceeded with ſo much fanctity.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>The Church hath now great need to ſee either the Popes of thoſe times return, or thoſe times themſelves.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>Yes indeed, for if it holds on in this manner, woe be to all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendom! for every thing begins to degenerate to ſuch a degree, that all begin to be weary of ſerving the Church of God; and if we will but conſider ſeriouſly the nature of the Roman Court but an Age back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, we ſhall find ſuch great Extravagancies, that if a Book were made of the Metamorphoſes of <hi>Rome,</hi> I am very certain it would bear the Bell away from thoſe of <hi>Ovid;</hi> but this is not to be wiſht, leſt it
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:50939:17"/>ſhould be the occaſion of more ſorrow, to the Weeping Univerſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>I would fain know whether the Popes Nephews make uſe of the ſame kind of Spectacles which the Popes uſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, they make uſe of both ſorts, but being made by their Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Authority, they always order thoſe which are made for their own uſe, to be tempered much finer and ſubtiler, than the Spectacles of the Lords their Uncles.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>I ſhould be glad to know at what time, to what purpoſe, and to what perſons they make uſe of thoſe Spectacles.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>Well, I will tell thee then what things are done at <hi>Rome,</hi> which thou ſhouldſt know as well as my ſelf; but this is the common miſery of the Romans, who live at <hi>Rome</hi> and know not what is done in the <hi>Vatican,</hi> where they treat of nothing but the deſtruction of the Romans. The Nephews then make uſe of theſe Spectacles at all times, unleſs it be at certain days of Solemnities, when blindneſs prevails, a giddy madneſs flying up into their heads, they do act all things hoodwinkt, but at all other times, except thoſe days, they put on, and pull off thoſe Spectacles in this manner. When they would reward ſome Servant of their family, who has ſerved them a great many years, they put on the Spectacles which leſſen and contract the ſight; in conſidering of their Services, and to take a view of what they ſhould give them, they put on the other Spectacles, that magnifie every thing; ſo delighting them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, by eſteeming themſelves generous, they fancy they beſtow much more than they have deſerved: but always when they are to receive any thing themſelves, they take the Spectacles which make every thing look very little; by which means they can never be ſatisfied; for when a <hi>Genoeſe</hi> Prelate, for they bid higheſt, comes and gives them fifty thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Crowns, the Nephews inſtantly put on the foreſaid Spectacles, which contract every thing that the fifty thouſand Crowns hardly appear one thouſand; by which means they remain with ſo unſatiable an appetite, that they are always craving more.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Now I gueſs I underſtand their thoughts, or to ſpeak trulier, the reaſons why my Lords their Nephews ſlight the Injuries which are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſt againſt them, being call'd Thieves; nay, the worſt of Thieves, becauſe they look upon all things which they ſteal with their leſſening Spectacles, which makes great things ſhew as little or nothing, &amp; cannot imagine there ſhould be any cauſe of complaint, being matters of ſo little moment.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>God be praiſed, <hi>Marforius,</hi> that thou haſt once gueſt right, which I am mightily pleaſed with; for, 'tis true, that if the Popes Nephews ſhould look upon all they ſteal in its own magnitude, they would not ſteal ſo much, becauſe the Art of Thievery needs ſome concealment, that it might be exerciſed with ſuch a cloſeneſs, that it could not be known to obſervers: but they rob with ſo great greedineſs, that Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:50939:17"/>may diſcern it, with thoſe helliſh Glaſſes which make Crowns ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear but Farthings hence they inſult over the People after they have flead them, as if the People who were robb'd rather deſerved to be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, than the Nephews who play the Thieves at the very foot of the Altar.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Yet we need to pitty thoſe poor Nephews, tho they be Thieves, becauſe the fault is rather in the Spectacles than themſelves; and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks the diſeaſe might be cured, by that ſentence of Philoſophy, <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move the cauſe and you remove the effect.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>They are worthy both of Compaſſion, and Puniſhment; of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion, becauſe they are induced to it by the Violent power the Devil hath over them; of Puniſhment, becauſe they allow themſelves to be tempted to do ſuch actions, which make them Scandalous to the eyes of the whole World. When a Servant will Rob his Padron he never ſteals all his money at once, leſt his theft ſhould be immediately diſcovered, but ingeniouſly takes now and then a Piſtol, and ſo would the Nephews of Popes do, if they had but ſo much wit, as to rob with that Moderation, that might keep them from being accounted publick Thieves: But I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve they do not imagine, that they are great Thieves, or elſe think the world is blind, for otherwiſe they would not have expoſed their reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſo groſly. The beſt remedy would be to take from them thoſe accurſed Spectacles, which make Piſtols ſeem like Farthings, and ſo diminiſh ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive thefts, Reducing them to ſuch minute Atomes, that the very Confeſſors abſolve them as if the theft were not of value enough to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount to a ſin. But this is a thing not poſſible, whilſt theſe Spectacles are incorporated to them, by the bleſſing granted unto them by his Holineſs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Let us then talk of ſomething elſe; how did theſe Popes ſpend the hours of the day that you ſaw.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>I am aſhamed to tell thee, and yet I will, that thou mayſt have thy part of the ſhame alſo. Some of them applauded themſelves for what they had done, and others imploy'd their time in doing ſomething worthy of Memory; now thoſe memorable things were either appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Croſs to be adored in the Church, and that it ſhould be ſet up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a Pedeſtal repreſenting Mount <hi>Calvary;</hi> in Commanding prayers for the deceaſed, in diſtinguiſhing the Canonical hours; in forbidding Marriage to the Eccleſiaſticks: in making Hymn's and Canticles for the Church: in reforming the Breviary, in adding and diminiſhing the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiphona's,</hi> in bleſſing ſome Medals; in forbidding the eating of fleſh in <hi>Lent;</hi> in diverſifying the habits of Prieſts, and Friers; in appointing Lamps to be continually burning in Churches; in conſecrating the Stones of Altars; in making the bodies of Saints to be tranſported from one Church to another; in decreeing that thoſe of Religious Orders ſhould abide in their Cloiſters; in Commanding Pillars to be ſet at the Gates
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:50939:18"/>of Temples; in altering the Colours of the Sacerdotal Veſts to Cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brate Maſs; in repairing old Church-yards: In Canonizing ſome dead Saint: in placing Images and Candleſticks upon Altars: in confirming privileges on the Mendicants, in allowing Hermitages to be built in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts that devout Travellors may be there more eaſily robbed; in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidding Marriages between thoſe who have been Goſſips; in multiply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the number of Biſhops: in making the Relicks of Saints to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dored and kiſſed: in forbidding Religious orders wearing habits of ſilk: giving order that <hi>Hallelujah</hi> ſhould be ſung in Churches: in conjuring out Devils; in commanding Proceſſions through publick ſtreets: in appointing dying people to be anointed with holy Oyl; in forbidding thoſe of Religious Orders to own any Subjection to Princes; in putting a Croſs on the Popes Shooe: in decreeing Incenſe to Images; in grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Indulgences ſome for years, and others for ever, together with an hundred ſuch kind of juggles, to which they bent all their ſtudies.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>I doubt not but thy pleaſure was great in ſeeing and conſidering them ſo prettily imploy'd.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>I was in a ſtrange toſs, not knowing what to make of it, not ſo much for ſeeing the Popes buſied with ſuch trifles, as for ſeeing them diſingaged from heaping up riches, and I really ſaid within my ſelf; how ſtrange a thing is this! the Popes in <hi>Rome</hi> now think of nothing elſe but building Palaces for their Nephews, and pulling down thoſe which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers have built with ſo much Sweat, to advance their own memories in impoſing Taxes and Cuſtoms on the miſerable people; in ſelling of Offices and Benefices to thoſe who offer moſt money for them; in threatning Princes with War upon every petty account; in looking out for great Marriages to advance their own families, in charging Biſhopricks with heavy Penſions; In giving liberty to their Relations to accumulate immenſe treaſures; in robbing the Altars of Chriſt for to hang the Walls of their Nephews palaces. And after I had made ſome reflections on theſe particulars, I freely told my ſentiments to the good man who accompanied me, who quickly anſwered me thus; Friend, the Popes never change their nature, always preſerving the very ſame inclinations they had at firſt; though nature is altered in them, yet whatever ſmall difference thou ſeeſt between this Vatican and that at <hi>Rome,</hi> it does not come from the nature of the place, but the alteration of time; for none of the Modern Popes enter into this place, for thoſe which thou ſeeſt here were Popes of the Primitive Age, which were not uſed to theft, perhaps becauſe the Church in thoſe times had not treaſures that could be ſtolen and therefore they imployed the hours of the day in ſuch af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs as thou ſaweſt them buſy in But ſince the Popes have had much Wealth, and Eſtates to diſtribute, they have other thoughts, and apply themſelves to thoſe Exerciſes that thou ſpeakeſt of, which are at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent the buſineſs in <hi>Rome.</hi> So that 'tis ſufficient to ſatisfy thee at preſent
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:50939:18"/>to know, that all the Popes which thou ſeeſt in this place are thoſe who have lived holily, or at leaſt moderately, and ſworn Enemies to their kindred: But as ſoon as ever the news was brought to this place, that the Popes had changed their nature, and put on humane affections, and minded nothing elſe but inriching their Nephews, to the prejudice of all Chriſtendom, Heaven thought it Expedient to ſhut its Gates againſt them, ſo that 'tis above two hundred years ſince any of them have come into this place. I was aſtoniſh't at this information, yet was curious e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to go round a ſecond time, the better to obſerve every thing there; and truly amongſt all the Popes faces which I ſaw there, I ſaw but three which I knew, which gave me the greater amazement, becauſe I had well known at <hi>Rome</hi> all the Popes for two hundred years laſt paſt, from which time the Gates of that place had been barr'd.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>And who were thoſe Popes you knew?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Adrian</hi> the ſixth, <hi>Pius</hi> the fifth, and <hi>Sixtus,</hi> the fifth. And having a more particular curioſity to look on them diſtinctly, I declared my Sentiments to my good Guide; thinking it very ſtrange, how they had got in after the doors had been ſhut, but he who was better inform'd than my ſelf, told me that theſe had got in after the ſhutting up of the Gates by ſingular favour, two of them for being enemies to their kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, and the third which was <hi>Sixtus</hi> for having left the Church ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly rich. O then, cried I, Heaven looks more narrowly into the Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Popes than the men of the world do, for they dare not ſpeak the leaſt word againſt their Holineſſes, though they ſee them rob all the wealth of the Church openly.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Heaven fears not impriſonment, as Men in the World do.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>Seeing I ſaw not one of the laſt Popes in this place, particularly not <hi>Alexander</hi> the ſeventh, I grew furiouſly angry, for having wholly loſt all my pains, which aimed above all things to be informed, not of the State of thoſe Popes who had died with the repute of holineſs but thoſe who had expired with the Name of very Devils; and my fury raged more violently, becauſe I had askt that man if he knew where the Popes of the two laſt Ages were, &amp; he had replyed he knew not any thing of them at all, becauſe the Lord God in the hidden ſecrets of his Juſtice had diſpoſed of them ſuitably to the deſerts of their works at <hi>Rome.</hi> But I notwithſtanding my knowing very well, that they Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rited Hell for their Tyrannies, and Extortions towards the poor people to inrich their kindred, yet would not at that inſtant Judge ſo rigorouſly, but I imagined they were in Purgatory.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>There then you might look for them, for when the Purgation of their ſins is paſt they would come thither to the others?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>Thy Councel does not pleaſe me in this Matter, for I would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be ſuch a fool to wait perhaps in vain thouſands of years there, and ſpecially whilſt I was ſo uncertain whether they were in Purgatory,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:50939:19"/>or indeed in hell; Nay, if they were really in Purgatory it were madneſs in me to wait for their coming out, the Popes having not only their own particular guilts on their backs, but alſo the ſins of their Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phews, and of Many others ſinners, whom they lead unto ſin, therefore Purgatory muſt be a very hell to them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>What didſt thou do then having loſt thy longing?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>I threw away all thoſe thoughts which ſo tormented my head to ſee the Popes, and began to fix in my mind a deſire to ſee their Nephews though it were requiſite to go into Purgatory for it; which that good perſon obſerving, he was ſo ſcandalized at me, that he went out before me, and when we were in the middle of the laſt Gate of the aforeſaid Vatican, he diſappeared I do not know how, and I remained in an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known place and where no body knew me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Poor <hi>Paſquin,</hi> I begin to pitty thee, but what reſolution didſt thou take?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>I was beſides my ſelf, and continued in ſuſpence, for the ſpace of a good half hour, when wandring about in a ſtrange perplexity, juſt like one of thoſe who know not whether they are of God, or of the Devil; in Heaven, or Earth; in Hell, or Paradiſe; when not knowing which Leg to ſet forward, I perceived there was but one way, ſo I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined to go on, and ſee the end of it. I bid farewel to the Vatican, and mended my pace for the quicker diſpatch; and had ſcarce gone on two hours, when I found my ſelf in a great Court, built about with lofty Walls, painted with ſundry ſtories, of Martyrs, of Confeſſors, of Nuns, of Virgins, and of Hermits; at the very entrance into this Court, I met with a perſon of good Meen, with an ill favoured rough face, and a beard like a Capuchin, in the habit of a <hi>Switzerland</hi> Carrier, I look't a little while on him, and he did the ſame, looking wiſtly upon me; and I perceiving he carried a great bundle of letters, I could not refrain in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring of him, whither he was travelling, and from whom he was ſent? who courteouſly anſwered me in few words, that he was go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with ſome letters to the Romans, which Chriſt the Redeemer ſent unto them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Without doubt this Meſſenger mock't thee, for heaven does not uſe to ſend ſuch Hatchet-fac'd Ambaſſadors, as thou deſcribeſt this man to be.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>He had not ſo much reaſon to mock me as I have to laugh at thee, who wondereſt at a thing ſo correſpondent to truth; doſt thou be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that Heaven knows not that the World at preſent is much more corrupt than it was ten ages paſt? Experience is the beſt Tutor. The So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domites were ſo extream perverſe that they would have defiled the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels who were ſent from heaven to <hi>Lot,</hi> becauſe they were fair, therefore heaven will not ſend beautiful meſſengers to the <hi>Romans,</hi> whom they account worſe than thoſe Sodomites, (not only the common people,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:50939:19"/>but the very Eccleſiaſticks which rule there) leſt they ſhould In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur a worſe hazard than thoſe Angels did in that place.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>But if this was ſo, how ſhould it enter into thy fancy, that Chriſt ſhould write letters to the <hi>Romans?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>True it is, that Chriſt having written ſufficiently by the hands of his Apoſtles, and Evangeliſts, which are indeed the true Interpreters of the divine will, Chriſtians have not any need of other letters to guide their Souls: but of the other ſide if the rigorous orders wherewith the Inquiſition forbids the reading of the ſacred Scriptures, be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Softly; I muſt needs interrupt thee, for the Inquiſition would have the Sacred Scriptures read, but it muſt be in the Latin Tongue, forbidding the Tranſlation of it into the Vulgar.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>Thou wouldſt make a very fly laugh, with this thy Latin Tongue, what difference doſt thou find between reading, and making a thing be read that one does not underſtand; or the allowing it to be read: This manner of proceeding is an invention of the Clergy of <hi>Rome,</hi> of thoſe of them who would rule the conſciences of the people, at their pleaſure, and according to the dictates of their own Intereſts, which could not be done without hiding from the eyes of the People the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Scripture; which demonſtrates all Errors, and needs no helps to lead and guide the faithful into the paths of Salvation: but becauſe the to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal baniſhment of it would be a turning of Chriſtianity topſy-turvy, what have the good Clergy-men done? They have found out this good Policy for themſelves, and Diabolical to others, to divide it into a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred fragments and pieces, cauſing part to be read in Quires by the Prieſts, and part on the Altars by others of them, cauſing it be tranſlated into the Latin Tongue, &amp; forbidding it under moſt rigorous puniſhments to be read in the Vulgar tongue; which is the ſame thing as to baniſh it out of Chriſtendom, for amongſt three thouſand Chriſtians you will ſcarce find two who underſtand the Latin tongue, and perhaps thoſe two are either ſuch as leaſt trouble themſelves about heaven, or ſuch as know not how to unite thoſe broken, and uncontinued fragments?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Thou thinkeſt then that the prohibition of the Sacred Scripture in the Vulgar tongue proceeded from the Policy of the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men? But what would it import them, if it were read in the Vulgar tongue?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>Doſt thou ask what it imports them, <hi>Marforius?</hi> it would import their total Deſtruction, and Ruin, or at leaſt the Ruin and Deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the vaſt riches they have uſurped with ſo many ſubtile Arts.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>I do not very well underſtand thee; prethee explain it a little better.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>If the people read the Sacred Scripture in their Mother Tongue, as it was compiled by the divine Writters; that is to ſay, all the Epiſtles
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:50939:20"/>of St. <hi>Paul</hi> one after another, likewiſe thoſe of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> and St. <hi>James,</hi> the Acts of the Apoſtles, the Goſpel of the Evangeliſts; in fine, all that is contained in the Old and New Teſtament, the People would find ſo great a Conſolation in the reading thereof, that they would rely on no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe, beſides they would ſee with their own eyes in what their ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation ought to conſiſt, and ſo would turn away from that falſe belief, which they have placed on their Eccleſiaſticks, who ſeeing very well that the People do not know what is their duty towards heaven, becauſe they do not read the divine Decrees, living like beaſts, being led by their Noſes, as they drag Aſſes into Foreſts, to load them with Wood; theſe Eccleſiaſticks draw conſequences levelled to their own Intereſts, Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhing Laws againſt the Laws of Chriſt, and Decrees againſt the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees of God; ſo that the people who know not the Laws of Chriſt, nor the Decrees of God, think themſelves ſaved by the Decrees and Laws of the Eccleſiaſticks. Ask me not, <hi>Marforius,</hi> what it would import the People to read the holy Scriptures in the Vulgar tongue? for if they once taſted it, their deſires would be more &amp; more inflamed, &amp; they would do nothing elſe but read it, whilſt this opened their eyes to ſee the infinite abuſes introduced into the Church by the Eccleſiaſticks, and the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence they would find between the Laws of God, and the Laws of Men; in fine, they would clearly ſee their Errors, and know how they are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by the Church-men, who ſtudy with all Induſtry to keep the people under, by leaving them in Ignorance, for as long as they are kept without the knowledge of the holy Scriptures, the Prieſts will turn them and winde them at their pleaſure, purſuing every way their own In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>I could wiſh all theſe words of thine were ſcattered all over Chriſtendom.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>And I would have all Chriſtendom furniſh themſelves with Bibles, and particularly New Teſtaments in the Vulgar Tongue, by which they would ſee in what ſtate of perdition they are, and how they are abuſed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>I would have thee underſtand, that my eyes begin already to be much opened, and I now remember, that ſome months ago there came ten Bibles in the Vulgar tongue, five of which were for the uſe of five Cardinals. But let us return to our diſcourſe, and tell me what could incline thee to believe, that Chriſt had not writ Letters to the <hi>Romans.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>Thou knoweſt, <hi>Marforius,</hi> I am none of thoſe wry Necks which Reign amongſt Chriſtians, eſpecially among Fryars. There is nothing I hate worſe than hypocriſy, therefore it appears very difficult to me to believe, that Chriſt after having left ſo many holy rules, and ſo many divine inſtructions in the ſacred Writ would ſend new injunctions, as if Heaven was obliged to accommodate it ſelf to the guſt of men, and not men to the Decrees of Heaven; but then I ſaid within my ſelf; What
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:50939:20"/>mighty miracle would this be? The <hi>Meſſineſes</hi> do believe they have received a letter which was Written by the Virgin unto them; and ſhall I that was born in <hi>Rome</hi> refuſe to believe that Chriſt writ letters to the <hi>Romans?</hi> Perhaps the <hi>Meſſineſes</hi> are more worthy than the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans?</hi> Perhaps there was Ink and Paper, found for the Virgin to write with to the <hi>Meſſineſes,</hi> and none found for Chriſt to write to the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> with? Truly the <hi>Romans</hi> have far greater need of the protection of Chriſt than the <hi>Meſſineſes</hi> have of the Protection of the Virgin yet the <hi>Meſſineſes</hi> ſay that the Virgin offered them her protection in that letter; now behold what made me think it poſſible, that Chriſt ſhould ſend an expreſs from heaven to the <hi>Romans.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>And I quite contrary ſhould have believed that Chriſt had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed his Memory in <hi>Rome,</hi> with that particular Letter, that it might not be abſolutely effaced, becauſe the <hi>Romans</hi> think ſo much of the Pope now, that they remember nothing at all of Chriſt. But tell me, could not the meſſenger inform thee of ſome particularities?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>Meſſengers, dear brother, are ſuch who carry without knowing what they bear, or having any thing to do beſides undergoing the Weight. Yet I could not forbear asking him ſome queſtions, but he excuſed himſelf, ſaying he had no time to diſcourſe with me; beſides, he could not tell any great matter unleſs it were what he imagined, and what an Angel had told him, which was that Chriſt exhorted the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> in theſe letters not to ſuffer themſelves to be abuſed with ſo many falſe Introductions of Papal Statutes &amp; that they ſhould continually read the Sacred Scripture in the Vulgar tongue, for in that they would ſee the great abuſes which were found in the Church his Spouſe. The poor meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger could tell me nothing elſe, ſo he followed on his way, and I enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into the Court, turning about this way and that way to view the Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures, which indeed deſerved looking on, for the curioſity of the deſigns.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>But what were thoſe curious deſigns, you ſo magnify?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>Of ſome Fathers who force their daughters to become Nuns; of certain Prieſts who ſelect penitents, of Miſſionaries who manage the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion of the Hereticks, of Prelates who Negotiate for Benefices, of Popes who diſpenſe Indulgences: of Merchants who buy Mules for the Cardinals, and a hundred thouſand of ſuch kind of things; but that which delighted me moſt, was, to ſee the poſtures thoſe perſons were drawn in: and as I was walking round about, a Prieſt ſtood juſt before me, at leaſt he appeared to be one to my eyes, who ſhewed me a great Gate, which was in the middle of one of the four Walls, which I had ſeen well enough before, but had no intention to go in at it, Judging it better to go in at another leſſer door, which was in the other Wall over againſt the great one: when the Prieſt coming near me, without ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing me either how, or when, or whence I came, or whither I went, perſwaded me to go into that great Gate which ſtood open, telling me
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:50939:21"/>it was my right way, and talking thus he led me on to the threſhold of that Gate; but I knowing very well of what metal the Prieſts and Fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers are made, ever teaching things contrary to what the Apoſtles had taught, thought to have entered, in by the little Gate, (which the good Prieſt had turned his back to) not being able to imagine that the other Gate could Conduct me into any place of a good iſſue, becauſe a Prieſt directed it, who ceaſed not to reiterate his intreaties, to have me go in at the great one; upon which making a little reflexion I reaſoned thus with my ſelf, What can this be? What can ever befal me worſe than to go into Hell? And if it be ſo I ſhould not be the firſt man which has been ſent into Hell by the Prieſts: why do I then delay and lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger ſo long before I go in? What is my life more precious than the life of ſo many Emperors, and Princes, and Kings that have ſuffered them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be led into Hell by the Counſel of ſo many Prieſts, and Fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers? But what do I ſay? What am I afraid of? This perſon can by no reaſon be accounted a Prieſt, for the Prieſts will ſcarce open their mouths to ſpeak two Syllables unleſs they be paid for it before hand, with ready money; therefore this man that does not ask me a farthing cannot be a Prieſt, no not ſo much as a Frier.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>The Argument was not bad; but what did you reſolve at laſt?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>I reſolved to obey the Prieſt; and go in at the greater Gate, which I did; but ſee the ill luck on't, I was no ſooner gone in, but the Gate ſhut it ſelf, and the Prieſt remained without, and my ſelf within. Then to tell thee the truth, I thought my ſelf diſpatch't, believing I had been Tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pan'd; and the rather becauſe I obſerved that the inſide of this place, was very different from the outſide, there being Light and Ornament, and here Obſcurity and Confuſion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>God knows how thy heart beat, ſeeing thy ſelf in ſuch a place, and without knowing of any body.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>Truly I trembled all over, and would have been glad to have been near the Gate of the people in <hi>Rome.</hi> Yet ſeeing it was impoſſible to get out of doors that were ſhut, I began to knock, and cry out aloud to the Prieſt to come open them for me: but all in vain, for the Prieſt who ſtaid of the other ſide, let me chatter and ſcold, laughing as if his ſides would burſt. If I had had any money I would have proffered him ſome, becauſe theſe fine Gentlemen the Prieſts, are uſed to fetch Souls out of Purgatory, by the Vertue of money; and I in that darkneſs, ſhut up with ſo many great Chains, reſembled a Soul in Purgatory, and ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined my ſelf to be one indeed: Yet I left off crying any more, <hi>Miſere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini mei,</hi> being ſure I ſhould not have any relief, becauſe I had got no money to purchaſe it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>My thinks 'tis a great ſhame to Chriſtianity to have it ſaid that the Religious will not fetch any Soul out of Purgatory without money.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>'Tis ſo; and what is worſe, every thing is maſqued under the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:50939:21"/>Cloak of devotion, and the Intereſſed Avidity of the religious Orders are come to ſuch a height, that they are no more look't upon as abuſes, having ſo bewitched the minds of the people that they believe thoſe things to be Alms and Charities which are abſolute Thefts, and Ambition of ruling. But I will ſtop no longer at this ſtory of the door, but proceed to tell thee, that deſpairing of any hope of getting back I reſolved to purſue my Voyage further, though to ſpeak the truth, the further I went in, the more I repented the undertaking ſuch a Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney; being ſure I ſhould arrive very ſuddenly at Hell; becauſe as I went on I perceived many ſigns of it, as ſparks of fire, ſtinking of pitch and great heat in the ground to my feet, and huge ſhowers of Cinders and Aſhes, ſo that it was impoſſible for me to Imagine that that way could lead to any other place but either the Hell of the damned, or <hi>Veſuvius</hi> of <hi>Naples.</hi> That which moſt afflicted me was, that from time to time I ſeemed to hear languiſhing voices, howling of Wolves, Yelling of Goats, Neighing of Horſes and other ſuch kind of noiſes. Which voices, though it was impoſſible for me to ſee any perſon, ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as if they had been juſt before me. And now being very weary of walking, my Spirits began by little and little by my great ſufferings to fail, when coming to the end of that path, where I eſpyed the mouth of a great Dragon, ſo monſtrouſly big that the Popes Coach with all his Nephews in it might very eaſily have driven in; which I coming as near to as it was poſſible, I ſaw two paſſages, one of which I imagined led to Hell, and the other to Purgatory; and whilſt ghaſtly I was look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not without fear into that moſt horrid mouth, a certain perſon flaſh't before my eyes like him that had tempted Chriſt in the deſert, which in plain words ſpeaks him to be a devil, nevertheleſs I durſt not give him that name, becauſe I was not certain of it, neither had I indeed ſeen from whence he iſſued. When he notwithſtanding came very courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly towards me, and asked me what I ſought for, but in ſuch an intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent way that ſhewed me he was well informed of all my adventures ſince my departure from <hi>Rome,</hi> asking me only whither I deſired to go; and becauſe he ſaw I was out of breath he cheered me up, with ſuch kind of Conſolations, as the Capuchins beſtow upon thoſe whom they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company to their Execution; whilſt having a little recovered my Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, I anſwered him in few words, that my intention was to go into Purgatory to Viſit my Lords the Nephews of the Popes, if I might be permitted, believing in that place I ſhould certainly find a great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of them; I would have added further that I ſhould willingly go on, and if I did not find them there, it would be a great delight to me, to paſs in as far as hell to ſee them: but I forbore, thinking it better to ſay no more, being confident I might at any time find out the Gates of that place. When this reverend Devil underſtood my intention of go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into Purgatory to Viſit the Popes Nephews, he began to laugh at ſuch
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:50939:22"/>a rate as I had never ſeen any body laugh in the World, holding his hands on his ſides as if he had feared burſting.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>It would pleaſe me alſo to ſee the Devil once laugh: but what did he laugh at ſo heartily?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>At my ſimplicity in imagining that the Popes Nephews were in Purgatory; ſo that being weary of his laughing which held him a good half hour, he with a ſmiling face ſpoke thus unto me; I know very well that thou art a Pilgrim from <hi>Rome</hi> where the people are abuſed by the Crafty malice of the Eccleſiaſticks who make them believe that there is a place of Penance for thoſe perſons who are impenitent, and that the very Guilt is purged in Purgatory, without ſo much as giving an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the wickedneſs committed to any except a Prieſt. But I would have thee know, <hi>O Roman,</hi> that none enters into Purgatory, that robs the Church to beſtow it on the World, but thoſe who rob the World to give it to the Church. None of the Nephews of the Popes enter into Purgatory, though there be ſome to be found amongſt them who Juſtly deſerve it, becauſe heaven is forced to ſend them all into Hell out of policy. I was now more aſtoniſhed than ever, not being able to comprehend how it was poſſible to ſend the Popes Nephews into hell out of Policy; but this reverend Devil, having perceived my amazement, relieved me from my Anxiety by unridling the <hi>Aenigma</hi> preſently in theſe words, Thou oughteſt to know, being born a <hi>Roman,</hi> that all which the Popes Nephews poſſeſs are the very bowels &amp; ſubſiſtance of the Souls in Purgatory; ſtealing out of the treaſury of the Church that Wealth &amp; Riches which is given by the People only to eaſe and alleviate with their alms thoſe poor Souls who are in Purgatory; now if the Souls in that place ſhould ſee the Nephews of the Popes enter into it, they would fall upon them and Revile and Tear them with theſe words; Ah Barbarians and wicked Enemies of our reſt, Ah Cruel and Tyrannical deſtroyers of our treaſures, you make our pains perpetual, which would have ended ſome ages ago. You cauſe us to burn ſtill in theſe flames, you deprive us of the Divine Viſion, you Enemies of Purgatory, that devour the ſubſtance, which our friends have given unto the Church, for the mitigation and relief of our pains. You build Pallaces with the Price of our blood. You hang your Walls with that Gold which was ſet apart, to have delivered us of theſe flames, you buy Coaches, and Horſes with that mony which ſhould have help't to have carried us up to heaven? You walk up down in Gardens with freſh fountains and fine Water-works, whilſt we are hear broiling in theſe fires. Now ſince theſe reproaches would be cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly given to the Nephews of the Popes of they ſhould enter into Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, not to add Miſery to Miſery on thoſe unhappy Souls which are in that place, the Popes Nephews are ſent to hell, that the ſight of them which are ſo juſtly Odious to thoſe inhabitants of Purgatory might not ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke them, though they deſerved indeed to have come firſt into that
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:50939:22"/>place. This diſcourſe moſt tenderly wounded my heart, nevertheleſs I could not forbear looking Earneſtly on the Eyes of this Oratour, not being able to think he was a Devil. So much truth was there, in what he ſaid, who whilſt I was looking thus fixedly on him, went on, ſaying, I might have gratified my curioſity in ſeeing the Nephews of the Popes, by deſcending into Hell by that other mouth; but 'tis worth ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving, that he had ſo much inflamed my deſires of ſeeing them, that I thought he muſt needs be either a <hi>Roman</hi> Inchanter or Sorcerer, or at leaſt a <hi>German</hi> Witch; and when he perceived that I was reſolved to obey his exhortations, he ſummoned an hobgoblin as black, and as ugly as the Devil, and whiſpered in his Ears, ſo that I do not very well know what he ſaid, whereupon he entred again into Hell, and a Minute after that came out again, and brought along with him a Veſſel very like thoſe which the Prieſts keep their holy Oyl in, which they uſe at the Extream Unctions; and without making any great Compliments to me, he made me lye down flat upon the ground and anointed my body all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver with the Liquor which was in that Veſſel. I inſtantly fancied that this was the Oyl of Extream Unction in Hell, in Intimation to me, that I ſhould never return from thence; but the Devil bid me take Courage, for that Ointment had a certain Virtue, not only to Quench, but alſo to cauſe the very Ardour of the flames not to be felt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>If this remedy was in <hi>Rome</hi> a great many Prieſts would run to Martyrdom, becauſe they love to ſee ſufferings, but not to feel them; but what followed after this Ceremony of the unction was over?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>The Chaplain of the function having received his Orders from the other, gave me his Parole, and courteouſly aſſured me that he would faithfully accompany me: So riſing up on my feet I thanked him, as I did the former, who diſappeared I know not how, ſo that I remained with this laſt Devil: Who expected that I ſhould go firſt into hell, and I on the other hand thought he ſhould carry me on his back; &amp; having told him my intention, he anſwered me to it, that the Devil did not uſe to carry any body into hell, becauſe it was forbidden by a very rigorous Edict of the divine Majeſty, who had Eſtabliſh't a decree in his Sacred Throne, that thoſe who had a mind to go into Hell ſhould go Voluntarily, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being carried thither by any one; whence the Devils had this ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, that they had not the trouble of carrying any Souls into Hell, for they came of themſelves thither. I anſwered him I underſtood not how this was, and therefore beg'd his Pardon, adding that I the rather believed the reverend Devils had carried men into Hell, becauſe that in the World, and more particularly in <hi>Europe,</hi> at every word when any diſpute ariſes between men, they inſtantly ſay, <hi>The Devil take thee,</hi> ſo that I imagined it had been the Devils Office to have carried men into Hell, becauſe men did ſo give one another unto the Devil. To which he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed, that thoſe Curſings did make the Devil the more inraged. See<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:50939:23"/>men offer one another ſo frequently unto him without his being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to lay hold on ſo fair an Opportunity, by reaſon God would have thoſe men who ſo often wiſh to go into Hell, ſhould go of themſelves, that they might not have that excuſe to alledge that they were forced to go thither.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>'Tis a pretty Complement to go into Hell; thou then wert con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to go firſt without any Ceremony?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>Why what would you have me do? I ſhould have been better pleaſed to have been carried, but ſeeing the Devil either would not, or could not undertake the charge, I reſolved to paſs on firſt; true it is, that being entered into the Mouth, in which were two holes, and offering to go down by that which was on the right hand, the Demon cryed out with a loud voice, that I miſtook the way, for I was to go on the left hand, which I immediately obey'd, and caſt my ſelf on that ſide, which ſlided me finely down in ſuch a dainty manner, that I had no ſooner ſet my feet in it, but I was at the bottom in the Twinkling of an Eye, deſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing juſt like thoſe who Glide upon Ice. The Devil helping me a little alſo, puſhing me on behind, to haſten our Journey the better, that we might end it in good time.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>I think the Devils do ſo in the world alſo; never driving any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Hell, unleſs they firſt preſs themſelves forwards.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>Moſt certainly; now both of us Precipitating our ſelves ſliding on ſtill, we came to the Shore of a large lake, which was extreamly A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitated and toſs'd, the Waves riſing up above two hundred yards, and then precipitated down again with a hideous roaring which I wondered much at, ſeeing ſo great a tempeſt, and not being able to hear the ſmal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt breath of any Wind. But the Devil who was with me told me that Water boil'd, by the great Violence of fire, which is underneath it, to whom I ſaid then, that the flames of Hell muſt needs be very ardent, ſeeing they force the Waters to riſe with ſo much Violence, which ſeemed to part into five parts, and yet held great correſpondence, though the Nature, or Perhaps the Virtue, of one part of the Water, did not agree with the Nature, and Vertue of the other; the Devil proceeding on to inform me better, as followeth, the Water which thou ſeeſt, every one that goes to hell is neceſſitated to ferry over, and 'tis Expedient for them to ſteer ſo exactly that they may be ſure to go through each of thoſe diviſions which thou obſerveſt: And if thou wilt know the cauſe of this Lakes being divided into five parts, I will tell thee briefly; that the firſt hath the Vertue to cauſe every thing to be forgotten, and thence is called the Water of <hi>Lethe;</hi> the ſecond is nominated the Water of <hi>Phlegeton</hi> which ſignifies the Ardor of Torment; the Third the Water of <hi>Acheron</hi> which imports deprivation of all joy; the Fourth the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Cocytus</hi> which denotes Weeping; and the Fifth is the <hi>Stygian</hi> Lake, which is as much as to ſay Eternal Hatred and Miſery.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>But how is this Water paſt? do they ſwim or are there boats ready to waft them?</p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:50939:23"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>There is one boat, which is commonly called <hi>Charon</hi>'s Ferry which is loaded with paſſengers twice a day, but it is worth noting that the Barque goes thither, but never comes back, for the ſaid Waters are eaſy to be navigated in the return upwards; therefore there are a multitude of Shipwrights ever building new ones, a Bark ſerving only for one Voyage, being always broken in a hundred pieces at the other Shoar. I embarqued then in this boat, together with the Demon, for want of a better companion, but <hi>Charon</hi> would not take any other paſſenger in at this time, beſtowing a thouſand civilities upon me, and the Mariners behaved themſelves with more than ordinary Courteſy, ſtriving with one another who ſhould be moſt ſerviceable to me; at the entring into this boat, there came an Intolerable ſtink to me of Pitch, of Bitumen, Sulphur and ſuch kind of things, but above all of Aſſa faetida, to ſuch a degree that I thought the Violence of the ſtenches would have poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned me, and thought what fools are they who would go to hell; when we were arrived at the haven an Infinite number of Demons came and met us, every one of them having Five or Six Horns on their Heads, and every one of them offered me his ſervice, without any thing for their pains, which was the more Remarkable, ſo that I wondered very much that none ſhould demand of me payment for my paſſage or freight, neither did any of them ſo much as ask a little drinking mony. So I bleſt God that had once let me ſee a Country that was diſintereſſed and free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearted; the Devil who conducted me knowing my admiration, inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogated me whether frankneſs was not in faſhion all over <hi>Rome;</hi> to which Query I anſwered thus: Since <hi>Meum</hi> and <hi>Tuum</hi> have been Intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced into the World, Taxes and Cuſtoms have been brought to ſuch an Extravagance, that the People are forced to buy at dear Rates every thing which Nature had given freely to mankind: But this ſort of Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny which is ſo univerſal in the World, ſeems to be moſt peculiar to <hi>Rome,</hi> where the Popes have introduced ſo many impoſitions and ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Cuſtoms, that the very deceaſed are not exempted, whilſt thoſe bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies are often kept unburied which have not left enough to pay the Prieſt his burying fees; in fine, thoſe who travel in the World, had need be always with a purſe in their hands; for ſtrangers, beſides their paying for the very roads they tread, &amp; ſuffering a hundred Inſolences from the watchmen who keep the Gates for the Officers of the Cuſtoms, are alſo conſtrained under the Notion of Alms, to pay for the kiſſing the Reliques of the Saints, for the very confeſſing of their own ſins.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>God forgive the inventers of theſe things, but what need had the Devil of this Information, if, as the Divines ſay, the Demons do already know all that is, or has been done in the World.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>Thou art deceived, <hi>Marforius,</hi> for the Devils know nothing elſe beſides thoſe things which they are able to penetrate by the ſubtilty of
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:50939:24"/>their nature but the <hi>Roman</hi> Eccleſiaſticks commit certain kinds of rogue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries that the Demons have never been able to Penetrate into with all their Speculations; therefore 'tis requiſite to know that where the greater Spirits prevail, the leſſer Spirits give place immediately; beſides, the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phews of the Popes have invented in <hi>Rome</hi> more Tyrannical ways to draw money from the People, than the Devils to draw Souls into Hell; therefore the Demons may be called ignorants in <hi>Rome,</hi> becauſe the Eccleſiaſticks, and the Popes Nephews out-wit them; in fine, the Devil who was with me took great pleaſure in my information, and gave me many thanks, tho in few words, by reaſon of the mighty com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plements which the other-Devils made me, who all conducted me Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphantly to the true Gates of Hell, which opened without any diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty, and before I could ſet my feet over the Threſhold of the Gate, <hi>Lucifer,</hi> who had notice of all, ſent me abundance of Pages, and Footmen to wait on me; but I thanked him, and beſeech't him to reſerve theſe favours for the moſt Eminent Cardinals, and Prelates who are uſed to be ſerved by certain Pages and Lacquies, who are no whit inferiour in Craft and Wickedneſs to the courtiers of <hi>Lucifer</hi> himſelf.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Thou ſayeſt true, and for my part I believe that this race of Raſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cals, are put to School in <hi>Rome,</hi> at the coſt of the Lords the Cardinals, and Prelates, to fit them to ſerve with the greater aſſurance the Devil himſelf.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>I believe the ſame, and therefore, rid my ſelf of them, being bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter content to go <hi>Incognito</hi> without any attendance, than to be waited on by ſuch beaſts, although it would indeed not have coſt me a farthing, whereas in <hi>Rome</hi> one is forced to pay not only for being ill ſerved, but for being betray'd alſo; yet notwithſtanding my refuſing the attendance of thoſe Servants <hi>Lucifer</hi> had ſent unto me, I was not waited on with a jot leſs Majeſty, and Grandeur, for an infinite Company of Devils ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelves in Ranks on both ſides, one behind another, ſaluted me as I paſſed through with ſo high Civility that I thought I was ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Pope going to <hi>Monte Cavallo.</hi> I had ſcarce made ten ſteps within Hell, when a Perſon came towards me ſo full of Lace and Ribbons, and with low Congies pulled off, and put on his hat again, and then in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly began to untye my breeches, which I had tyed with double knots fearing they might have fallen down in my Journey; but he ſet him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſo earneſtly to it both with his hands and his teeth, that I had ſome ſport, to ſee him torment himſelf; that gave me ſome pleaſure, but on the other ſide I ſound I cannot tell what alteration in my ſelf, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding poſitively that this man was ſome <hi>Sieneſe</hi> or <hi>Florentine</hi> who was u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to Untruſs the Boys Breeches in <hi>Rome;</hi> and therefore I defended my ſelf as much as it was poſſible, objecting unto him my Age; but theſe reaſons not cauſing him to deſiſt from the Office he had begun, heating himſelf more and more with the reſolution of prevailing, he put me into
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:50939:24"/>a mighty rage, which the Demon who was my aſſiſtant perceiving, he endeavoured to pacify me, by aſſuring me that that Perſon was neither a <hi>Sieneſe,</hi> nor a <hi>Florentine</hi> but an honeſt <hi>French-man.</hi> How! a <hi>French-man,</hi> cried I? and how long is it ſince <hi>French-men</hi> are become Sodomites? I have been told, that they love the eaſier pleaſures and are ſeldom wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to ſtruggle hard for what gives little Satisfaction; their impatience makes them Shrink from trouble, and it ſeems more natural to them to Ruffle a Petty-coat, than to put their Teeth to a Cod-piece point? O anſwered the Devil again to me, there is great myſtery hidden in this, which would pleaſe thee well to be inform'd of. Thou know'ſt the <hi>French</hi> ſtudy nothing elſe than to ſearch &amp; pry up &amp; down wherever they go, ſo that they run about thruſting their noſes into every thing; now you muſt know, our <hi>Lucifer</hi> who loves to imploy every one as his Inclination leads him, not to leave the <hi>French</hi> idle in Hell; ſince idleneſs is the Domeſtick E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy of that Nation, he allows them the Liberty to thruſt their noſes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the tail of all ſtrangers when they firſt come into Hell, but from this du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty they cannot exempt themſelves though the humour of it ſhould be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, becauſe the Devil knows not how to imploy the <hi>French</hi> otherwiſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>This imployment would not much pleaſe me, though, becauſe they are ſo uſed to it, perhaps it is no great toil to them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>Now I being well ſatisfied with this information let my points be untyed by this <hi>Monſitur,</hi> who being pleaſed with that, after he had a little looked in my face fell on his knees to my backſide, and with a good grace began to nozzle his noſe into my breech. But to tell thee the truth, <hi>Marforius,</hi> I was never more confounded, not knowing of a ſudden how to winde my ſelf out of ſuch a complement, for the more I ſhrunk up my Buttocks, ſo much the more earneſtly he puſhed in his noſe. Whereupon I reſolved to end it, to let Scape a Rouzing Fart, which made above forty Devils that were about us fall a laughing; but the <hi>French-man</hi> was content rather to noſe a little of the fume, than leave off rubbing his noſe in my breech, to my no ſmall-vexation, not knowing how to get rid of him; but fortune ſent in another ſtranger whom the <hi>French-man</hi> ſet upon to perform the ſame function; and I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing delivered from this encumberance, paſs't on with my companion, and the further we went the more ſport we had to ſee the <hi>French man</hi> go up and down to give the noſe in breech to every new comer.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Let's talk no more of ſuch a Subject, but relate if you pleaſe ſome ſeriouſer thing.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>Thou ſpeakeſt of Gravity, juſt as I am about to talk of thoſe peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple who are graver than their <hi>Pyrenean</hi> Hills. You muſt know then that the ſight of this <hi>French-man</hi> ſtirred up a Curioſity in me to ſee the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> not being able to fancy that the occupation, or rather pains of them ſhould be any thing inferiour, or leſs curious then the pains and imployment the <hi>French</hi> practiſed, and endured. The <hi>Demon</hi> had no ſooner ſounded my thoughts, but he made me take the way on the left
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:50939:25"/>hand, over againſt which ſtood a very high Gate wide open, broken, and ſo ruinous, that it perfectly lookt like an old tattered Enſign: At the entrance of this Gate I had like to have broke my ſhins; all the Stones did ſo totter, being out of their right places; on both ſides lay two vaſt heap of Chains, Logs, Iron Manacles, Ropes, and other ſuch like Inſtruments, all black and ruſty, by which mark one might eaſily know that they had not been uſed of a long time. The extent of this place was ſo great, that the Eye could not look to the end of it; whence I imagined that this was <hi>Lucifer</hi>'s own Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; but one of the Devils, who was upon the Guard, took me out of this fancy, by telling me, that this was the <hi>Spaniards</hi> Apartment, which ſtirred up my curioſity to know what thoſe heaps of Chains, and Ropes, which were thrown ſo careleſly on the ground, ſignified; to which Queſtion, the Devil, who was on the Guard there, anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me in this manner; The <hi>Spaniards,</hi> who, whilſt the fortune of the houſe of <hi>Auſtria</hi> laſted, were formidable in the world, had put the Dominion of Hell into great jealouſie, that our Prince, fearing leſt, as the <hi>Spaniards</hi> were reſolved to domineer over the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe, ſometimes bringing a Kingdom into their ſubjection, and ſometimes a Repub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, ſo they would alſo, by the ſame policy and ambition, ſubdue Hell it ſelf, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce all the Infernal Vaſſals to their obedience, was reſolved to prevent them: But it was not ſo eaſie for them to tyrannize over Hell, as it had ſucceeded to them in Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it over <hi>Europe.</hi> For the Devils, who are ever ſtudying to preſerve their own Liberty, ſoon perceived their unbridled ambition, and brought a quick Remedy, hampering the <hi>Spaniards</hi> in ſuch Chains and Fetters, that they durſt not ſo much as attempt the leaſt violence, although the force neither of Iron, nor Chains, is able to take from them the Pride which they ever maintain outwardly—But the Princes of <hi>Europe</hi> no ſooner percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved this torrent of Pride, which flowed from <hi>Spain</hi> to the damage of the Univerſe, but they all united together to lowre that <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Pride, which corroded with the Venom of Jealouſie, the Quiet of all Principalities: No ſooner did they begin to joyn Forces to deſpoil them of thoſe States, which they had ſo over-haſtily inveſted themſelves in; no ſooner did they begin to ſow Diſcords, by popular Revolutions, to deprive them of thoſe Kingdoms, which they had ſo tyrannically uſurped from other Kings; In fine, no ſooner were the <hi>Spaniards</hi> ſeen languiſhing and dying, from proud, to become humble, and from haughty to become wretched, being pointed at by thoſe very people who obeyed them at the holding up of their finger: But <hi>Lucifer</hi> imitating the Princes of <hi>Europe</hi> (who had not only laid aſide their fears, but made them tremble in the Center of their own Countrey) ordered the Chains ſhould be taken from their necks, and the Fetters from their feet, and they ſhould be let looſe, being ſecured they could never regain with all their Policy, the Power which they had loſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>This ſeems to me rather a diſcourſe of a good Politician, than a wicked Devil; but what, did you not then ſee the <hi>Spaniards?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, I ſaw them, why ſhould I not, ſince I went in for that purpoſe? After then the Sentinel at the door had informed me of theſe particulars that I have told thee, we paſſed on further, and entred into a great Hall, open on all ſides, but covered over head, which Roof or Cieling was ſupported with many Pillars round about it. I ſaw the <hi>Spaniards</hi> there ſtretched upon the ground, kiſſing the Earth with their mouths, over whom were many <hi>French-men</hi> hung by the Arms, as if they had been upon the Rack: But that which was moſt curious in the fight, was to ſee the <hi>French</hi> endeavour earneſtly to ſtretch out their feet to touch the ſhoulders of the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> not valuing the break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of their own arms to have the ſatisfaction of treading upon them, and the <hi>Spaniards</hi> ſhrinking from them as much as they could, rubbing their bellies on the ground, as Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents, to avoid the trampling with the feet of their Enemies, ſo that I could not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern which was the greater pain, that of the <hi>French,</hi> which trod upon them, or that of the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> who were trodden upon. There were mingled up and down ſeveral <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> and <hi>German</hi> Princes, and ſome Embaſſadors from <hi>England,</hi> from <hi>Swedeland,</hi> from <hi>Denmark,</hi> from <hi>Venice,</hi> and from <hi>Holland,</hi> and <hi>Switzerland,</hi> who were almoſt burſt with laughing to ſee ſuch a Scene; but the beſt of all was, to ſee them uſe all their craft to egg
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:50939:25"/>on ſometimes the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> and ſometimes the <hi>French:</hi> To the <hi>French</hi> they ſpoke ſoftly, in this manner; It is a ſhame, that you who have ſeen your ſelves ſo many years ill uſed by the <hi>Spaniards;</hi> that you cannot revenge your ſelves fully for all that they have done againſt you: What, have not the <hi>French</hi> then wit enough to reduce the <hi>Spaniards</hi> into ſuch a calamitous condition, as the <hi>Spaniards</hi> have formerly reduced the <hi>French?</hi> Sa, ſa, take heart, you generous <hi>French-men,</hi> ſtretch out your legs, ſprawl out your feet, endure a little more pain of your arms, loſe not this opportunity: For if the <hi>Spaniards</hi> ſhould at this time get from under you, they would not fail with their ſubtle crafts, to ſeek for ways to get over you again: Then to the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> with a low voice, they diſcourſed thus; What a ſhame is this, that you ſhould ſuffer your ſelves to be thus trampled upon by the <hi>French,</hi> who were formerly trod upon by the <hi>Spaniards?</hi> What, have you the heart to ſee the name of the <hi>Spaniards</hi> thus vilified? What, are you able to ſee that <hi>Spain,</hi> which other whiles hath made all the Nations of the World to tremble, be affright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the name of the ſingle <hi>French</hi> Nation? If you would but begin to kick at the <hi>French,</hi> which tread upon you, you would find an hundred hands ready to help you: It concerns you to begin the work, and us to find out means to compleat it; we, who have been favourable to <hi>France,</hi> to bring down <hi>Spain,</hi> would now be favourable to <hi>Spain</hi> to bring down <hi>France:</hi> Loſe no time then; for an inveterate diſtemper corrodes the bowels of them that have it: You muſt either recover your loſt honour, or be content to loſe all you have left. The <hi>French</hi> have already brought you to ſuch extremities, as to ask twice for Peace out of Charity; and if you do not do your utmoſt to defend your ſelves, you will be forced to beg your lives as an Alms. You will find thoſe that will ſupply you with Men and Moneys, both ſecretly and openly; and what would you have more?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Provided the Effects correſpond with the Promiſes, every thing will go well: But I am afraid of ſomewhat, whilſt the other Princes, who egg on the <hi>Spaniards</hi> and the <hi>French,</hi> very often leave them both afterwards in the Suds.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>There is no doubt, but that the Policy of other Princes will not only roaſt, but kindle, the fire to roaſt the <hi>Spaniards</hi> in the Fat of the <hi>French;</hi> but becauſe theſe two Monarchies are ſo ſituated by nature, and the diſtribution of Politick Intereſts, that the one cannot be diminiſhed without the augmentation of the other; ſo that all the Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Reaſon of other Princes requires them to keep theſe two Monarchies in an eaven balance; wherefore every time they ſee one of them falling, they run immediately to lend them their hand againſt the other: And, in truth, it is a curious thing to ſee how the <hi>Engliſh, Venetians, Hollanders</hi> and <hi>Swiſſes,</hi> and the other Princes of <hi>Italy</hi> and <hi>Germany</hi> labour to raiſe up the poor <hi>Spaniards;</hi> one lifts up one leg, another another; ſome one arm, others another; ſome hold up his head, ſome hold him out a Rope: In fine, ſome with one thing, and ſome with another; all endeavoured to raiſe up the oppreſſed <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards;</hi> but with all this they do nothing; and, to ſpeak truly, how can they, becauſe they fear ſo much the riſing Fortune of <hi>France,</hi> that they dare not declare themſelves openly in favour of the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> whereby the help they bring him, ſerves to little pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>I know not how Affairs go in Hell, becauſe I was never there, but am ſure they are otherwiſe tranſacted in <hi>Europe;</hi> Policy and Religion being ſo jumbled together, that the Intereſt of Religion is very often obſtructed, by the Intereſts of Policy.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>He that preſcribed that <hi>Recipe</hi>—muſt be a Fool of a Phyſician, and I am angry, <hi>Marforius,</hi> that thou ſhouldſt talk ſo like a wiſe man of <hi>Gotham;</hi> for how, prethee, can the diſcourſing of Princes and Religion agree together? ſince the Religion of Princes, muſt ever ſerve, or be uſed as Antimony is by the ſick, and ſometimes by the healthy; which when taken in ſmall quantity, exactly weigh'd, and prepared curiouſly, reſtores health to the Infirm, and confirms it to the Healthy: But the leaſt Grain, taken too much, without due weight and preparation, poyſons the ſtomach, and kills the body: So Religion, by Princes, muſt needs be but little uſed, and very well weighed; for a little too much is ſufficient to diſturb the quiet of any Principality. Nay, I will ſay more,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:50939:26"/>that as Antimony is not commonly given but in deſperate caſes: So Princes ought not to ſtick too cloſe to the Intereſts of Religion, but in thoſe Occurrences, when they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not poſſibly do otherwiſe. <hi>Bethlem Gabor</hi> underſtood that preſcription exceeding well, and therefore when the <hi>French</hi> Embaſſador went into <hi>Germany,</hi> to tell him, that tho' Indeed it was true, that Policy required the King of <hi>France</hi> to humble the Houſe of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtria,</hi> and that a more opportune ſeaſon could never be found to do ſo, than at that time; yet the Intereſt of Religion did oblige the King to go off from that League he had made with the ſaid <hi>Gabor,</hi> to the prejudice of the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> for fear of ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Catholick Religion deſtroyed in thoſe parts: To which propoſal <hi>Gabor</hi> anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in theſe few words; <hi>Tu Princeps, &amp; de Religione curas?</hi> Is your Maſter a Monarch, and is he ſcrupulous in matters of Religion?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>This Example doth not much ſatisfie me; for this <hi>Gabor</hi> was worſe than any Turk, and, amongſt Chriſtian Princes, there are other kinds of Principles.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>Hear, <hi>Marforius,</hi> what I have to ſay to thee upon this particular; it is more diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſing to God, when a Chriſtian does good works, and afterwards repents the doing of them, than if he had not done them at all; he being fitter to be excuſed, who hath omitted doing good, but he is worthieſt of puniſhment, that repents of his good deeds. Now, amongſt Princes, the ſame Reaſon is current; for they had much better lay aſide ſome Maxims of Religion, than to embrace them a while, and repent of them after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards. When the King of <hi>France</hi> beſieged <hi>Rochel,</hi> the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> againſt all Maxims of Policy, ſolely upon thoſe of Religion, ſent their Army to help the Moſt Chriſtian King, which much weakened their own Force, and made the Party of the Moſt Chriſtian King their Enemy ſtronger, which, a while after, the <hi>Spaniards</hi> well perceiving, repented ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremely what they had done, biting their Nails for rage at it. Thus they got little with God, nothing with the King of <hi>France,</hi> and leaſt of all with the World, loſing that blaſt of Fame which they thought to have gained in <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> as ſoon as it was rumoured about, that they repented what they had done. Of theſe Examples one may find a thouſand; and it is certain, that Princes ordinarily repent of all thoſe Maxims of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion which they make uſe of ſometimes, for I know not what reaſon. And it would be much better for them never to embrace them, than to repent ſo ſuddenly of their ſo doing; loſing the favour of Heaven by their Repentance, and what they might have got by the Intereſts of Policy. The <hi>French</hi> are not ſo ſimple as the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> and they never touch the Affairs of Religion, but with the tips of their fingers.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>But, methinks yet in the time of <hi>Bethlem Gabor,</hi> they have hugged Religion in their arms.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>Alas, how thou art couzened! Thoſe Maxims of Religion ſerved them only in appearance, to cover ſome particular private Intereſts, which were a foot then in <hi>France,</hi> deſigning to oblige the <hi>Infanta</hi> of <hi>Spain</hi> to yield to, I cannot tell you what Marriage; without which conſideration, the Maxims of Policy would have infinitely out-ſtript thoſe of Religion. The <hi>French</hi> are not ſo ſcrupulous; they love rather never to embrace the Maxims of Religion, than embrace them, and repent of them, as the <hi>Spaniards</hi> do. Whilſt Cardinal <hi>Richlieu</hi> lived, who perfectly underſtood theſe Rules, the Pope's <hi>Nuncio,</hi> tho' he often ſet before him the War againſt <hi>Geneva,</hi> and always propoſed the great Maxims of Religion, the good <hi>Cardinal</hi> continually anſwered him thus; <hi>Provided the Maxims of Religion do not ruine the Maxims of State:</hi> And in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner he diſmiſſed the <hi>Nuncio,</hi> who never went further with him, becauſe he ſaw him much more ſteered by the Maxims of State, than by thoſe of Religion. Maxims of Religion are really groſs Victuals, and fit for common people; but thoſe of State are curious bits, and only fit for Princes; to whoſe Tables groſs Meats ought never to be brought, but in times of great neceſſity, it being unfit to fill their ſtomachs with that, which is only good to fill the bellies of the ruder popularity. That ſuch Meat is good to ſatiate common people, I grant, but to nouriſh Princes, I deny, becauſe the ſame food which ſerves for nutriment to the People, would hurt Princes when they would make uſe of them; becauſe, a ſtomach which is accuſtomed to delicate Meat, is not able
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:50939:26"/>to bear groſſer food: In fine, the beſt Princes leave Maxims of Religion to Monks and Prieſts, as food proportioned to their temper, and reſerve for themſelves Maxims of State as food proper for Princes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Before I forget, prethee tell me what pains the <hi>Germans</hi> ſuffer in Hell?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>The ſame pains that are endured by <hi>Tantalus,</hi> which is, to be very thirſty, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out having any Wine to quench their drought; ſo that it is a curious thing to obſerve their going up and down in Hell, to look out ſome place to plant Vines in; and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they endeavour it with all poſſible diligence, they have not yet, nor ever will ſucceed in their deſign; becauſe the Devil, knowing perfectly well, that it is natural to the <hi>Germans</hi> to eſteem any place Paradice where they find good Wine, tho' all the Dae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons in Hell were in the place; therefore they ever find an oppoſition to theſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Since there are ſo many Lakes, ſurely they ſhould do them the favour to make them Ferry-men, rather than let them periſh with thirſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>They would never accept that Office, becauſe they have taken an Oath never to be drowned but in Wine, which they will not break to die in the Water.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Well, follow on thy Voyage, and let us ſay no more of the Maxims of Religion; Princes having more need of it than we.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>Thou art in the right; after we had obſerved the <hi>French</hi> and the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> we walked about that ſpacious place a little while, where we ſaw ſeveral deſerted, in which we met ſome poor <hi>Spaniards</hi> full of Lice, with bare Breeches; and I, being full of cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſity, asked one of them his name, to which he replyed haughtily, I am called <hi>Don Lopez of Lopis;</hi> at which I was extremely aſtoniſhed to ſee, that neither Lice, Poverty, Miſery, nor Hell could humble the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Pride; therefore I intreated him to tell me, what good that Title did him? to which he anſwered, that it ſhewed him to be a <hi>Spaniard,</hi> loving rather to be known to be of that Countrey, tho' a Beggar, than eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a <hi>French-man,</hi> tho' rich: Which Opinion being heard by a <hi>French-man</hi> who paſſed by, he ſaid, Keep thy Title; for that Feather of a Title will be the laſt thing that the <hi>French</hi> will take away from the <hi>Spaniards;</hi> in which time, turning my Eyes from this object, I had paſſed but a few ſteps on, when I found my ſelf very near the Gate, through which I had entred; whereupon, making haſte to get out, I unexpectedly heard a noiſe, a rumour, a ſcreeching, a fearful cry, which ſaid very mournfully, <q rend="margQuotes">
                     <hi>O miſerable people! we are loſt; Oh our poor Princes! where are you? Oh our beloved Liberty which art gone! when ſhall we ever recever thee again?</hi>
                  </q> I believed theſe had been Souls new come into Hell; but a Devil himſelf, who was in great pain, told me, that thoſe who made that horrible noiſe, were the <hi>Italian,</hi> and <hi>German</hi> Princes, who apprehended they ſhould loſe all, becauſe the <hi>French</hi> had gone on ſo far, that, in fine, they had ſet their very feet upon the necks of the poor <hi>Spaniards,</hi> and the Embaſſadors of thoſe Princes wandered up and down like Flies to procure Leagues, but to retard a little the immenſe Victories of the <hi>French:</hi> But it was pleaſanter to me to find a certain Daemon (who underſtood Politicks well enough) ſeeing the ſaid Embaſſadors run ſweating up and down, cry out unto them with a loud voice, <q rend="margQuotes">O with reverence to your Lordſhips Character! you are very Fops; you ſhould have cured your diſeaſe at its birth, and not ſtayed till it was grown old, and difficult to be cured.</q> In the mean time, I ſaid to my Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtant, Let us go on to diſpatch our buſineſs, and leave the care of theſe intanglements to the Princes, that are like to loſe by it; ſo mending our pace, we went out of that place, and came into a large path, crouded with an infinite company of people, who were travelling, and bemoaning their moſt bitter deſtiny, curſing the very Earth that had ſuſtained them; which made the Daemons rage ſo much the more, that with great diligence and care, they employed every one in his Task, and adminiſtred torments and puniſhments, according to the Sentence paſſed upon every one for his faults: But I, who was not to ſuffer there with others, but only to conſider the puniſhments of others, went away with the pace of a new-made Gentleman, obſerving every thing mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutely; and although the ſight was very terrible in it ſelf, yet I found ſome pleaſure
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:50939:27"/>in the variety of that Tragical Scene, becauſe they were ſo equally proportioned. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt others, I obſerved a great company of naked Women, who held one another by the hand, and wringed one another hard: behind them went an innumerable croud of Devils, with Iron Rods in their hands, threatning them, and forcing them to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn back; at which I was much aſtoniſhed, not knowing how to find out the reaſon, why the Devils would not have Women be in Hell. But the Daemon that was with me, eaſed me of this doubt, telling me, that they were married Women, of which kind of perſons, the Devils held there was more need of in the World, than now in Hell. To tell you the truth, this firſt reaſon did not ſatisfie me, thinking it too obſcure; and I told him, I could not believe that married perſons were more neceſſary in the World, than in Hell; becauſe theſe, who were condemned to ſuch pains, had incurred them by their wicked life, and the World was eaſed by the abatement of that miſchief; for from the diminution of wickedneſs ariſeth the increaſe of goodneſs. Then the Devil, who laughed all this while at my words, gave me this anſwer; I did not tell thee, that Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men were neceſſary in the World for the good of it, but for the advantage of Hell, which draws a double profit from Womens living in the World; and I'le tell thee how; firſt, for the cuſtom of bearing Horns, which is grown ſo common amongſt the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils, that it's now thought a ſhame for any one to be without them; and becauſe we Devils have no Wives, who will take the pains to fill our heads with Horns, we are forced on that account, to multiply the number of married Whores, as much as it is poſſible in the World, knowing no other way how to maintain this faſhion which reigns amongſt us, introduced by the fantaſticalneſs of thoſe Painters that will needs have us Horned, which hath occaſioned our taking care, that among the whole Female Sex the Painters Wives ſhould afford us the greateſt ſupply of that ſort of Animals; and now, as ſoon as any Woman's Liberality hath planted Horns on her Husband's fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, a hundred Devils are ready to cut them off; whence no Horns are ever ſeen up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the heads of men, though their Wives be the greateſt Whores in the World. This agreement being made between them, that the Men ſhould preſerve the Roots, and the Devils wear the Branches. Secondly, We are as ambitious as the <hi>Spaniards</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore endeavour to draw the nobleſt prey's into Hell, and becauſe Women are eſteemed vile, and abject Beaſts, therefore we procure with all our power their continuing in the World, by whoſe means alſo the number of the damned is always multiplying: nor let this ſeem ſtrange which I ſay unto thee, O <hi>Roman!</hi> It being a very great truth, that Women are cauſes of the abſolute deſtruction of Men. How many poor Husbands are forced to ſteal, that they might have the liberty to kiſs their own Wives, who will not ſell Matrimonial kiſſes but at the weight of Gold? How many are conſtrained to deſpair, to ſee their multiplicity of Children exceed the conveniency of their Fortune? and that which is worſt of all, that they are Children given to, and not begotten by them. How many men call upon the Devil all the day, becauſe they cannot ſee their Wives by night, they being engaged by promiſe to their ſecret Friends? How many Murders are committed for Women? How many Bankrupts are made by their Luxury? How many Altars are profaned by their pleaſure? How many Poyſons are prepared by Women for their Husbands, being counſelled to it by the unbridled luſts of their Lovers? In fine; let the Women therefore ſtay in the World, ſince it is a great truth, that one Woman there brings a greater profit to the Daemons, than a thouſand can do in Hell.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>This Devil was no fool: But let us leave theſe wicked Women with a miſchief, and paſs on; Whither wenteſt thou afterwards?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>We entred into a place which was all fire, round about which were many Devils in the ſhape of Satyrs; upon every one of which ſate a perſon courted by many Devils, which ſerved as an <hi>Apollyon,</hi> but ſuch an <hi>Apollyon,</hi> as was agreeable to the quality of that place. One put certain fiery Spurs on their feet, others blew in their ears the hiſſing of a Serpent; this incenſed them with Sulphur and Pitch; and another gave them Venom and Poyſon to eat, and every one was mighty buſie to ſhew themſelves meritorious Courtiers of thoſe perſons on horſe-back in the form of Women, upon thoſe Satyrs;
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:50939:27"/>and there were millions of theſe perſons all ſerved in the ſame manner: but that which I found moſt ſtrange, was, to ſee them all without eyes; and my amazement was ſo great, becauſe I knew not what it ſignified: my thoughts this while boiled with infinite imaginations; and I ſearched about for the reaſon of ſuch a change: I believed that theſe might be that ſort of Men, who with many laſcivious looks had fallen in love in Churches, in the preſence of the Sacrament of the Altar, as is ſeen every day in <hi>Rome;</hi> whence I eſteemed it a very ſuitable puniſhment for ſuch kind of perſons to be depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived of their eyes-ſight. Again, I imagined that theſe were ſuch as had been curious in prying into the actions of others, and as a Caſtigation fit for that, I ſuppoſed they were condemned to have their eyes pluckt out: But none of theſe thoughts ſatisfying me, I begg'd a particular account of the moſt complaiſant Daemon, that I ſaw there, who anſwered me thus; Thoſe whom thou ſeeſt us ſerve with ſo much Infernal Magnificence, are the moſt Reverend <hi>Fathers of the Inquiſition,</hi> to whom we are much obliged, having with their rigorous Tyranny forbidden the Reading of the Sacred Scriptures in the Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar Tongue; which is that, which moſt perfectly inſtructs thoſe Men, who underſtand it in their duty, and turns them from evil, filling and repleniſhing Heaven, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peopling Hell; which we here being very ſenſible of, have found out this invention; <hi>viz.</hi> to oblige the Popes under other pretences to introduce the Inquiſition into the Church, and to aſſiſt the Inquiſitors continually, to ſerve us as Inſtruments to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh our main deſign, which is the peopling Hell, and diſpeopling Heaven of its Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants, which our good Friends and Companions the Fathers Inquiſitors help us not a little in, whilſt they are the cauſe, that many thouſands in the World live in utter Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance by being prohibited the Reading of the Sacred Scriptures: So that the people, not being able to know their duty, wander out of the way, believing they live well, when they live wickedly. Beſides this, the Fathers the Inquiſitors forbid the Reading of all Books, which diſcover the Vices of the Eccleſiaſticks, which is the ground of two miſchiefs, the one in obliging the people to imagine the greateſt enormities and defects of thoſe who ſhould be Looking-glaſſes to the common people of Chriſtendom to be Virtues; the other in flattering the Eccleſiaſticks, who being ſafe from receiving any affront or ſhame from the people, who are forbidden by a rigorous Edict, either to ſpeak ill, or to think ill of the wickedneſs of the Eccleſiaſticks, they remain plunged in gluttony and luſt, and an hundred thouſand diſſoluteneſſes contrary to the Laws of the God of Heaven. In fine, the profit which the Inquiſitors bring to this place is incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible, whoſe eyes we therefore put out, leſt they ſhould read that themſelves which they debar others from; for they would be ſure, if they did but look into thoſe Books which they prohibit others, to renounce the Inquiſition themſelves, and perceive the error which brings ſo many to Hell, and ſo much miſchief to Chriſtianity.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Truly I believe, that this reſtraint from Writing againſt, and Reading of the Vices of the Eccleſiaſticks, makes them not a little proud, believing themſelves greater than they are, in deſpite of what they know themſelves to be.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>The Inquiſition was not introduced by thoſe Popes, who piouſly ruled the Church, but by thoſe Eccleſiaſticks who would live in the Church, as <hi>Sardanapalus</hi> did in the World: whilſt the Church-men were holy, and zealous in the Divine Service, and Edifiers of the people, there was no ſpeech of the <hi>Inquiſition</hi> in the Church; and yet the Hereſies, againſt which they ſay the Inquiſition was ſet up, had more vigour at that time than they have now. But, no ſooner did the Eccleſiaſticks begin to degenerate from their Priſtine State, nay, from the very nature of their Character, but they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thought themſelves of bringing in the Inquiſition, to bridle the mouths of the people from publiſhing thoſe Vices, which they had embraced with ſo much licentiouſneſs: an evident ſign that the end of thoſe, who invented the Inquiſition, hath not been to throw down Hereſie, but to keep the people in awe, that they might not ſo much as murmure at the impiety of the Eccleſiaſticks: Whereat the Religious taking courage, do ſin with ſo much liberty, that ſin in them ſeems to be grown to a natural habitude; and
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:50939:28"/>the poor people dare do no leſs than ſanctifie the Vices of the Eccleſiaſticks, leſt they ſhould fall Victims to the cruelty of the Inquiſition. If the people had liberty to ſpeak and to write againſt the Scandals, which the Eccleſiaſticks commit in the face of the Church, aſſuredly theſe things would be amended, that they might not be reproached, and trampled upon by the people: but the Inquiſitors will not endure it, wherefore I do believe they have made an agreement with the Devil to fill up Hell with damned Souls.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>I have heard, that the true reaſon of forbidding Books, is nothing elſe but an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of the purſe, and of the brain: of the brain, becauſe by keeping others from read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, they encloſe amongſt themſelves that which ought to be in common to all; by which means picking out from forbidden Books what the Labours of deceaſed Authors have compoſed, they make uſe of them to enrich their own Sermons. And I my ſelf knew a certain Inquiſitor that paſſed for a famous Preacher, who extracted all the fine juice of his Sermons from ſome forbidden Books, changing nothing but the names, and I know not what figures: And indeed in the prohibited Books, the fineſt concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in the World are to be found, to expoſe Vice, it being neceſſary to make that common, which the Inquiſitors intended a ſecret; and for the pecuniary intereſt, men are afraid of prohibited Books, becauſe ſome ſcrupulous perſons, out of fear of Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication, as ſoon as they hear of an Edict againſt any Book, carry it to the Inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, and the Father Inquiſitor, or his Vicar, after they have drawn all the juice our of it, ſell it at a dear rate to ſome ſtranger; finding, to colour ſuch a ſale, a hundred pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences, which all the Inquiſitors abound in.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>If thou hadſt ever obſerved, my dear <hi>Marforius,</hi> the particularities of forbidden Books, as I have done, thou wouldſt be aſtoniſhed. Doſt thou believe that thoſe Popes are zealous of the Honour of God, and that the Cardinals fear God, or thoſe Inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, who exclaim againſt thoſe Books which publiſh the Vices of the Church-men. Alas! the Popes, who have zeal in their hearts; the Cardinals, who have Souls pure from the ordures, which corrupt the Eccleſiaſtical State; and the Inquiſitors, who walk in the ways of our Lord, mock at thoſe Satyrs, and Libels, and Hiſtories, which correct the Vices of others; ſaying, with a heart full of zeal, We muſt correct Vices, and ſo take away from Detractours the cauſe of their murmuring and writing. Behold all that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Prelates ſay, when they hear talk of prohibited Books, and why ſo, but becauſe they find not their Conſciences offended by thoſe Books? The Horſe, who feels the Spurs in his ſides, bounces, runs away, and throws his Rider. The ſame thing falls out with the Eccleſiaſticks; for thoſe who find their Conſciences prickt with the prohibited Books, leap, exclaim, run up and down, clamour, and, one would think the Devil were at the tail of them; but thoſe who are not ſpurr'd in their Conſciences, knowing very well that the Books do not ſpeak of them, having given no occaſion, laugh at every thing, feigning to know nothing, not needing to take notice of that which doth not at all concern them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>'Tis certain, the thing is juſt, as thou ſayeſt; and I know a <hi>German Canon,</hi> who goes crying up and down the Streets, and the Courts of <hi>Cardinals,</hi> againſt all thoſe Books, which reprove the Church-men's Vices, and not without reaſon, whilſt in every page of the prohibited Books, he finds the picture of his Life, he being a <hi>Sodomite,</hi> a <hi>Simoniack,</hi> a <hi>Cut-throat,</hi> a <hi>Seducer,</hi> a <hi>Whore-maſter,</hi> a <hi>Pimp,</hi> ſcandalous, and a ſworn Enemy of his <hi>Breviary;</hi> therefore ſeeing he cannot correct himſelf, becauſe his nature is too much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praved and inclined to evil, he beats his brain to ſmother all thoſe Books, and thoſe Authors, who deſcribe him juſt as he is.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>I know what Canon thou ſpeakeſt of; I am acquainted with him; he lives in <hi>Rome;</hi> but the greateſt of his Vices is, that he is a great Spy.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Thou haſt hit him: it is the very ſame. But I pray thee let us return into the Chamber of the Inquiſitors.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>No, I am juſt going out of it; for with theſe Kinds of People, the leſs you have to do with them, the better: So that as ſoon as we had obſerved this magnificent In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:50939:28"/>I went forward, going out at another very little door, and ſo narrow, that <hi>I</hi> was fain to draw in my very breath to get out the eaſier; the way, tho dark, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducted me to a much more obſcure Gallery, where was a Man walking, and mourning in certain Accents, which forced compaſſion; whoſe deſpairing ſorrow, made my very heart melt, and the more, becauſe I could diſcern nothing but his voice, and the motion of his body. Beſides, when he perceived me to draw near him, he burſt out the louder, ſaying, <hi>O wretched me! that I ſhould ever have Damned my ſelf for the evil actions of others!</hi> which made me believe he was ſome poor <hi>Confeſſer;</hi> ſince the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors uſually damn themſelves by taking upon them other folks ſins: ſo I endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to conſole him, as if he had been ſuch a one; but he weeping more bitterly, thus an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered me; What, a Confeſſor! I am a miſerable Book-ſeller, who am condemned to theſe torments, for having Traded in other men's Works: Then drawing a little nearer him, I began to call to mind who he was, and I no ſooner knew him, but I began to admire the Effects of the Divine Juſtice, becauſe he was one of thoſe Stationers who Print and Sell the moſt ſcandalous, profane, railing, and wicked Books, that the Devil himſelf could have ſuggeſted. In fine; his Shop was a Brothel-houſe of the wickedeſt and moſt laſcivious ſort of Books. Notwithſtanding, I ſeemed to pity him, not to put him into higher deſpairs; but he eaſily perceived that my compaſſion was but feigned; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon he ſaid unto me, What ſhould one do? This is the uſual miſery of our Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, that we Stationers are not condemned like other men, for our own wicked works, but ſuffer theſe Acute Torments, for the wicked works of others. He would have run on, but a Devil ſtopt his mouth, by burning leaves of old Books at his noſe, which made an inſufferable ſtink; at which I ſaid within my ſelf; If Book-ſellers be condemned to ſuch bitter pains, for only ſelling ſuch Books, what the Devil ſhall be done with the Authors who Compoſe them?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Was there no other Stationer then but this? I very much wonder at that, and the more, becauſe ordinarily the Book-ſellers and the Authors underſtand one another very well; ſo that I ſhould have thought they might have been altogether.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>I am alſo of that Opinion, that there were more Stationers in this place, but no great number; for there are but few that meddle with ſuch fort of ware, and thoſe moſt commonly ſuch, who have a large Conſcience, that is to ſay, none, or an intereſted one; but yet there are ſome, who do it to ſerve their Friend; but that ſervice is never ſeparate from intereſt. Then, as to Authors, I will tell thee, that having asked the poor Stationer, if he did not know whither ſo many Authors went, who blot ſo much Paper with their ſcribbles, he made me lean my ear to an Iron wall, which was on the right ſide, with a little window in it, which I no ſooner drew near too, but I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived a braying like that which Aſſes make, but much louder, and more lamentable; ſo that I was amazed, and wholly beſides my ſelf; and the rather, becauſe the Devil told me, that all theſe were Authors of Books; and this intelligence encreaſed my confuſion; for, it ſeemed to me, that there were more Authors of Books in Hell, than men in the whole Univerſe. Whilſt I earneſtly endeavoured to thruſt in my head fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to ſee if I could diſcover any of my acquaintance; a Daemon, who kept that Gate, entreated me, that I would be pleaſed to come in; and I anſwering him, I would: He opened the Gate, which, tho' not very large, I entred in convemently, together with that other Daemon who had the charge of accompanying me. At the firſt I imagined that there were divers Orders of Authors, and by conſequence, divers puniſhments; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſought for <hi>Divines, Philoſophers, Hiſtorians, Politicians, Mathematicians, Lawyer's, Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mancers, Caſuiſts, &amp; Antichriſtian States-men,</hi> in ſeveral Apartments. But not ſeeing any dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, I asked the reaſon of the Daemon, who anſwered me, that amongſt Authors they could not make a difference of perſons, or of matter, tho' the matter and the perſons were different, becauſe in Hell, Authors are condemned, not for the Works they had Printed, but for the end that moved them to Compoſe them. Then I prayed him to inform me of the end; he told me briefly; that Authors had no other end in writing, but Intereſt and Ambition, which were the very two Puries ſent by <hi>Lucifer</hi> into the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:50939:29"/>World, to draw thouſands of Souls into Hell; and becauſe theſe two Furies did make their Neſts in the breaſts of Writers, we ſee more of them in Hell, than of any other perſons: Add to this, that there muſt needs be more Writers damned, than other perſons, becauſe they all write to make others be damned. Beſides, they ſpend their time, ſome in ſeeking out new conceits, inventions and ſpeculations, and others in lies, fancies, and impoſtures; whereby they have no ſenſe left to know the pure nature of that God, whom they feign only to adore in outward appearance.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>I believe that Writers are damned, becauſe they empty their brains too much in deſiring to teach others, that there remains not a dram of underſtanding in them, to know their own duty, whence the moſt of them become vicious.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>I believe ſo too: Now, whilſt the Daemon was informing me of theſe things, I went up and down, obſerving the quality of thoſe pains which theſe miſerable damned Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors ſuffered: And firſt, they conſtrained them to eat all thoſe Books they had made, and then, without waiting for the natural time of digeſtion, they drew them all out again at their breeches. I found this proceeding very unreaſonable; and told my ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timent to one of thoſe Devils, who anſwered; I was a very fool to undertake to give Rules to Hell; adding further, that this was a chaſtiſement proportionable to their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts; becauſe, as theſe Writers brought forth their Books as ſoon as they had begotten them in their fancy, without ripening them in their Judgment; ſo it was very conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient they ſhould ſhit them out before they were maturely digeſted. The other puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was, that the Devils held certain Iron Combs, with which they did not only comb, but tear the hands of thoſe miſerable Authors, that it forced compaſſion to ſee and hear them cry out in deſpairing terms; O curſed be the day that I ever took Pen in hand! Oh curſed be he that ſold me the Ink! Oh curſed be the Paper that I made uſe of! Oh curſed be thoſe Book ſellers that bought my Manuſcripts! Oh curſed be the Standiſh that ſtood upon my Desk! I wondred again at theſe Curſes, and ſaid to the Daemon; Methinks theſe damned Souls deceived themſelves, for they ought rather to curſe the time taken up in their Studies, and loſt in their compoſure, and not the Pen and Ink, which are but the acceſſory Inſtruments: To which the Daemon anſwered me, That I was more out than they, becauſe the Authors could not curſe their Studies, becauſe they knew very well they had never ſtudied for them: Wherefore they would not rave againſt that Occupation which they had never uſed: But that which moſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported, which he told me with the beſt grace, and I did not find to be falſe, tho' he was a Devil, was, that it was very certain, that the greateſt part of thoſe that write, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver went to any other School but that of Imagination.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>But tell me, did not the Devil give thee an Anſwer particularly to the Curry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>combs with which they curried the hands?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>He told me, that in this laſt Age, the Art of Writing was reduced to a certain itch in the hands, whilſt the Authors writ with their hands, but not with their hearts, with words, and not with judgment; and therefore the Devils ſtudied how to take off that Itch from their hands, becauſe their hearts and their judgments had no guilt in the compoſing of ſo many ſopperies which are Printed in the World. Whilſt the Devil was thus informing me, I did not forbear going forward, that I might the better ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the torments of theſe moſt miſerable Authors: when I heard my ſelf called by ſo doleful a voice, that I was forced, tho' I did not intend it; to draw near, I knew him to be <hi>Ferrante Pallavicino,</hi> which was nothing ſtrange to me, becauſe I had ever imagined, that he having lived like an Heretick, and written like an Atheiſt, he could have no other Apartment but that where Atheiſts and Hereticks are doomed together. He who ſtill kept his uſual nature, no ſooner ſaw me, but delighting to vent himſelf with his Friends, began to ſay to me; O <hi>Paſquin!</hi> how I repent me, (tho' I know how little repentance ſignifies) for having written ſuch large Volumes of Satyrs. Who could ever have thought, that a man who never had any other end, but to correct the Vices of the Eccleſiaſticks, and bring back the Church into the purity of its Primitive Inſtitutions, ſhould be rewarded with ſuffering ſuch bitter pains? What
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:50939:29"/>elſe is found in my Books, but the contempt of Vices? and yet the correcting them hath brought me nothing but miſchief. I anſwered him, Thoſe who write to correct the vices of others, need firſt to puniſh their body ſeverely to correct their own. St. <hi>Paul</hi> diſciplined himſelf in the night, and then in the day exclaimed againſt the vices of the people: from whence the Church received great benefit. But what fruit canſt thou bring with thy ſatyrizing againſt the vices of the <hi>Barbarini,</hi> if thou walloweſt in thy diſſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs as Swine do in the mire? In fine, my dear Seignior <hi>Ferrante,</hi> they who would write to purge others, had need firſt to purge themſelves.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Might it pleaſe the Heavens, that all Writers were like to <hi>Pallavicino;</hi> for he writ with a Foundation, and with Learning, whereas others write without either of them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>That which I ſaid to <hi>Pallavicino,</hi> I ſaid to all others that heard me; it being cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, that they had much more need of it than he: and truly I was diſpleaſed to ſee him in ſuch a place; therefore, knowing I could give him no relief, I turned away, and had gone but a very few ſteps ere I found my ſelf in a place, which I took to be the Arſenal of Hell, ſeeing the Devils were ſo intent in forging Inſtruments to torment the poor Souls which were there; and tormented them with ſo much deſpite, that the very ſight of it were ſufficient to terrifie half the World. At firſt I imagined that this was <hi>Judas</hi> his Hell, and the Crucifiers of Chriſt, not being able to imagine that there could be any others that ſhould deſerve ſo great puniſhment: But having asked one of thoſe Devils which were at work, he ſlouted at this fancy of mine, and ſaid to me, What, <hi>Judas!</hi> What, <hi>Judas!</hi> Theſe are Phyſicians, Chyrurgeons, Apothecaries, Poyſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, Aſſaſſins, and Executioners, and ſuch ſort of people; againſt whom we find our ſelves obliged to uſe all our ſtrength, to revenge ſo many wrongs that they have done to us. What wrongs, ſaid I? nay, you are rather beholden to ſuch kind of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, who beſtowed all their induſtry to diſpeople the World of Mankind, to ſtock Hell the ſooner. Look, cryed he, here is a <hi>Roman</hi> come to inſtruct the Devil in his own Trade! We are not angry that theſe Executioners of the World do labour to empty it of Men; but we are much diſpleaſed to ſee them deſtroyed before their time; for, it is more delightful to us to have Souls come continually freſh and freſh into Hell. And yet the Phyſicians with Preſcriptions, Apothecaries with their Doſes, Chyrurgeons with their Bleedings, the Poyſoners with their Doſes, the Aſſaſſins with their Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheries, and the Executioners with their Axes, do ſo much, ſay ſo much, contrive ſo much, that they kill more Men in a day, than we tempt in a year. It ſeems an incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible thing, that one Phyſician is more able to diſpatch a Body, than fifty Devils are to gain a Soul. But that which moſt concerns us is, that we would have Men live a little longer time, that they might ſo much the more multiply the number of their ſins, that Hell might alſo multiply the quality of their puniſhments; but for all this, Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians, Apothecaries and Chyrurgeons muſt have their will, who are wont to kill folks from the Cradle. Before this great croud of Raſcals ſwarmed in the World, Men lived an hundred, and two hundred years, we enjoying all that while the pleaſure of ſeeing them ſin daily: But, ſince theſe Devils of Phyſicians, Apothecaries and Chyrur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geons were introduced into the World, Men are rarely ſeen to live to eighty years, they killing them ſo very young. Yet they do not deſign directly to kill them, but to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long their ſickneſs, that by the length of time they might multiply the number of their Fees; but by ſeeking to ſpin out the diſeaſe, they deſtroy the Body before the time. But hear whether we have not reaſon to envy the fortune of theſe human ſlaughterers: we are all deſtinated to Murder; that is, we Devils the Soul, and Doctors, Apotheca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and Chyrurgeons the Body by all ways imaginable; now we who kill the Soul, which is the more Noble part, have nothing; and they who kill the Body, which is the Inferiour part, are paid with a liberal hand; This would make, not only the Devils, but the very Saints mad alſo, to ſee a Phyſician paid ſo well, that with one word kills a Prince; and we Devils beſtow ſo great fatigue to deſtroy a Soul without the leaſt gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification. In fine, it extreamly pleaſes us in Hell, to torment the Souls of thoſe,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:50939:30"/>that with ſo many herbs, weapons and poiſons torment the bodies of Men.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Let's go to other matters, <hi>Paſquin;</hi> for, the farther we get from Phyſicians, the better; for they ſtink above ground of the odour which remains of the Urine and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crements which often catches the Noſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>That little ill flavour coſt the Patients Purſe a good deal of Money, Brother. We paſſed then from that place into another, much more ſpatious, girt round with very high walls of fire, ſo that it ſeemed impoſſible to get thorough them; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I had reſolved only to look on the outſide; ſo, coming as near as I could, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to hear more doleful, frightful, and deſpairing Voices; therefore being very deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to know the Voice of any one of them, the better to underſtand the Quality of the damned, which that place was full of, I ſtopt a little, and liſtned with all attention, yet could hear nothing but a confuſion of Voices, which cryed, <hi>O that I had ſaid over the Divine Office! O that I had gone in good time into the Quire! O that I had not robb'd the Treaſury Church! O that I had celebrated Maſs with Devotion! O that I had not writ ſo many falſe Letters to my Superiors! O that I had lived more retired in the Cloyſter! O that I had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver brought Whores and Catamites into my Chamber! O that I had not Gamed with Seculars! O that I had not defrauded the Alms-boxes! O that I had refrained from giving ſo many pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Scandals! O that I had not been ſo Mortal an Enemy to the Breviary! O that I had not had ſo much hatred to Obedience! O that I had not been ſo ambitious of Offices! O that I had not ſo often broke</hi> Lent! <hi>O that I had contented my ſelf with the Religious life I entred into! O that I had not buſied my ſelf with worldly Affairs! O that I had not kept that Infamous Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man in my houſe, under the title of a Niece! O that I had been more aſſiduous in the Cure of Souls which was given me in charge! O that I had not ſold the ſacred Utenſils to put into my Purſe! O that I had not transformed my ſelf from a Religious perſon to a Merchant! O that I had been more meek and humble! O that I had not been ſo ſlothful in the ſervice of God! O that I had not made a mock of Hell and Heaven! O that I my Soul had been diveſted of worldly Paſſions! O that I had not done this and that!</hi> Theſe were all the ſounds which eccho'd in my ears, which quickly made me underſtand, that this was the Hell for Prieſts and Fryers; ſo that informing my ſelf at large of that Daemon who attended me, and he aſſuring me it was ſo, I prayed him to do ſo much for me, as to help me to get in, that I might make my boaſt, that I had ſeen the Prieſts and Fryers tormented in Hell, who do ſo torment all the People in the Univerſe, and, more than that, under pretence of their good.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>For my part, I could have bated that curioſity, and have given ſuch a Race of People to the Devil.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>So one might have done, but all men cannot: However, the Daemon ſatisfied my curioſity; for he found a hole, which lookt like that of a Sink, at which we went in, finding never a door, which obliged me to ask him the reaſon of it; and he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered me, That as the Fryers went out of their Cloyſters by an out-let of their own boring, without the leave of their Superiours; ſo they went into Hell without any ones perceiving them, there being only ſome certain holes for Prieſts to go in at; to which I anſwered, That I wondred there were any holes in the Manſions of Prieſts and Fryers, ſince they ſtudied nothing elſe but to ſtop them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>But how could you get in at ſuch a ſtrait hole? were you not in danger of ſticking in the midſt of it?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>Alas! the holes that the Prieſts go in at, are big enough for a Horſe. Now when we were got in, I was at my wits end, becauſe indeed I thought I ſhould have found nothing but Fryers and Prieſts, or at leaſt Prieſts, Fryers and Devils together all clothed alike, without any difference: And that which made me think ſo, was, the uniformity I knew there was between the Religious and the Devils; becauſe, as the Devils ſtudy nothing elſe but to enrich Hell with ſpoils; ſo theſe Religious do nothing but procure the ſtuffing of their Cloyſters with other peoples goods: Beſides, I have ever heard thoſe Women, who uſed to have a commerce with any Fryer, reproached with being Hackneys to the Devil, an evident ſign that the Fryers are very Devils. But I found
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:50939:30"/>it quite contrary to what I thought; for, the Fryers, and the Prieſts, were in the ſame Habits they had uſed in the World; and the Devils, who tormented them, were dreſſed in the Habits of Women and Boys; which I wondred more at, than what I had ſeen at firſt, and enquired of the Daemon the reaſon of it, who told me, I ought not to be ſcandalized to ſee the Religious ſuffer in their own Habits, for having committed many of their Knaveries and Scandals, under the ſecurity of the Reſpect which is given to that Habit, it being but juſt they ſhould ſuffer under thoſe Habits, which had cloaked ſo great guilts and wickedneſſes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>To ſpeak the truth indeed, without reflecting upon the Religious, who really fear God; the Habit cloaks great Vices, and hides intolerable ſins; but what particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars did the Daemons tell thee concerning their being transformed into the ſhape of Women and Boys?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>They told me, That this was done to make the Religious to endure the infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal pains with the greater courage, and gave me this reaſon for it; That the Devils, knowing the nature of the Religious inclined to do all manner of wickedneſs, and ſuffer injuries, villanies, affronts, ſcorns, and torments, for the love of Women and Boys, thought ſit to metamorphize themſelves into thoſe ſpecies, which had had the greateſt praedominancy over them. Mean while I went on viſiting thoſe miſerable damned perſons, to my great amazement, knowing an infinite number of theſe Fryers, whom I had ſeen in <hi>Rome,</hi> paſſing for ſo many <hi>Macarius's</hi> and <hi>Hilarions:</hi> Particularly I ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved one Cappuchin, who ſuffered intolerable pains, to whom I drew near, to ſee if he were the ſame that I had known in <hi>Rome,</hi> and found him to be the very man; who had the reputation of eating nothing but roots of herbs, ſeaſoned with aſhes, diſciplining himſelf all night before a Crucifix, and ſpent all the day in Prayers and Oriſons; and, in fine, was eſteemed a <hi>Compendium</hi> of Miracles; ſeeing him in that place, held up my hands, with all thoſe geſtures uſual to thoſe who behold ſome won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful thing fallen out contrary to the courſe of Nature; which the Devil perceiving, ſaid thus unto me; O ſtranger! if thou didſt but know, of what Leaven the Religious are moulded, you would not think it ſo ſtrange to ſee them ſuffer what they ſo juſtly deſerve. Hypocriſie, which is ſo hateful to Heaven, hath made its Neſt in the Cloy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Religious, which never do any good, they are not forced to, and contrary to their Sentiments, which are naturally diſpoſed to wickedneſs; but I will tell thee no more, becauſe, under the name of Hypocriſie, all their lewdneſs is comprehended, couzening the World with Exteriour Goodneſs, and Heaven with Interiour Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. To which I only replyed, That I would take an Oath I would never believe again the falſe Appearances of the Religious.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>And I will promiſe there the ſame; but I prethee tell me, whether any of the Order of Saint <hi>Dominick</hi> was in that place?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>Whether there were any there! Alas! there was ſo great a number of them, that the Arithmeticians could not be able to count them; yet I could not poſſibly know any of them, by reaſon of the puniſhment they underwent, ſo different from all the reſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>But how ſo? Did every Religious Order then ſuffer a diſtinct pain?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>Yes; and the pain of the <hi>Dominican</hi> Fathers was, that a Devil rid upon every one of them; and it was good ſport, to ſee thoſe good Fathers ſcrambling along-upon all four, and the Devil ſitting aſtride them with a Whip in his Paw, laſhing their buttocks, and at the ſame time checking them with his Bridle which the poor Beaſts had in their mouths. I had the curioſity to ask what was the reaſon, why theſe Fathers only were appointed ſuch a puniſhment? to which Query the Daemon anſwered me; that theſe Fathers were ſo accuſtomed to lord it over all the World, that they were prouder than all the reſt of the Fraternities put together. So that <hi>Lucifer</hi> emulating the Pride of the ſaid Fathers, had condemned them to be ſo humbled in Hell, becauſe they had been ſo exalted on Earth: And I, having begg'd again to know why they were ſo whipt on their buttocks, and ſo hard bridled in their mouths; he added, that it
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:50939:31"/>proceeded from the great indulgence they had given their back-ſides, which had never had any ſcourage of Diſcipline, which all other Fryers are wont to have. O! ſaid I, this is new to me, tho' I am ſure enough, that theſe Fathers have Pride radicated in their very bones, yet I never thought that their Pride prevailed againſt their Diſcipline. Yes, replyed the Devil, becauſe the Effect of Diſcipline is to mortifie the body, and theſe good Fathers uſed to ſtrut up and down in Cities like Peacocks, turning their breeches firſt to the right hand, and afterwards to the left. I, who had ſeen theſe Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers walk up and down in that manner a thouſand times, ſaid no more, but that his deſcription of them was very true. Yet I ſupplicated to have a further information of the Bridles that they had in their mouths, and was anſwered, that they being uſed to ſtop the mouths of all ſorts of perſons, by their Tyrannical Tribunal of the Inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſo that it appeared to the World, as if the liberty of diſcourſe was baniſhed out of Chriſtendom, by the Authority of the holy Office, which the ſaid Fryers held in their hands, purpoſely to ſtop all folks mouths; therefore in Hell they are condemned to ſuffer the ſame puniſhment, which they make others endure upon Earth. Beſides, they deſerve to have the Bridle put in their mouths, for having tattled ſo much againſt the immaculate Conception of the Virgin. I would not ſtop any longer to obſerve the torments of theſe Fryers, but went on, to remark the ſufferings of others, which were of a different nature. The <hi>Franciſcans</hi> were diſputing Precedency with one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; every Order amongſt them deſiring to be the firſt; and at the ſame time the <hi>Cappuchins,</hi> and the <hi>Reformed,</hi> who had been of the poor Orders, were reviling and railing at the <hi>Conventuals,</hi> who defended themſelves, by proving that their Poverty was compelled, and faſtned on their Habit, and not in their heart; and the <hi>Recollects,</hi> who were neither of the poor, nor of the rich, were enraged againſt both of them, and left not a Curſe that was ever found out, unuttered againſt them<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>; but the moſt to be noted was, that the Devils, who ſtill fomented this diſcord, when they ſaw them well heated with diſdain, interpoſed and ran in between them, and with certain Iron Bars parted them, and ended the Fray, ſaying, Remember that ye are <hi>Minoriſts.</hi> 'Tis true, the <hi>Recollects</hi> were exempted from this puniſhment, but the Devils, in lieu of Baſtinading them, as they did the others, hung them up by the throats; and I, having deſired to know the reaſon, was anſwered, that they juſtly merited to be uſed like Thieves, for having ſtollen ſo many Convents from the other <hi>Franciſcans;</hi> the whilſt I turned to the other ſide, and ſaw the <hi>Auguſtinians,</hi> who ſuffered torments equal to the <hi>Franciſcans;</hi> ſo that I cared not to fix any longer on ſuch Objects; and the rather, becauſe they were ſo near unto the <hi>Minimes,</hi> which are the <hi>Franciſcans</hi> of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> the laſt Order that came into the World.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>How is it poſſible? What I are thoſe Fathers, who are all Charity, in Hell?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>Why, they go the ſurer into Hell, for having relyed too much upon their Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, as one of thoſe Daemons told me, who was entruſted to torment thoſe Fathers, and their torment was to eat the flames of fire, which was a ſort of meat, that I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived very well, was not a little nauſeous to them (tho' they were obliged to it) by their making ſuch ill-favoured faces, as ſick men do, that are to take a loathſom Potion; and they had reaſon, for the Devils uſed no great Ceremony towards them, in putting ſuch Viands in their mouths, but threw the flames in with Pots and Kettles, without either Ladles or Spoons. I thought at firſt, that the Devils had done this on a good deſign; to wit, to digeſt ſo much Oyl, ſo much crude Herbs, ſo much Fiſh ill dreſt, ſo much unwholeſom Pulſe, and ſo much other Lenten fare, which theſe Fryers uſed to ſtuff their bellies with in their Cloyſters: But the Daemon, which I ſpoke to thee of before, told me, that amongſt all the Religious Orders, theſe had the greateſt need of being inwardly heated, all the fire of Charity being extinguiſhed in their hearts, by having too much inflamed the Walls of their Cloyſters with the Device and Emblem of <hi>Charity;</hi> and ſo priding themſelves in ſetting up ſuch a <hi>Motto,</hi> that it is ſet over the very doors of their Kitchins, and Privy-houſes; and at the rate they inflame their Walls with Charity, they exhauſt it out of their hearts, neither regarding the Religious, nor
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:50939:31"/>the Poor, driving all from the Gates of their Cloyſters; ſo that we have taken a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution to enkindle their hearts with all the warmth our fire can give them. The Daemon ſaying nothing further about this particularity, ſuffered me to go wandring on in the Rode, where I met with nothing but <hi>Fryers</hi> of all ſorts, on whom I atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively fixt my eyes, not out of any Devotion I had towards them, but only to ſee if I could find any <hi>Jeſuits</hi> among them, on which all my thoughts were bent; but the more I pryed about, ſo much the greater was the confuſion of my ſpirit; that, having already ſeen thouſands, and ten thouſands of <hi>Franciſcans, Auguſtinians, Carmelites, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minicans, Regular Canons;</hi> in fine, <hi>Monks</hi> and <hi>Fryers,</hi> of all kinds, notwithſtanding I had not ſeen one <hi>Jefuite:</hi> whereupon I threw my ſelf, without either fear or wit, into the midſt of theſe miſerable wretches, to find them out: At laſt I diſcovered at a great diſtance certain black Habits like unto thoſe of the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> and ſo I turned my feet that way, hoping to find them in that place, but found my ſelf much deceived; for theſe were the <hi>Theatines,</hi> and the <hi>Sommaſchs,</hi> who do likewiſe make a profeſſion to imitate and Ape the <hi>Jeſuits;</hi> and drawing near to one of theſe Fathers, to inquire ſome news of the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> he could tell me nothing at all; but complained after a ſtrange rate againſt thoſe Fathers, ſaying, That they the <hi>Sommaſchs</hi> and <hi>Theatines</hi> were ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> for their being in Hell, ſeeing the moſt of them were damned for following of the Jeſuitical Maxims. Mean while I imagined that the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> being neither <hi>Prieſts</hi> nor <hi>Fryers,</hi> nor of the World, nor Religious men; that perhaps they would be placed in the middle between both: Whereupon, after I had well obſerved all the <hi>Fryers</hi> and <hi>Monks,</hi> and all the Religious of every other ſort and Order, I paſſed calmly on into the Prieſts Apartment, but their number was ſo very great, that I was forced to ſtay above two hours, before I could get in, and yet in that place there were only <hi>Maſs-Prieſts,</hi> for the others were intermixt with the <hi>Fryers.</hi> Then I began to ſtare every one in the face, and asking every one of them whether he were a <hi>Jeſuit,</hi> they anſwered in ſuch a manner, as if I had injured them mightily By that Queſtion; ſo, having ſeen the <hi>Prieſts,</hi> the <hi>Canons,</hi> and the <hi>Abbots</hi> tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented (all of them) with very ſharp pains, I paſt to the reſidence of the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> and the <hi>Arch-Biſhops,</hi> having loſt the very hopes of ever ſeeing the <hi>Jeſuits;</hi> for they did al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways ſo contemn the <hi>Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Arch-Biſhops,</hi> ſcorning ſuch dignities, as things infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour to their Merits; that it could not be thought they would endure them to be there amongſt them; ſo that deſpairing that I could not ſee the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> in Hell, I ſet me down upon a Stone, beating my brains, and ſtudying with my ſelf, where the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil theſe <hi>Jeſuits</hi> ſhould be. Perhaps, ſaid I, theſe Fathers pawn the Souls of the dead, to guard the Treaſures they have got by ſo many Stratagems from the living. Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps by the power of the Moneys which they poſſeſs in ſo great an abundance, they have bought the Inheritance of Heaven. Perhaps the Devils leave them in the cuſtody of the Women, who made profeſſion on Earth to be ſuch civil Guardians of that Sex. Whilſt I was roving thus within my ſelf, the Devil, who conducted me, being ſenſible of all, and knowing very well the great paſſion that I had to ſee the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> could not contain from deriding me, yet, not having the heart to ſee me in ſo much ſuſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, told me, that he had found a way how to ſatisfie my curioſity, but it was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite to go very cautiouſly; for the ſeeing of the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> in Hell, was eſteemed a matter of State, becauſe the Devils kept the ſaid Fathers there, meerly out of policy. I replyed, I would do all things he eſteemed neceſſary; whereupon he went before me, and bid me follow him, and ſo we entred into a very ſpacious way, which was ſet on both ſides with great numbers of Devils in ranks one over another, and clothed like the Guards of Kings; ſo that I gathered from thence, we were going to the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace of <hi>Lucifer,</hi> Emperour of Hell, which was too true; for, we had gone but a very few ſteps further, when we came to the Gate of the ſaid Palace, which was guarded by a good number of Souldiers, divided into three Companies of Guards; yet we had no difficulty in getting in; tho' 'tis true that great <hi>Lucifer</hi>'s Uſhers and Grooms met us in the Hall, and told us, that they had preciſe Orders, to carry no Embaſſador
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:50939:32"/>into their Prince, without telling him, who it was, that asked for Audience; and for what cauſe they required it; and therefore the Devil, who was with me, acquainted them with my requeſt, which was to obtain a licence from his Infernal Majeſty, to give me leave to go into the Hell of the <hi>Jeſuits.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>It would not quit the Charge of expoſing ones ſelf to the ſight of ſo great a Prince of Darkneſs, to gain a ſight of theſe Fathers, who boaſt themſelves to be the Light of the World: For my part, I would e'ne have been ſatisfied to hear that they were ſafe in the Devils Clutches.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>The Appetites of Men are very different; I, for my part, would go willingly into Hell, to have the pleaſure of ſeeing one <hi>Jeſuit</hi> in Purgatory. Now, when I was introduced into the preſence of <hi>Lucifer,</hi> who ſate upon a mighty high Throne, made of burning Coals, interwoven with certain flames, which threw out ſparks on all ſides, like a Smiths Forge, I tendred my requeſt to him, which he readily heard; but asked me ſo many Queſtions, that I began a little to repent I had ever thought of the <hi>Jeſuits;</hi> diſcerning very plainly, that he derided my curioſity; nevertheleſs he roſe up, and with his own hands took three Keys which lay under his breech, and gave them to three of the moſt Diabolical Counſellors, that waited about his Throne, commiſſion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them to conduct me to the reſidence of the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> and ſo I was diſmiſt by <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifer,</hi> without ſaying any more to me, but, Go ſatisfie your fooliſh curioſity; and I immediately began to follow thoſe Devils who carryed the Keys, who, without going out of the Royal Palace, conveyed me thro' certain very deep Dens, all full of Aſps and Baſilisks, from whence we paſt into ſo ſtrait an Alley, that we could ſcarce go in it one after another; in the middle of which, there was a door, which was opened with one of the three Keys; and, at the end of this Lane, there was another door, which was likewiſe opened with the ſecond Key; and, entring in there, we found a Draw-bridge guarded by four huge Devils, to whom one of the three Counſellors ſpoke, commanding them by the Authority of <hi>Lucifer,</hi> to let us go in; ſo they fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not inſtantly to let down the Bridge, which we paſſed over; and, not far from thence, we found a great Gate, which was alſo kept by <hi>Lucifer</hi>'s Guards, ſhut on the out-ſide with a great Chain, which was alſo opened with the third Key, and by the Counſellors own hand; who knocked two or three times, and, at the laſt knock, one within came and opened a ſmall Wicket, thro' which he ſpoke to the Counſellors, but I could not hear what they ſaid; but, in fine, the Gate was opened to us, and we entred in, and after that Gate was ſhut again very ſafely: Another leſſer Gate was opened, where we were let in, attended by a dozen of Halberdiers; but two of the Counſellors ſtay'd behind, and only one of them went along with me. We had ſcarce ſet our feet with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in that place, but we began to ſee ſo prodigious a number of <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> that I could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have credited it: They all ſtood with their hands and feet chained up, and with Padlocks in their mouths, that they could not ſpeak; nevertheleſs, they ſuffered no other torments but that of flames, which indeed were very great, but there was not one word heard; for thoſe Devils, which were there to look after them, had no other form, than of the moſt poyſonous Serpents, ſo that there was a moſt exact ſilence ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved. I was ſo preſently ſatisfied concerning the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> that I askt to go out, and reſolved to loſe the very memory of them; therefore I knockt at the Gate, which was opened, and we returned back in the ſelf ſame manner that we came: But my cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſity engaged me to beſeech one of thoſe Counſellors, as we travelled, to know what was the cauſe that made the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> be kept in ſo ſtrict a cuſtody in Hell; deprived of the very ſatisfaction of converſing with the other damned Souls? To which Queſtion, the Counſellor anſwered me, in Political Sickneſſes 'tis convenient to make uſe of Violent Remedies, to exterminate the ariſing evil, elſe the Wound rankling, might render the Diſeaſe incurable. Now, we who perceived from the very firſt that the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> appeared in the World, that they had no other deſign, than aſpiring to the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Monarchy, whence to arrive to the end of their intention, they have not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born trying Impoſſibilites, joyning the <hi>Morals, Speculatives, Rhetoricks</hi> and <hi>Politicks</hi>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:50939:32"/>together, to gain upon the minds of Princes and People: and tho' at firſt fight it does appear as if they had obtained their deſign; yet nevertheleſs, if you ſearch into the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom of what they have done, you will find that theſe Fathers have obtained the abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Monarchy over all the Kingdoms of <hi>Europe,</hi> whilſt they command the Princes in counſelling them, and impoſe Laws on the People in confeſſing them, and lord it over other folks wealth, in ſeeming to deſpiſe their own. All theſe things being perceived by our <hi>Lucifer,</hi> who watches over the free Monarchy of Hell with an accurate Vigilancy, that he may not fall into that Error which the Princes of <hi>Europe</hi> have, and daily do fall into, who ſuffer themſelves to be ruled, nay, domineer'd over by Jeſuitical Subtilties and Stra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagems, has determined to keep them thus fettered and deprived from all manner of Commerce, that the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> might not attempt to become Monarchs of Hell, like as they have made themſelves Monarchs of the World. Truly, I found my ſelf all melted into tears at this diſcourſe, giving up my ſelf to weep for the miſery of the People, or rather of Chriſtian Princes, who are ſo contented to ſell their own Liberty, coming ſhort of the wit of Hell, who know much better how to maintain the Liberty and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of their Monarchy, than theſe Princes and People have done theirs. In the mean time, being come back to <hi>Lucifer</hi>'s Palace, the Counſellors being about to take their leaves of me, they all ſaid to me, That now I was returning to the World, I ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member Princes, and endeavour to open their eyes a little better, becauſe the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> had their eyes ever open; and watching to ruine every Monarchy, and ſupport their own, which I promiſed them I would do, ſo I took my leave of them, and as I paſſed out by the back Gate of <hi>Lucifer</hi>'s Palace, into a large Street, I heard ſuch horrid yellings and howlings, as would have ſtruck terrour into the moſt courageous heart: this noiſe ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized me, becauſe I could not imagine theſe to be the <hi>Jeſuits;</hi> but, as I went on a little further, I perceived, upon ſeveral Apartments, a different Banner, which ſeemed to look rather like the Enſign of ſome Secular, than Religious Order.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>What were theſe then? and what Account did the Devil thy Guide give thee of them?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>They were ſeveral Societies of Men, that by Hypocriſie and Deceit, under a Veil of Piety, had cunningly defrauded their Neighbours, and ſeveral Trades-men, under the pretence of honeſty and fair dealing, cheated thoſe that uſed to Trade with them; and upon theſe wretches the Policies of Hell ordered ſevere pains to be inflicted; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, I could eaſily diſtinguiſh them, by obſerving the Banners of every ſeveral Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany. There were <hi>Vintners</hi> and <hi>Ale-Drawers, Mercers</hi> and <hi>Drapirs, Brewers</hi> and <hi>Bakers, Pewterers</hi> and <hi>Goldſmiths, Grocers</hi> and <hi>Dyers,</hi> and above an hundred ſeveral Companies, as well of <hi>Retailers</hi> as <hi>Whole-ſale-men.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>But pray tell me what order is taken with the <hi>Vintners</hi> in Hell, who torture Men upon Earth with their Sophiſtications and baſe Wine? methinks they deſerve ſeverer puniſhments than other Men.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>Oh! the <hi>Devils</hi> know them too well, to let them eſcape due Chaſtiſement; they are a company of Rank Raſcals, and are uſed accordingly: Nay, it has been often de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bated in Hell, to have them ſuffer the ſame torments that are inflicted upon the <hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians, Surgeons, Apothecaries</hi> and <hi>Hang-men,</hi> and to have them turned amongſt them; for in truth they are as great ſlaughter-men, as any of the reſt; but for ſome Politick Reaſons it hath hitherto been forborn; for theſe <hi>Vintners</hi> bring advantage to Hell, and by the fumes of their bad Wine, many Men are exaſperated to commit Murders, and other Villanies, and, by that means, ſend Griſs to the Mill; therefore, for theſe good ſervices, they are allotted an Infernal Habitation to themſelves, being very numerous.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>But did you not go in, and ſee ſome other Trades-men, as well as the <hi>Vintners,</hi> and how they were employed?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>O yes! the <hi>Devils</hi> had prepared work enough for them, as you ſhall hear. The <hi>Mercers</hi> and <hi>Drap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rs</hi> were compelled to fold and unfold Artificial flakes of fire conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually. The <hi>Brewers</hi> were purboiled in their own Coppers, inſtead of Mault. The <hi>Bakers</hi> were thrown into heated Ovens, and taken out again piping hot, but not ſo
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:50939:33"/>well ſavour'd as their new-baked Loves uſed to be. The <hi>Pewterers</hi> and <hi>Goldſmiths</hi> had their ſhare of torment alſo, for all their falſe Allays of Copper, Lead, and other Metals, being ſeparated from the true Gold, Silver and Pewter, were melted and poured down their throats ſcalding hot, to cool their covetous thirſt after unlawful gain. The <hi>Grocers</hi> were kept as reliſhing Pickles, and delicious Sawces, haſht and cookt up by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perienced Daemons, and choicely preſerved as Rarities and Ragouſts for <hi>Lucifer</hi>'s own Table: But, amongſt the variety of Trades-men, I was the moſt of all amazed to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the <hi>Dyers,</hi> who being thrown into their own Caldrons of variety of Colours, came out ſuch motly creatures, that the <hi>Devils</hi> themſelves knew not what to make of them; this very Trade had its different puniſhment; and every particular man had his torments ſuitable to the Cheats he had uſed in his Vocation.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Truly, my old friend, thou haſt given me a notable Account of the <hi>Devil</hi>'s pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings againſt wicked men in the other World; but go on and tell me what hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened afterwards in thy Voyage.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>Whilſt I was adviſing with the Daemon my Comrade, which way to take, I heard a buzzing noiſe, as if ſome great houſe had been on fire; every body ran about in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, and ſome leaped down three or four ſteps to get out the ſooner; ſo I followed the Crowd, and the Devil my Companion with me, but neither of us knew whither we were going; but running with the multitude, and preſſing in the throng, he met one of his Fellow-Devils, and asked him what was the matter; who anſwered him, that <hi>Don Mario,</hi> was juſt now come to Hell, which made every one run to ſee him make his entrance, and give him a kind reception: When I heard this news, I rejoyced, and ſaid within my ſelf, Ha! ha! the Popes Nephews are not far from this place, ſince <hi>Don Mario</hi> is come hither, expecting to meet them: So I ran with all poſſible ſpeed, leſt I ſhould loſe ſuch an opportunity; but I was abſolutely confounded to ſee and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the mighty honours which were done to the ſaid <hi>Don Mario;</hi> for it appeared to be a Solemn Triumph, whilſt <hi>Lucifer</hi> himſelf went out to meet him, and vouchſafed to conduct him alſo, into the Apartment of other kinſmen of the Popes, which were all courted by ſo great a number of Devils, that I dare truly ſay, there was in that one Apartment more of them, than in all the reſt of Hell. This extraordinary honour which I ſaw done to <hi>Don Mario,</hi> and to the other Nephews of Popes, and the Myriads of Devils that I ſaw ſo buſied to ſerve them, moved me to the curioſity of Asking a Dae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, who cryed out with a louder Voice than any elſe, Long live the <hi>Nepotiſmo:</hi> What was the reaſon of all this? who anſwered me thus; That the Devils had much more rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to give greater ſervices to Relations of Popes, than to the reſt of the whole World; that they might not ſin by Ingratitude, becauſe the Nephews of the Popes were the cauſe of ſo many Souls dying in deſpair.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>What did he mean by this? the point ſeems to me a little too ſpeculative.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>Not ſo much as you think; and I am of the opinion he had reaſon enough; for indeed, to ſpeak the truth, the Nephews of the Popes do torment Prelates, Religious men, Prieſts, Fryers, Nuns, Nobles and Plebeans, with Grievances, with Violen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, with ſpightful actions, with taking Offices from the beſt deſerving, to give them to the beſt Chapmen; and with a hundred thouſand of ſuch kind of tricks, by which they reduce the greateſt part of Chriſtians to deſpair, and by that drawing much profit to Hell, who therefore aſſiſt, and honour the Nephews to inflame them the more to Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, now inſtantly after I had ſeen <hi>Don Mario</hi> in Hell, I began to think of returning back to <hi>Rome,</hi> being certain I ſhould find much more quiet there; whereupon I told my Sentiment to the Demon who had bin allotted me for my Companion, who made me fall I cannot tell you how, into a profound ſleep, which when I wakened out of after hours, I found my ſelf in <hi>Rome</hi> where thou ſeeft me. Behold then in what manner my deceaſe and revival hath hapned; but as I have made thee a relation of the affairs in the other World, do you now give me ſome account of what hath paſſed at <hi>Rome,</hi> ſince my departure.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>What reliſh canſt thou have in hearing diſcourſes of this World, after having ſeen
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:50939:33"/>ſuch great things in Hell? Thou oughteſt to be content with the knowledg of things un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known to all, without ſearching into ſuch as are notoriouſly manifeſt to the very ſcum of the People. There is nothing at preſent done at <hi>Rome,</hi> that is not publick throughout the Univerſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>This is a diſeaſe which is now ſo gangren'd that it's paſt all cure; but for me who am juſt come from ſo diſtant a Country, every thing is new, for in that place below, the voices from here above do not penetrate.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>I could tell thee a great many things, my dear <hi>Paſquin,</hi> if the time would permit me, but it growing now late it would be well for us to retire, to avoid thoſe accidents which are apt to befal ſuch as wander up and down in the night, beſides, thou, being juſt now come from ſuch a fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Countrey, ſhouldſt be glad to take ſome reſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>But tell me ſomething however; How did the Election of the New Pope take?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Truly, as we have had hitherto very juſt reaſon to blame the Vices of ſome; now we may, for an Univerſal Conſolation, praiſe the Virtues of others, it being the office and part of a good Chriſtian to praiſe goodneſs, and blame wickedneſs. If the <hi>Roman</hi> people have groaned for theſe 12 years under the miſeries that <hi>Alexander</hi> the Seventh, and the Family of <hi>Chigi</hi> hath plunged them into; now they may enjoy their full felicity acquired by the Election of <hi>Clement</hi> the Ninth, and the introduction of the Family of <hi>Roſpiglioſi</hi> into <hi>Rome.</hi> For 'tis moſt certain, that the Papacy, for the ſafety of Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and the benefit of the <hi>Roman</hi> people, could not have fallen into any other hands, but of Cardinal <hi>Roſpiglioſi</hi>'s, who therefore was pleaſed with great reaſon to inveſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with the name of <hi>Clement,</hi> to ſhew, that all the Zeal of his Soul ſhould be levelled to govern that people with Clemency, who had been lorded over till this hour with Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merciful Tyrannies of others The firſt dawnings of his Papacy ſhined forth in diſcharging the Oppreſſed people of ſo many Taxes, and in placing Juſtice upon the Throne, from whence ſhe had been driven, during the moſt wicked Government of the wretched Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of <hi>Alexander:</hi> And 'tis clearly ſeen, that the Operation of the Holy Spirit directed in the Election of this Perſon, ſince he was ſcarce created Pope, when the languiſhing ſtrength of his body, afflicted with a thouſand indiſpoſitions, began to recover a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed health; inſomuch as that when he was a Cardinal, and had but very little labour and toyl, he was hardly able to walk; now he is ſo indefatigable in all buſineſs, that he feeds as it were on troubles and pains, verifying in himſelf, that holy ſaying of the Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt, <hi>Bonus Paſtor animam ſuam dat pro Ovibus ſuis,</hi> The good Shepherd lays down his life for his Sheep.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>O <hi>Marforio!</hi> 'tis the end is to be prais'd; for <hi>Alexander</hi> alſo began in this manner, and yet in a very ſhort time, from a Shepherd of Souls, he became the Hang-man and Executioner of the people, leaving <hi>Rome</hi> in a worſe ſtate than it was left by <hi>Nero.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>The Corruption of <hi>Alexander</hi> did not come from himſelf, for he was of a nature almoſt incorruptible, at leaſt experimented pure, in his own manners and dealings, for a very long time; but it was derived, and came from the perverſe nature of his Kindred, who never in their lives ſhewed ſo much as an inclination of doing good; but this rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſignifies nothing in the particular of <hi>Clement</hi> the Ninth; for he hath not introduced a <hi>Don Mario</hi> into <hi>Rome,</hi> clothed with a thouſand Humane Imperfections; but a <hi>Don Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>millo,</hi> endowed with Angelical Virtues, a <hi>Don Camillo,</hi> who generouſly ſtrips himſelf of what is his own, to beſtow it on the Poor; not a <hi>Don Mario,</hi> who Tyrannically ſpoils the Poor to clothe himſelf: He hath not introduced a Cardinal <hi>Chigi,</hi> an ignorant young man, unexpert in all Affairs of Government; but a Cardinal <hi>Julius Roſpiglioſi,</hi> a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of infinite worth, and a Capacity balanced to maintain the Quality of a Favourite Nephew, having by the height of prudence, and perſuaſion of his Uncle, renounced the Title of <hi>Cardinal Padrone,</hi> declaring he would much rather ſerve than domineer. He hath not introduced a <hi>Don Auguſtine,</hi> who, as ſoon as he came into <hi>Rome,</hi> ſet himſelf to abuſe and deal hardly with the <hi>Roman</hi> Nobility; but a <hi>Don Vicenzo,</hi> who contemning the eaſe, ſloth and ſolaces of <hi>Rome,</hi> hath eſteemed it a greater Glory to go meet with Death from the Infidels, than to enjoy in the Court that Vanicy's idle breath which the
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:50939:34"/>Nephews of other Popes did ſo delight in. In fine, from this Papacy there is nothing to be expected but univerſal happineſs and good, the Pope and the Nephews both ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly endeavouring it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>God be praiſed! It is fit truly that a great Tempeſt ſhould be ſucceeded by a great Calm; the people then is contented with this Pope.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Moſt infinitely contented, and the Prelates alſo; tho 'tis true, that amongſt theſe there are ſome Male-contents may be found; for, 'tis the great miſery of <hi>Rome,</hi> that there are more prelates, than Dignities to be diſpenced; I ſpeak of conſiderable Dignities; and every one believe themſelves moſt meritorious, without any excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, whence 'tis impoſſible to ſatisfie one, without diſguſting another: yet the Pope nevertheleſs with the higheſt prudence, ſtrives to oblige ſome with Favours, others with good words, and all his Kindred do the ſame, being every one of them of ſweet and complaiſant diſpoſitions.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>This is one of the greateſt happineſſes that could come to <hi>Rome,</hi> being continually in time paſt, ill treated both in word and actions.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Amongſt other things, the Nephews do not appear to be ſo greedy of Uſurping over the Pope, as the other Nephews to this day have been, which whether they feared to have loſt him, or whether they feared, that being much frequented by others, their inward corruptions, by that means, ſhould come to be revealed. They kept him hid, as it were, in ſuch a ſtrange manner, that he was with much difficulty permitted to give Audiences to publick Miniſters: But this reaſon doth not prevail now at this preſent time, whilſt the Pope, knowing himſelf to be truly the Univerſal Father in deſpight of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wicked Hereticks that deny it, hath given expreſs order unto all his Family even to the meaneſt, that they ſhould introduce every perſon that will come into the publick Audience, which he gives once a week, receiving every one with a paternal affection, who praiſe God as they return to their houſes, that hath vouchſafed to give them a Pope, who both deſerves, and worthily bears the name of Univerſal Father.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>Really I do not know now the other Popes could pretend to the Title of Univerſal Father, if they made themſelves ſo only in particular to their Nephews. Let us therefore give thanks to the Lord our God, who hath been pleaſed to give Chriſtianity an Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Father; but how treats he with the Crowned Heads, and other Princes?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>With the very ſame difintereſtedneſs, which he uſed whilſt he was a Cardinal, walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in a very even path, to give no Jealouſie either to one body or another; ſo that every one ſees themſelves obliged to confeſs with truth, that he is the Univerſal Father. He is extreamly inclined to the Peace and Tranquility of Chriſtendom; whence he uſes all means imaginable to make Peace again between <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spain;</hi> and every day recommends unto the publick Miniſters their labouring and ſtriving with their ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt Induſtry to preſerve a good Union and Correſpondency betwixt thoſe Princes; his Paſtoral Zeal is known by the Ardour that he ſhews in ſuccouring the <hi>Venetians,</hi> who ſo long a time have fought with ſo great Glory againſt the common Enemy of the Church of Chriſt; nay, not being content to ſuccour them with the Patrimony of St. <hi>Peter</hi> given by himſelf, he ſolicits the Princes of Chriſtendom daily with reiterated Intreaties, who can do no leſs, ſeeing ſo great an Example in the Pope, but open their treaſures, and aſſiſt that Republick liberally, who is as the Bulwork of the Freedom of the Chriſtian Church. In fine, the Hereticks themſelves confeſs, that this Pope came from Heaven, not being ſoely Elected by Men; his ways being directed altogether to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Honour of God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>What. does he then ſhew himſelf ſo wholly intent on the publick good? But what ſay his Relations then? are not they jealous, that what he ſpends for the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of the publick good, diminiſhes the advancement of their particular Family?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>The Kindred of the Pope cannot indeed complain againſt him; neither can the Pope complain againſt his Kindred; for they are of a nature eaſie to be contented, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving not hitherto ſhewed themſelves greedy, altho' many opportunities have been of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered unto them; tho' always before the Nephews of the Popes have ever ſhewed as if
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:50939:34"/>it were the temperature of their Nature. And Pope <hi>Clement</hi> alſo loves his Nephews as much as one ought to love the Body; and the Church as much as one ought to love the Soul; which, to ſpeak plainly, ſhews his heart is much more ſet upon the good and advantage of the Church, than that of his Kindred; he concedes thoſe Emo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luments to his Nephews, and furniſhes them with thoſe profits which proceed from thoſe Dignities and Offices which the Church by Antient Cuſtom did uſe to diſpence to the Kindred of the Popes, but he will not ſuffer them to burthen the people at all; neither are they the leaſt inclined to it, and moſt particularly <hi>Don Camillo,</hi> who is ſo ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous, that he had rather die poor, and leave a good name, than rich with an ill fame behind him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>The <hi>Chigi</hi> were not ſo ſcrupulous, eſpecially <hi>Don Mario</hi>'s Lordſhip.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Let's ſpeak no more of the graces of <hi>Don Mario;</hi> for I tell thee, the Government of the <hi>Chigi</hi>'s was the Government of the Devils, and that of the <hi>Roſpiglioſi</hi>'s a Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Angels; the <hi>Roſpiglioſi</hi>'s are delighted in ſtudying the common good of the people, whereas the <hi>Chigi</hi>'s grew fat with their blood and deſtruction. If the Nephews of other Popes had been content, as the <hi>Roſpiglioſi</hi>'s are, to have enjoyed the uſual Rents of thoſe Offices and Charges which are fitting in all reſpects for the Popes Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phews, without tyrannizing over the miſerable people, by ſo many Taxes impoſed upon them, the Church undoubtedly would have been much more peopled with Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks; and Hereſie would have been deſtroy'd by the very Hereticks. And there would not either have been ſo many infamous Manuſcripts kept in <hi>Rome,</hi> nor ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Satyrical Books printed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>But on the mention of Books, prethee is there any new ones come out ſince I was ſeen here?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>If I would name all the Books, and all the Pamphlets which have come to light lately, there would be certainly ſuch a vaſt Catalogue of Books, as would ſwell into a Volume bigger than the Book of Martyrs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>Who the Devil ſhites all theſe Scriblers? and where do they inhabit?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>I know not that; but it's certain, that as ſoon as any Gentleman that is a ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger comes into <hi>Rome,</hi> an innumerable company of black Coats, out at the elbows, come about him, all ſtriving to faſten upon him their ſatyrical and infamous Manuſcripts, which they ſell at good penny-worths, applying all their wits to feed their bodies, tho' to the damnation of their ſouls; and, becauſe the moſt part of ſtrangers of Quality that come to <hi>Rome</hi> are Hereticks, they, by this means, return back into their own Countreys loaded with Manuſcripts, and they impart them to Book-ſellers who are their Friends, who finally as Enemies to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> make no ſcruple to Print what the <hi>Romans</hi> themſelves are not aſhamed to write. But the greateſt ſhame of all is, that the very Hereticks are more ſcrupulous than the Catholicks themſelves, the Catholicks writing ſuch very infamous things, that they bluſh to read them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>I know not what to ſay to it, but pray God to pardon thoſe who give the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>'Tis the Corruption of the Age in which we live, whilſt men have ſuch depraved Guſts, that they know not, or rather will not read any other works but Satyrs, as wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as they are infamous, and thoſe who have no other way of living, but by belying either themſelves, or at leaſt their own Conſciences, writing any thing that will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light the Men of the Age.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>But how comes <hi>Rome</hi> only to be the Mother of all theſe Satyrical Books? Is it becauſe the <hi>Romans</hi> have leſs Conſcience, or more leiſure than other people? For my part I know not what to make of it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>'Tis becauſe they are more ſly and cunning than others; for theſe things require twice the wit and ſubtilty of others: And yet if thou didſt know how much alſo others writ, thou wouldſt not lay all the blame on the <hi>Romans:</hi> for in <hi>France</hi> and <hi>England</hi> it ſelf, but the two laſt years there have been Printed above ſeventy Books all Satyrical, againſt the chief of that Kingdom, and ſome of them ſo filthy, that they nauſeate the
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:50939:35"/>Reader; tho' tis very true, that the <hi>French</hi> have a peculiar dexterity in knowing how to Jeſt with Satyriſm, taking it abſolutely for a kind of Gallantry of wit, and the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt revenge is to ſcorn it. Of <hi>Spain</hi> then I ſay nothing, becauſe Satyrs there run as the Poſt-horſes; in every corner there is one to be had; but the worſt is, that there are no Satyrs ſo ſharp as thoſe which come from a <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Pen, by reaſon that that Nation being very pious and devout, when they be corrupted, they become venom and poyſon, becauſe the corruption of the beſt is ever the worſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>If this be ſo, then we need not wonder that the <hi>Romans</hi> are ſo very skilful in Compoſing Satyrs; for they can be good or bad according to Time, Place or Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>For my part, I believe the <hi>Romans</hi> do not write out of malice, but out of pure neceſſity, and ſtab out of revenge; for, 'tis too true, that the moſt part of thoſe who ſell Manuſcripts in <hi>Rome,</hi> are certain neceſſitous Prieſts, and certain diſcontented Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers, theſe being ſpurred on by revenge, and the others by want; and becauſe the <hi>Julio,</hi> which is given them for ſaying Maſs, is not ſufficient to live upon, they give themſelves up to doing things, which perhaps are contrary to their very nature; and therefore every thing they do looks ſupernatural.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>But what Books are come out ſince the time that I have ſeen thee? name me one.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>There is the <hi>Putaniſmo</hi> as jolly in the invention, as it is foul and infamous in its matter, and which laſhes the Court moſt, where it was made and compoſed. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, there is <hi>Mercury turned Poſt-boy,</hi> and whipping and laſhing very hard. There is alſo the <hi>Monarchy of</hi> Spain <hi>in its Riſe and Declenſion,</hi> which is a very pleaſant Treatiſe in form of Comedy, ſet off with a curious Prologue, which ſmites the <hi>Spaniards</hi> hip and thigh: Yet, to ſpeak the truth, they may make ſome good uſe of it, tho' the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor was none of their Friends. Moreover, there is <hi>the Model of the Jeſuitical Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> with an Inſtruction to Princes of the manner by which the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> govern them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to advance their Society to a perfect Monarchy, which touches them to the quick; eſpecially an <hi>Amphibological</hi> and <hi>Perſuaſive Letter of a</hi> Jeſuit <hi>to a Gentleman his Diſciple,</hi> with <hi>the Gentleman Diſciples Anſwer to his Maſter the</hi> Jeſuits <hi>Letter, The Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binet of Princes,</hi> conſiſting of four Concerts, that ſnip and piece every thing as the toy takes them. Then the <hi>Speaking Animals</hi> is alſo to be ſeen, a very rigorous piece, that ſufficiently ſhews it was produced by ſome learned head who ſpeaks not like an Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal, tho' he treats and handles all like Beaſts, as if there was never another Man but himſelf. There are <hi>ſundry Relations from ſeveral Princes Courts,</hi> which Treatiſes ſeem licked over with Honey, but have Gall in their Entrails.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>Alas! all theſe are ſmall pieces, the Manuſcripts of which I have often ſeen.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>May be ſo; but there is alſo the <hi>Cardinaliſmo,</hi> which is divided into three Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumes; and, for my part, I believe there never was any thing ſeen which was more disjoynted without beginning or end, without reaſon or foundation, only a meer heap of Lies and Railing.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>It was not then done by the Author of the <hi>Nepotiſmo;</hi> for that was not ſo abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>The ſtile was like enough to it, both being but ill Compoſed, and to ſay truth, groundleſs; yet nevertheleſs the <hi>Nepotiſmo</hi> hath ſomething that ſparkles at the firſt ſight, but as for the <hi>Cardinaliſmo,</hi> it is not poſſible to relate the abſurdities that are in it; and I know not how the Devil any Man can be found, that will take the pains to read it, being ſo far from reaſon, and carrying a Lye in every ſentence of it. Were it a plain Satyr, it might paſs, but the miſchief is, that it corrupts all Hiſtory, turning and bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it into a formal Satyriſm.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>Is it not like the <hi>Juſt Balances of Cardinals,</hi> which is full of a thouſand filthy im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purities?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Juſt Balances,</hi> tho' Satyrical, hath ſomething agreeable in them, becauſe they are a ſort of gueſſing or divination of what they ſay; but the <hi>Cardinaliſmo</hi> praiſes
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:50939:35"/>thoſe Cardinals it ought to blame, and blames thoſe it ought to praiſe, giving and taking Offices and Dignities at its own pleaſure. In fine, if it was ſaid of the other, that there were as many Sentences as there were Words, of this it may be ſaid, there are as many Fooleries as there are Words.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>It will then have a great Effect upon inquiſitive Men reading it, it will ſpoil the humour of reading ſuch kind of Books; but is there no more?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>There is the <hi>Conclaves of all the Popes,</hi> which ſtinks extreamly, but Hiſtory makes it ſo; and tho' they be but fragments of things long ſince paſt at <hi>Rome,</hi> yet being now all gathered together, they very much move the curioſity at this time of many perſons to read them. But above all, there is a little exquiſite piece that much pleaſes me, which is called <hi>The Counts Defence of the Rights of Princes,</hi> where a Marquiſs is feigned ſpeaking Satyrically againſt the Chief Potentates of <hi>Italy,</hi> and all <hi>Europe;</hi> and the Count refuting the Marquiſs's Arguments, maintains the Princes; all which is contained in Eight Dialogues. In the firſt is diſcourſed the Advantages that Spies bring unto Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: In the ſecond is diſcourſed all the concerns of the Duke of <hi>Crequi,</hi> Ambaſſador of his Moſt Chriſtian Majeſty, his Negotiations and Tranſactions in <hi>Rome,</hi> and of the heads he publiſhed touching his Pretenſions: In the third is diſcourſed the Intereſts about <hi>Portugal,</hi> ſhewing how the Pope is obliged by Political Reaſons to admit them the Nominations of their Churches: In the fourth the King of <hi>England</hi>'s Marriage with the <hi>Infanta of Portugal</hi> is diſcourſed of: In the fifth is diſcourſed the Peace made by the <hi>Emperour</hi> with the <hi>Turks:</hi> In the ſixth the King of <hi>Spain</hi> is praiſed for yielding the Precedency of his Embaſſadors, to the Embaſſadors of the Moſt Chriſtian King, with the Reaſons for it: In the ſeventh the Prudence of the King of <hi>France</hi> is diſcourſed in buying the Signiory of the Duke of <hi>Lorain,</hi> ſhewing that he did no body any Injury: And in the eighth it's proved, that the <hi>Venetians</hi> did not do ill but well, to continue the War againſt the <hi>Turk.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>The piece ought to be profitable, treating of Noble Subjects, and adapted to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie curioſity.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>There is nothing better, Compoſed, and more Political, but thoſe who are prickt do not approve it, yet they cannot forbear to read it, finding Honey mixt amongſt the Stings.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>When Satyrs are well Compoſed, the very Stings themſelves are ſweet.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>I believe at the preſent they are beginning to leave off Satyriſing, at leaſt againſt <hi>Rome;</hi> for 'tis certain, if they do not ceaſe now, they will never ceaſe at all.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>But why wilt thou have this happen at preſent? what reaſon induces thee to believe ſo?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe we are now in the Age of Clemency, and Chriſtian Religion is ruled by a Head who is all <hi>Clement</hi> in effect, much more then in the name of it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>Truly there is nothing that humbles, and brings back the moſt ſtrayed perſons to Agreement, ſo well as Clemency: Therefore if the Chief Biſhop will practiſe that, as thou ſayeſt he does, he will gain much more than many others have done who have uſed Violence.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>God pardon thoſe who have ſo invenom'd the Pens of others, that they have been very often extream cruel againſt that Mother who feeds them. The good Religious Men cannot ſuffer any injury from the pricks and ſtings which are given to wicked ones. They who write have no deſign to offend thoſe Eccleſiaſticks, who live ſoberly and holily, and with the greateſt Edification poſſible towards the people, of which ſort there is an infinite number, as there is likewiſe an infinite number alſo of thoſe, who forgetting the Obligation due to their Vows, rebel againſt their very Superiors; but the good Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious cannot poſſibly fear receiving any detriment in their own Reputations, by the Satyrs againſt others, tho' they ſhould have come from Hell it ſelf. God hath left us the example of poor <hi>Lazarus,</hi> and the <hi>rich Glutton</hi> before our Eyes, that we might ſlie from the <hi>rich Glutton,</hi> and follow <hi>Lazarus,</hi> who was ſet before us that we might follow his ſteps: Therefore it is neceſſary ſometimes to expoſe thoſe that are addicted to Vice, to put them in mind of their duty; but this does not reflect upon good Men, but on the contrary, makes their Virtues more eſtimable.</p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="64" facs="tcp:50939:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>The truth is, were there no diſtinction made in the Church between the good and the bad, the virtuous and the vicious, between vile corrupted Popes, and thoſe that are not ſo, between Cardinals deſerving that high Charge, and thoſe that merit a Halter, between truly devout and hypocritical Chriſtians, the Church muſt of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity ſoon fall to ruine, ſhould we extol thoſe, who by their wicked examples rather ſcandalize their Neighbours, than endeavour to preſerve the honour and reverence due to Religion? Should we attribute to ſuch men the praiſes they only deſerve, who ſweat and labour, and undergo a thouſand hardſhips, not only to ſanctifie themſelves, but to beget a reſpect and awe to Religion it ſelf? It would be a thing impious and inhumane, if the lazy and negligent Miniſter may pretend to a recompence equal to the pious and laborious; what have they to do but to ſtudy to become like the others? 'Tis better therefore to publiſh the Vices of lewd men, that either they being made aſhamed, may turn from their wicked courſes, and enter into the paths of Virtue; or at leaſt that by this means the holineſs of the juſt may ſhine brighter.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>The miſchief is, that thoſe wretches finding a ſting in their Conſciences, wince and kick at reproof, like a Horſe that has a Nettle clapt under his Tail, or a skittiſh Jade when he feels the Spur.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>Well bred Horſes that go on readily in their way, are never diſquieted with Spurs, tho' the Horſe-men ride with them never ſo cloſe to their ſides.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>'Tis very true indeed, that many do abſtain from doing ill, rather for fear of being reproached by the World, than any true love of God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>Perhaps there will be no more neceſſity of pricking and ſpurring to provoke ill people to do well, and turn from the ways of wickedneſs, not to wrong the Clemency that thou ſpeakeſt of, which I alſo highly commend, as a moſt neceſſary Expedient in this Age, where we ſee the nature of Men ſcorns and diſdains in their very Souls the Violences of others.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>The Head ever governs all the other Members, inſomuch that whilſt the Church had virtuous and holy Popes, and zealous of the Salvation of the People, the other Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious alſo were ſo many Examples of Virtue, whence we ought to hope that God ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been pleaſed to bleſs us at this time by ſending his Church a Pope enriched with ſo many Virtues, who, like a Pellican, tears out his own bowels, for the love of his people, the other Prelates and Religious who are Members of the Church will be animated unto good, and by the Example of the Head, who is ſo good, will edifie the people, and do their duties in all virtuous and holy works; ſo all Satyriſm will ceaſe, and all Pens will be employed with the utmoſt Abilities to magnifie thoſe good and religious Eccleſiaſticks, which they formerly reviled for being wicked.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>Then we ſhall not need to talk any longer, my dear <hi>Marforio,</hi> but turn our Eves from thoſe wicked Objects, promiſing unto God for the time to come, to praiſe thoſe good Religious ſo much the heartilier, for having formerly blamed the bad ones.</p>
            </sp>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="map">
            <pb facs="tcp:50939:37"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>map of europe</figDesc>
                  <head>EUROPEA Deſcriptio Nova Impenjis <date>Annae SEILE 1663</date>
                  </head>
                  <byline>Ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>Vanohan ſculp</byline>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
